<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='lib/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!--<?rfc header="Documentation"?>-->
<!--?rfc private="RFC2629 through XSLT"?-->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no"?>
<?rfc editing="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<!-- <?rfc topblock="no"?> -->
<!--<?rfc strict="no"?>-->

<rfc category="info"
    ipr="trust200902"
    docName="draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-02"
    >
    <front>
        <title abbrev="HPACK">HPACK - Header Compression for HTTP/2.0 </title>

        <author initials="R." surname="Peon" fullname="Roberto Peon">
            <organization>Google, Inc</organization>
            <address>
                <email>fenix@google.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author initials="H." surname="Ruellan" fullname="Hervé Ruellan">
            <organization>Canon CRF</organization>
            <address>
                <email>herve.ruellan@crf.canon.fr</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date month="August" year="2013"/>
        <area>Applications</area>
        <workgroup>HTTPbis Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>HTTP</keyword>
        <keyword>Header</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document describes HPACK, a format adapted to efficiently
                represent HTTP headers in the context of HTTP/2.0.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">

            <t>
                This document describes HPACK, a format adapted to efficiently
                represent HTTP headers in the context of HTTP/2.0.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Overview" anchor="overview">
            <t>
                In HTTP/1.X, HTTP headers, which are necessary for the
                functioning of the protocol, are transmitted with no
                transformations. Unfortunately, the amount of redundancy in
                both the keys and the values of these headers is high, and is
                the cause of increased latency on lower bandwidth links. This
                indicates that an alternate more compact encoding for headers
                would be beneficial to latency, and that is what is proposed
                here.
            </t>

           <t>
                As shown by <xref target="SPDY">SPDY</xref>, Deflate
                compresses HTTP very effectively. However, the use of a
                compression scheme which allows for arbitrary matches against
                the previously encoded data (such as Deflate) exposes users to
                security issues.

                In particular, the compression of sensitive data, together
                with other data controlled by an attacker, may lead to leakage
                of that sensitive data, even when the resultant bytes are
                transmitted over an encrypted channel.
            </t>

            <t>
                Another consideration is that processing and memory costs of a
                compressor such as Deflate may also be too high for some
                classes of devices, for example when doing forward or reverse
                proxying.
            </t>

            <section title="Outline">
                <t>
                    The HTTP header encoding described in this document
                    is based on a header table that map (name, value) pairs to index values.
                    This scheme is believed to be safe for all known attacks
                    against the compression context today.  Header tables are
                    incrementally updated during the HTTP/2.0 session.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The encoder is responsible for deciding which headers to
                    insert as new entries in the header table.  The
                    decoder then does exactly what the encoder prescribes,
                    ending in a state that exactly matches the encoder's
                    state.  This enables decoders to remain simple and
                    understand a wide variety of encoders.
                </t>
                <t>
                    As two consecutive sets of headers often have headers in
                    common, each set of headers is coded as a difference from
                    the previous set of headers. The goal is to only encode
                    the changes (headers present in one of the set and not in
                    the other) between the two sets of headers.
                </t>
                <t>
                    An example illustrating the use of these different
                    mechanisms to represent headers is available in <xref
                        target="example"/>.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Header Encoding" anchor="header.encoding">
            <section title="Encoding Concepts" anchor="encoding.concepts">
                <t>
                    The encoding and decoding of headers relies on some
                    components and concepts. The set of components used form
                    an encoding context.
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Header Table:">
                            The header table (see <xref
                                target="header.table"/>) is a component used
                            to associate headers to index values.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Reference Set:">
                            The reference set (see <xref
                                target="reference.set"/>) is a component
                            containing a group of headers used as a reference
                            for the differential encoding of a new set of
                            headers.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Header Set:">
                            A header set (see <xref target="header.set"/>) is
                            a group of headers that are encoded jointly. A
                            complete set of key-value pairs as encoded in
                            an HTTP request or response is a header set.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Header Representation:">
                            A header can be represented in encoded form either
                            as a literal or as an index (see <xref
                                target="header.representation"/>). The indexed
                            representation is based on the header table.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Header Emission:">
                            When decoding a set of headers, some operations
                            emit a header (see <xref
                                target="header.emission"/>). An emitted header
                            is added to the set of headers that form the HTTP 
                            request or response. Once emitted, a header can't
                            be removed from the set of headers.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>

                <section title="Encoding Context" anchor="encoding.context">
                    <t>
                        The set of components used to encode or decode a
                        header set form an encoding context: an encoding
                        context contains a header table and a reference set.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Using HTTP, messages are exchanged between a client
                        and a server in both direction. To keep the encoding
                        of headers in each direction independent from the
                        other direction, there is one encoding context for
                        each direction.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The headers contained in a PUSH_PROMISE frame sent by
                        a server to a client are encoded within the same
                        context as the headers contained in the HEADERS frame
                        corresponding to a response sent from the server to
                        the client.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Table" anchor="header.table">
                    <t>
                        A header table consists of an ordered list of (name,
                        value) pairs. The first entry of a header table is
                        assigned the index 0.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A header can be represented by an entry of the header
                        table if they match. A header and an entry match if
                        both their name and their value match. A header name
                        and an entry name match if they are equal using a
                        character-based, <spanx>case insensitive</spanx>
                        comparison (the case insensitive comparison is used
                        because HTTP header names are defined in a case
                        insensitive way). A header value and an entry value
                        match if they are equal using a character-based,
                        <spanx>case sensitive</spanx> comparison.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Generally, the header table will not contain duplicate
                        entries. However, implementations MUST be prepared to
                        accept duplicates without signalling an error.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Initially, a header table contains a list of common
                        headers. Two initial lists of header are provided in
                        <xref target="initial.headers"/>. One list is for
                        headers transmitted from a client to a server, the
                        other for the reverse direction.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A header table is modified by either adding a new
                        entry at the end of the table, or by replacing an
                        existing entry.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The encoder decides how to update the header table and
                        as such can control how much memory is used by the
                        header table. To limit the memory requirements on the
                        decoder side, the header table size is bounded (see
                        the SETTINGS_MAX_BUFFER_SIZE in <xref
                            target="parameter.negotiation"/>).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The size of an entry is the sum of its name's length
                        in bytes (as defined in <xref
                            target="header.name.representation" />), of its
                        value's length in bytes (<xref
                            target="string.literal.representation" />) and of
                        32 bytes. The 32 bytes are an accounting for the entry
                        structure overhead. For example, an entry structure
                        using two 64-bits pointers to reference the name and
                        the value and the entry, and two 64-bits integer for
                        counting the number of references to these name and
                        value would use 32 bytes.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The size of a header table is the sum of the size of
                        its entries.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Reference Set" anchor="reference.set">
                    <t>
                        A reference set is defined as an unordered set of
                        references to entries of the header table.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The initial reference set is the empty set.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The reference set is updated during the processing of
                        a set of headers.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Using the differential encoding, a header that is not
                        present in the reference set can be encoded either
                        with an indexed representation (if the header is
                        present in the header table), or with a literal
                        representation (if the header is not present in the
                        header table).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A header that is to be removed from the reference set
                        is encoded with an indexed representation.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header set" anchor="header.set">
                    <t>
                        A header set is a group of header fields that are
                        encoded as a whole. Each header field is a (name,
                        value) pair.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A header set is encoded using an ordered list of zero
                        or more header representations. All the header
                        representations describing a header set a grouped into
                        a header block.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Representation"
                    anchor="header.representation">
                    <t>
                        A header can be represented either as a literal or as
                        an index.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="Literal Representation:">
                                A literal representation defines a new
                                header. The header name is represented either
                                literally or as a reference to an entry of the
                                header table. The header value is represented
                                literally.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                Three different literal representations are provided:
                                <list style="symbols">
                                    <t>
                                        A literal representation that does not
                                        add the header to the header table
                                        (see <xref
                                            target="literal.header.without.indexing"/>).
                                    </t>
                                    <t>
                                        A literal representation that
                                        adds the header at the end of the
                                        header table
                                        (see <xref
                                            target="literal.header.with.incremental.indexing"/>).
                                    </t>
                                    <t>
                                        A literal representation that
                                        uses the header to replace an existing
                                        entry of the header table
                                        (see <xref
                                            target="literal.header.with.substitution.indexing"/>).
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="Indexed Representation:">
                                The indexed representation defines a header as
                                a reference in the header table (see <xref
                                    target="indexed.header.representation"/>).
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Emission" anchor="header.emission">
                    <t>
                        The emission of header is the process of adding a
                        header to the current set of headers. Once an header
                        is emitted, it can't be removed from the current set
                        of headers.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The concept of header emission allows a decoder to
                        know when it can pass a header safely to a higher
                        level on the receiver side. This allows a decoder to
                        be implemented in a streaming way, and as such to only
                        keep in memory the header table and the reference set.
                        With such an implementation, the amount of memory used
                        by the decoder is bounded, even in presence of a very
                        large set of headers. The management of memory for
                        handling very large sets of headers can therefore be
                        deferred to the application, which may be able to emit
                        the header to the wire and thus free up memory
                        quickly.
                    </t>
                </section>

            </section>

            <section title="Header Set Processing"
                anchor="header.set.processing">

                <t>
                    The processing of an encoded header set to obtain a list
                    of headers is defined in this section.  To ensure a
                    correct decoding of a header set, a decoder MUST obey the
                    following rules.
                </t>

                <section title="Header Representation Processing"
                    anchor="header.representation.processing">
                    <t>
                        All the header representations contained in a header
                        block are processed in the order in which they are
                        presented, as specified below.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        An <spanx>indexed representation</spanx> corresponding
                        to an entry <spanx>not present</spanx> in the
                        reference set entails the following actions:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The header corresponding to the entry is
                                emitted.</t>
                            <t>The entry is added to the reference set.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        An <spanx>indexed representation</spanx> corresponding
                        to an entry <spanx>present</spanx> in the
                        reference set entails the following actions:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The entry is removed from the reference set.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A <spanx>literal representation</spanx> that is
                        <spanx>not added</spanx> to the header table entails
                        the following action:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The header is emitted.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A <spanx>literal representation</spanx> that is
                        <spanx>added</spanx> to the header table entails
                        the following actions:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The header is emitted.</t>
                            <t>The header is added to the header table, at the
                                location defined by the representation.</t>
                            <t>The new entry is added to the reference set.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Reference Set Emission"
                    anchor="reference.set.emission">
                    <t>
                        Once all the representations contained in a header
                        block have been processed, the headers that are in
                        common with the previous header set are emitted,
                        during the reference set emission.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        For the reference set emission, each header contained
                        in the reference set that has not been emitted during
                        the processing of the header block is emitted.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Set Completion"
                    anchor="header.set.completion">
                    <t>
                        Once all of the header representations have been
                        processed, and the remaining items in the reference
                        set have been emitted, the header set is complete.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Table Management"
                    anchor="header.table.management">
                    <t>
                        The header table can be modified by either adding a
                        new entry to it or by replacing an existing one.
                        Before doing such a modification, it has to be ensured
                        that the header table size will stay lower than or
                        equal to the SETTINGS_MAX_BUFFER_SIZE limit (see <xref
                            target="parameter.negotiation"/>).  To achieve
                        this, repeatedly, the first entry of the header table
                        is removed, until enough space is available for the
                        modification.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A consequence of removing one or more entries at the
                        beginning of the header table is that the remaining
                        entries are renumbered. The first entry of the header
                        table is always associated to the index 0.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        When the modification of the header table is the
                        replacement of an existing entry, the replaced entry
                        is the one indicated in the literal representation
                        before any entry is removed from the header table. If
                        the entry to be replaced is removed from the header
                        table when performing the size adjustment, the
                        replacement entry is inserted at the beginning of the
                        header table.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The addition of a new entry with a size greater than
                        the SETTINGS_MAX_BUFFER_SIZE limit causes all the
                        entries from the header table to be dropped and the
                        new entry not to be added to the header table. The
                        replacement of an existing entry with a new entry with
                        a size greater than the SETTINGS_MAX_BUFFER_SIZE has
                        the same consequences.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Specific Use Cases"
                    anchor="specific.use.cases">
                    <t>
                        Three occurrences of the same indexed representation,
                        corresponding to an entry not present in the reference
                        set, emit the associated header twice:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>
                                The first occurrence emits the header a first
                                time and adds the corresponding entry to the
                                reference set.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                The second occurrence removes the header's
                                entry from the reference set.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                The third occurrence emits the header a second
                                time and adds again its entry to the reference
                                set.
                            </t>
                        </list>
                        This allows for headers sets which include duplicate
                        header entries to be encoded efficiently and faithfully.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The first occurrence of the indexed representation can
                        be replaced by a literal representation creating an
                        entry for the header.
                    </t>
                </section>

            </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Detailed Format" anchor="detailed.format">
            <section title="Low-level representations" anchor="string.encoding">
                <section title="Integer representation" anchor="integer.representation">
                    <t>
                        Integers are used to represent name indexes, pair
                        indexes or string lengths. To allow for optimized
                        processing, an integer representation always finishes
                        at the end of a byte.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        An integer is represented in two parts: a prefix that
                        fills the current byte and an optional list of bytes
                        that are used if the integer value does not fit in the
                        prefix.  The number of bits of the prefix (called N)
                        is a parameter of the integer representation.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The N-bit prefix allows filling the current byte.  If
                        the value is small enough (strictly less than 2^N-1),
                        it is encoded within the N-bit prefix.  Otherwise all
                        the bits of the prefix are set to 1 and the value is
                        encoded using an <eref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Variable-length_quantity">
                            unsigned variable length integer</eref>
                        representation.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The algorithm to represent an integer I is as follows:
                        <figure><artwork type = "inline">
If I &lt; 2^N - 1, encode I on N bits
Else
    encode 2^N - 1 on N bits
    I = I - (2^N - 1)
    While I >= 128
         Encode (I % 128 + 128) on 8 bits
         I = I / 128
    encode (I) on 8 bits
                        </artwork></figure>
                    </t>

                    <section title="Example 1: Encoding 10 using a 5-bit prefix"
                        anchor="integer.representation.example1">
                        <t>
                            The value 10 is to be encoded with a 5-bit prefix.
                            <list style="symbols">
                                <t>
                                    10 is less than 31 (= 2^5 - 1) and is
                                    represented using the 5-bit prefix.
                                </t>
                            </list>
                        </t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| X | X | X | 0 | 1 | 0 | 1 | 0 |   10 stored on 5 bits
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Example 2: Encoding 1337 using a 5-bit prefix"
                        anchor="integer.representation.example2">
                        <t>
                            The value I=1337 is to be encoded with a 5-bit
                            prefix.
                            <list>
                                <t>1337 is greater than 31 (= 2^5 - 1).</t>
                                <t>
                                    <list>
                                        <t>The 5-bit prefix is filled with its
                                            max value (31).</t>
                                    </list>
                                </t>
                                <t>I = 1337 - (2^5 - 1) = 1306.</t>
                                <t>
                                    <list>
                                        <t>I (1306) is greater than or equal
                                            to 128, the while loop body
                                            executes:</t>
                                        <t>
                                            <list>
                                                <t>I % 128 == 26</t>
                                                <t>26 + 128 == 154</t>
                                                <t>154 is encoded in 8 bits as:
                                                    10011010</t>
                                                <t>I is set to 10 (1306 / 128 ==
                                                    10)</t>
                                                <t>I is no longer greater than or
                                                    equal to 128, the while loop
                                                    terminates.</t>
                                            </list>
                                        </t>
                                        <t>
                                            I, now 10, is encoded on 8 bits as: 00001010
                                        </t>
                                    </list>
                                </t>

                                <t>The process ends.</t>
                            </list>

                        </t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| X | X | X | 1 | 1 | 1 | 1 | 1 |   Prefix = 31, I = 1306
| 1 | 0 | 0 | 1 | 1 | 0 | 1 | 0 |   1306>=128, encode(154), I = 1306/128
| 0 | 0 | 0 | 0 | 1 | 0 | 1 | 0 |   10&lt;128, encode(10), done
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </section>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Name Representation" anchor="header.name.representation">

                  <t>
                      Header names are sequences of ASCII characters that
                      MUST conform to the following header-name ABNF
                      construction:
                  </t>

                  <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  LOWERALPHA = %x61-7A
  header-char = "!" / "#" / "$" / "%" / "&" / "'" /
                "*" / "+" / "-" / "." / "^" / "_" /
                "`" / "|" / "~" / DIGIT / LOWERALPHA
  header-name = [":"] 1*header-char
                  ]]></artwork></figure>

                  <t>
                      They are encoded in two parts:
                      <list style="numbers">
                          <t>The length of the text, defined as the number of
                              octets of storage required to store the text,
                              represented as a <xref
                                  target="integer.representation">
                              variable-length-quantity </xref>.
                          </t>
                        <t>The specific sequence of ASCII octets</t>
                      </list>
                  </t>

                </section>

                <section title="Header Value Representation" anchor="string.literal.representation">
                    <t>
                        Header values are encoded as sequences of UTF-8 encoded
                        text. They are encoded in two parts:
                        <list style="numbers">
                          <t>The length of the text, defined as the number of
                              octets of storage required to store the text,
                              represented as a <xref
                                  target="integer.representation">
                              variable-length-quantity </xref>.
                          </t>
                          <t>
                              The specific sequence of octets representing the
                              UTF-8 text.
                          </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      Invalid UTF-8 octet sequences, "over-long" UTF-8
                      encodings, and UTF-8 octets that represent
                      invalid Unicode Codepoints MUST NOT be used.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section title="Indexed Header Representation"
                anchor="indexed.header.representation">
                <figure title="Indexed Header">
                    <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 1 |        Index (7+)         |
+---+---------------------------+
</artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    This representation starts with the '1' 1-bit pattern,
                    followed by the index of the matching pair, represented as
                    an integer with a 7-bit prefix.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Literal Header Representation"
                anchor="literal.header.representation">
                <section title="Literal Header without Indexing"
                    anchor="literal.header.without.indexing">
                    <figure title="Literal Header without Indexing - Indexed Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 1 | 1 |    Index (5+)     |
+---+---+---+-------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <figure title="Literal Header without Indexing - New Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 1 | 1 |         0         |
+---+---+---+-------------------+
|       Name Length (8+)        |
+-------------------------------+
|  Name String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        This representation, which does not involve updating
                        the header table, starts with the '011' 3-bit pattern.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header name matches the header name of a (name,
                        value) pair stored in the Header Table, the index of
                        the pair increased by one (index + 1) is represented
                        as an integer with a 5-bit prefix.  Note that if the
                        index is strictly below 31, one byte is used.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header name does not match a header name entry,
                        the value 0 is represented on 5 bits followed by the
                        header name (<xref
                            target="header.name.representation" />).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Header name representation is followed by the header
                        value represented as a literal string as described in
                        <xref target="string.literal.representation" />.
                    </t>

                </section>

                <section title="Literal Header with Incremental Indexing"
                    anchor="literal.header.with.incremental.indexing">
                    <figure title="Literal Header with Incremental Indexing -
                        Indexed Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 1 | 0 |    Index (5+)     |
+---+---+---+-------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <figure title="Literal Header with Incremental Indexing -
                        New Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 1 | 0 |         0         |
+---+---+---+-------------------+
|       Name Length (8+)        |
+-------------------------------+
|  Name String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        This representation starts with the '010' 3-bit
                        pattern.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header name matches the header name of a (name,
                        value) pair stored in the Header Table, the index of
                        the pair increased by one (index + 1) is represented
                        as an integer with a 5-bit prefix.  Note that if the
                        index is strictly below 31, one byte is used.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header name does not match a header name entry,
                        the value 0 is represented on 5 bits followed by the
                        header name (<xref
                            target="header.name.representation" />).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Header name representation is followed by the header
                        value represented as a literal string as described in
                        <xref target="string.literal.representation" />.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Literal Header with Substitution Indexing"
                    anchor="literal.header.with.substitution.indexing">
                    <figure title="Literal Header with Substitution Indexing -
                        Indexed Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 0 |      Index (6+)       |
+---+---+-----------------------+
|    Substituted Index (8+)     |
+-------------------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <figure title="Literal Header with Substitution Indexing -
                        New Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 0 |           0           |
+---+---+-----------------------+
|       Name Length (8+)        |
+-------------------------------+
|  Name String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
|    Substituted Index (8+)     |
+-------------------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        This representation starts with the '00' 2-bit
                        pattern.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header name matches the header name of a (name,
                        value) pair stored in the Header Table, the index of
                        the pair increased by one (index + 1) is represented
                        as an integer with a 6-bit prefix.  Note that if the
                        index is strictly below 62, one byte is used.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header name does not match a header name entry,
                        the value 0 is represented on 6 bits followed by the
                        header name (<xref
                            target="header.name.representation" />).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The index of the substituted (name, value) pair is
                        inserted after the header name representation as a
                        0-bit prefix integer.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The index of the substituted pair MUST correspond to a
                        position in the header table containing a non-void
                        entry. An index for the substituted pair that
                        corresponds to empty position in the header table MUST
                        be treated as an error.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This index is followed by the header
                        value represented as a literal string as described in
                        <xref target="string.literal.representation" />.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="parameter.negotiation" title="Parameter Negotiation">
            <t>
                A few parameters can be used to accommodate client and server
                processing and memory requirements.
                <cref>
                    These settings are currently not supported as they have
                    not been integrated in the main specification. Therefore,
                    the maximum buffer size for the header table is fixed at
                    4096 bytes.
                </cref>
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="SETTINGS_MAX_BUFFER_SIZE:">
                        Allows the sender to inform the remote endpoint of the
                        maximum size it accepts for the header table.
                        <vspace blankLines="0"/>
                        The default value is 4096 bytes.
                        <vspace blankLines="0"/>
                        <cref>Is this default value OK? Do we need a maximum size? Do we want to allow infinite buffer?</cref>
                        <vspace blankLines="0"/>
                        When the remote endpoint receives a SETTINGS frame
                        containing a SETTINGS_MAX_BUFFER_SIZE setting with a
                        value smaller than the one currently in use, it MUST
                        send as soon as possible a HEADER frame with a stream
                        identifier of 0x0 containing a value smaller than or
                        equal to the received setting value.
                        <vspace blankLines="0"/>
                        <cref>This changes slightly the behaviour of the
                            HEADERS frame, which should be updated as follows:
                        </cref>
                        <vspace blankLines="0"/>
                        A HEADER frame with a stream identifier of 0x0
                        indicates that the sender has reduced the maximum size
                        of the header table. The new maximum size of the
                        header table is encoded on 32-bit. The decoder MUST
                        reduce its own header table by dropping entries from
                        it until the size of the header table is lower than or
                        equal to the transmitted maximum size.
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                This compressor exists to solve security issues present in
                stream compressors such as DEFLATE whereby the compression
                context can be efficiently probed to reveal secrets.
                A conformant implementation of this specification should be
                fairly safe against that kind of attack, as the reaping of any
                information from the compression context requires more work than
                guessing and verifying the plaintext data directly with the
                server.  As with any secret, however, the longer the length
                of the secret, the more difficult the secret is to guess. It
                is inadvisable to have short cookies that are relied upon to
                remain secret for any duration of time.
            </t>
            <t>
                A proper security-conscious implementation will also need to
                prevent timing attacks by ensuring that the amount of time it
                takes to do string comparisons is always a function of the
                total length of the strings, and not a function of the number
                of matched characters.
            </t>
            <t>
                Another common security problem is when the remote endpoint
                successfully causes the local endpoint to exhaust its memory.
                This compressor attempts to deal with the most obvious ways
                that this could occur by limiting both the peak and the
                steady-state amount of memory consumed in the compressor
                state, by providing ways for the application to consume/flush
                the emitted headers in small chunks, and by considering
                overhead in the state size calculation.  Implementors must
                still be careful in the creation of APIs to an implementation
                of this compressor by ensuring that header keys and values are
                either emitted as a stream, or that the compression
                implementation have a limit on the maximum size of a key or
                value. Failure to implement these kinds of safeguards may
                still result in a scenario where the local endpoint exhausts
                its memory.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Informative References">
            <reference anchor="SPDY" target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-mbelshe-httpbis-spdy">
                <front>
                    <title>SPDY Protocol</title>
                    <author initials="M" surname="Belshe" fullname="Mike Belshe">
                        <organization>Twist</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="R" surname="Peon" fullname="Roberto Peon">
                        <organization>Google</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="February" year="2012"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
        </references>


        <section title="Change Log (to be removed by RFC Editor before publication">
            <section title="Since draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-01">
                <t>
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>
                            Refactored of Header Encoding Section: split
                            definitions and processing rule.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Backward incompatible change: Updated
                            reference set management as per issue #214. This
                            changes how the interaction between the reference
                            set and eviction works. This also changes the
                            working of the reference set in some specific
                            cases.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Backward incompatible change: modified initial
                            header list, as per issue #188.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Added example of 32 bytes entry structure (issue
                            #191).
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Added Header Set Completion section.  Reflowed
                            some text. Clarified some writing which was
                            akward.  Added text about duplicate header entry
                            encoding.  Clarified some language w.r.t Header
                            Set.  Changed x-my-header to mynewheader. Added
                            text in the HeaderEmission section indicating that
                            the application may also be able to free up memory
                            more quickly.  Added information in Security
                            Considerations section.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Initial Header Tables" anchor="initial.headers">
            <t>
                <cref>
                    The tables in this section should be updated based on
                    statistical analysis of header names frequency and specific
                    HTTP 2.0 header rules (like removal of some headers).
                </cref>
                <vspace blankLines="0"/>
                <cref>
                    These tables are not adapted for headers contained in
                    PUSH_PROMISE frames. Either the tables can be merged, or
                    the table for responses can be updated.
                </cref>
            </t>
            <section title="Requests">
                <t>
                    The following table lists the pre-defined headers that
                    make-up the initial header table user to represent
                    requests sent from a client to a server.
                </t>
                <texttable title="Initial Header Table for Requests"
                    anchor="initial.headers.request">
                    <ttcol>Index</ttcol>
                    <ttcol>Header Name</ttcol>
                    <ttcol>Header Value</ttcol>
                    <c>0</c><c>:scheme</c><c>http</c>
                    <c>1</c><c>:scheme</c><c>https</c>
                    <c>2</c><c>:host</c><c></c>
                    <c>3</c><c>:path</c><c>/</c>
                    <c>4</c><c>:method</c><c>GET</c>
                    <c>5</c><c>accept</c><c></c>
                    <c>6</c><c>accept-charset</c><c></c>
                    <c>7</c><c>accept-encoding</c><c></c>
                    <c>8</c><c>accept-language</c><c></c>
                    <c>9</c><c>cookie</c><c></c>
                    <c>10</c><c>if-modified-since</c><c></c>
                    <c>11</c><c>user-agent</c><c></c>
                    <c>12</c><c>referer</c><c></c>
                    <c>13</c><c>authorization</c><c></c>
                    <c>14</c><c>allow</c><c></c>
                    <c>15</c><c>cache-control</c><c></c>
                    <c>16</c><c>connection</c><c></c>
                    <c>17</c><c>content-length</c><c></c>
                    <c>18</c><c>content-type</c><c></c>
                    <c>19</c><c>date</c><c></c>
                    <c>20</c><c>expect</c><c></c>
                    <c>21</c><c>from</c><c></c>
                    <c>22</c><c>if-match</c><c></c>
                    <c>23</c><c>if-none-match</c><c></c>
                    <c>24</c><c>if-range</c><c></c>
                    <c>25</c><c>if-unmodified-since</c><c></c>
                    <c>26</c><c>max-forwards</c><c></c>
                    <c>27</c><c>proxy-authorization</c><c></c>
                    <c>28</c><c>range</c><c></c>
                    <c>29</c><c>via</c><c></c>
                </texttable>
            </section>

            <section title="Responses">
                <t>
                    The following table lists the pre-defined headers that
                    make-up the initial header table used to represent
                    responses sent from a server to a client. The same header
                    table is also used to represent request headers sent from
                    a server to a client in a PUSH_PROMISE frame.
                </t>
                <texttable title="Initial Header Table for Responses"
                    anchor="initial.headers.response">
                    <ttcol>Index</ttcol>
                    <ttcol>Header Name</ttcol>
                    <ttcol>Header Value</ttcol>
                    <c>0</c><c>:status</c><c>200</c>
                    <c>1</c><c>age</c><c></c>
                    <c>2</c><c>cache-control</c><c></c>
                    <c>3</c><c>content-length</c><c></c>
                    <c>4</c><c>content-type</c><c></c>
                    <c>5</c><c>date</c><c></c>
                    <c>6</c><c>etag</c><c></c>
                    <c>7</c><c>expires</c><c></c>
                    <c>8</c><c>last-modified</c><c></c>
                    <c>9</c><c>server</c><c></c>
                    <c>10</c><c>set-cookie</c><c></c>
                    <c>11</c><c>vary</c><c></c>
                    <c>12</c><c>via</c><c></c>
                    <c>13</c><c>access-control-allow-origin</c><c></c>
                    <c>14</c><c>accept-ranges</c><c></c>
                    <c>15</c><c>allow</c><c></c>
                    <c>16</c><c>connection</c><c></c>
                    <c>17</c><c>content-disposition</c><c></c>
                    <c>18</c><c>content-encoding</c><c></c>
                    <c>19</c><c>content-language</c><c></c>
                    <c>20</c><c>content-location</c><c></c>
                    <c>21</c><c>content-range</c><c></c>
                    <c>22</c><c>link</c><c></c>
                    <c>23</c><c>location</c><c></c>
                    <c>24</c><c>proxy-authenticate</c><c></c>
                    <c>25</c><c>refresh</c><c></c>
                    <c>26</c><c>retry-after</c><c></c>
                    <c>27</c><c>strict-transport-security</c><c></c>
                    <c>28</c><c>transfer-encoding</c><c></c>
                    <c>29</c><c>www-authenticate</c><c></c>
                </texttable>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Example" anchor="example">
            <t>
                Here is an example that illustrates different representations
                and how tables are updated.
                <cref>This section needs to be updated to better reflect the new processing of header fields, and include more examples.</cref>
            </t>
            <section title="First header set">
                <t>
                    The first header set to represent is the following:
                    <figure><artwork type="message/http">
:path: /my-example/index.html
user-agent: my-user-agent
mynewheader: first
</artwork></figure>
                    The header table is empty, all headers are represented as
                    literal headers with indexing.  The 'mynewheader' header
                    name is not in the header name table and is encoded
                    literally.  This gives the following representation:
                    <figure><artwork type="message/http">
0x44      (literal header with incremental indexing, name index = 3)
0x16      (header value string length = 22)
/my-example/index.html
0x4D      (literal header with incremental indexing, name index = 12)
0x0D      (header value string length = 13)
my-user-agent
0x40      (literal header with incremental indexing, new name)
0x0B      (header name string length = 11)
mynewheader
0x05      (header value string length = 5)
first
</artwork></figure>
                    The header table is as follows after the processing of
                    these headers:
                    <figure><artwork type="inline">
Header table
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|  Index  | Header Name    | Header Value              |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    0    | :scheme        | http                      |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    1    | :scheme        | https                     |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   ...   | ...            | ...                       |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   37    | warning        |                           |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   38    | :path          | /my-example/index.html    | added header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   39    | user-agent     | my-user-agent             | added header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   40    | mynewheader    | first                     | added header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
</artwork></figure>
                    As all the headers in the first header set are indexed in
                    the header table, all are kept in the reference
                    set of headers, which is:
                    <figure><artwork type="inline">
Reference Set:
:path, /my-example/index.html
user-agent, my-user-agent
mynewheader, first
</artwork></figure>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Second header set">
                <t>
                    The second header set to represent is the following:
                    <figure><artwork type="message/http">
:path: /my-example/resources/script.js
user-agent: my-user-agent
mynewheader: second
</artwork></figure>
                    Comparing this second header set to the reference set, the
                    first and third headers are from the reference set are not
                    present in this second header set and must be removed. In
                    addition, in this new set, the first and third headers
                    have to be encoded.
                    The path header is represented as a literal header with
                    substitution indexing. The mynewheader will be
                    represented as a literal header with incremental indexing.
                    <figure><artwork type="message/http">
0xa6       (indexed header, index = 38: removal from reference set)
0xa8       (indexed header, index = 40: removal from reference set)
0x04       (literal header, substitution indexing, name index = 3)
0x26       (replaced entry index = 38)
0x1f       (header value string length = 31)
/my-example/resources/script.js
0x5f 0x0a  (literal header, incremental indexing, name index = 40)
0x06       (header value string length = 6)
second
</artwork></figure>
                    The header table is updated as follow:
                    <figure><artwork type="inline">
Header table
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|  Index  | Header Name    | Header Value              |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    0    | :scheme        | http                      |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    1    | :scheme        | https                     |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   ...   | ...            | ...                       |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   37    | warning        |                           |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   38    | :path          | /my-example/resources/    | replaced
|         |                |     script.js             | header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   39    | user-agent     | my-user-agent             |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   40    | mynewheader    | first                     |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   41    | mynewheader    | second                    | added header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
</artwork></figure>
                    All the headers in this second header set are indexed in
                    the header table, therefore, all are kept in the reference
                    set of headers, which becomes:
                    <figure><artwork type="inline">
Reference Set:
:path, /my-example/resources/script.js
user-agent, my-user-agent
mynewheader, second
</artwork></figure>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

    </back>
</rfc>
<!--
  vim:et:tw=78:sw=4:
 -->
