<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lib/rfc2629.xslt"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" 
     category="std"
     docName="draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-latest" 
     x:maturity-level="proposed"
     xmlns:x='http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext'>
  <x:feedback template="mailto:ietf-http-wg@w3.org?subject={docname},%20%22{section}%22&amp;body=&lt;{ref}&gt;:"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="HTTP/2.0">Hypertext Transfer Protocol version 2.0</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Belshe" fullname="Mike Belshe">
      <organization>Twist</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mbelshe@chromium.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="R." surname="Peon" fullname="Roberto Peon">
      <organization>Google, Inc</organization>
      <address>
        <email>fenix@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson" role="editor">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3210 Porter Drive</street>
          <city>Palo Alto</city>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>martin.thomson@skype.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="A." surname="Melnikov" fullname="Alexey Melnikov" role="editor">
      <organization>Isode Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5 Castle Business Village</street>
          <street>36 Station Road</street>
          <city>Hampton</city>
          <region>Middlesex</region>

          <code>TW12 2BX</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Alexey.Melnikov@isode.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />
    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>HTTPbis Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>HTTP</keyword>
    <keyword>SPDY</keyword>
    <keyword>Web</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This specification describes an optimised expression of the syntax of the Hypertext 
        Transfer Protocol (HTTP). The HTTP/2.0 encapsulation enables more efficient use of 
        network resources and reduced perception of latency by allowing header field 
        compression and multiple concurrent messages on the same connection. It also 
        introduces unsolicited push of representations from servers to clients.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document is an alternative to, but does not obsolete the HTTP/1.1 message format
        or protocol. HTTP's existing semantics remain unchanged.
      </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Editorial Note (To be removed by RFC Editor)">
      <t>
        Discussion of this draft takes place on the HTTPBIS working group
        mailing list (ietf-http-wg@w3.org), which is archived at
        <eref target="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/ietf-http-wg/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Working Group information and related documents can be found
        at <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/wg/httpbis/"/> (Wiki) and
        <eref target="https://github.com/http2/http2-spec"/> (source code
        and issues tracker).
      </t>
      <t>
        The changes in this draft are summarized in <xref
        target="changes.since.draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-02"/>.
      </t>
    </note>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a wildly successful protocol. However, the HTTP/1.1 message
        encapsulation (<xref target="HTTP-p1" x:fmt="," x:rel="#http.message"/>) is optimized for
        implementation simplicity and accessibility, not application performance.  As such it has
        several characteristics that have a negative overall effect on application performance.
      </t>
      <t>
        In particular, HTTP/1.0 only allows one request can be delivered at a time on a
        given connection.  HTTP/1.1 pipelining only partially addressed these concerns, and is not 
        widely deployed.  Therefore, clients that need to make many requests (as is common on the
        Web) typically use multiple connections to a server in order to reduce percieved latency.
      </t>
      <t>
        Furthermore, HTTP/1.1 header fields are often repetitive and verbose, which, in
        addition to generating more or larger network packets, can cause the small initial TCP
        congestion window to quickly quickly.  This can result in excessive latency when multiple
        requests are made on a new TCP connection.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document addresses these issues by defining an optimized mapping of HTTP's semantics to an underlying connection.
        Specifically, it allows interleaving of request and response messages on the same
        connection and uses an efficient coding for HTTP header fields.  It also allows prioritization of
        requests, letting more important requests complete more quickly, further improving perceived
        performance.
      </t>
      <t>
        The resulting protocol is desined to have be more friendly to the network, because fewer
        TCP connections can be used, in comparison to HTTP/1.x. This means less competition with
        other flows, and longer-lived connections, which in turn leads to better utilisation of
        available network capacity.
      </t>
      <t>
        Finally, this encapsulation also enables more scalable processing of messages through use of
        binary message framing.
      </t>

      <section title="Document Organization">
        <t>
          The HTTP/2.0 Specification is split into three parts: <xref target="starting">starting
          HTTP/2.0</xref>, which covers how a HTTP/2.0 session is initiated; <xref target="FramingLayer">a
          framing layer</xref>, which multiplexes a single TCP connection into independent
          frames of various types; and <xref target="HTTPLayer">an HTTP layer</xref>, which specifies the mechanism
          for expressing HTTP interations using the framing layer. While some of the
          framing layer concepts are isolated from HTTP, building a generic framing layer
          has not been a goal. The framing layer is tailored to the needs of the HTTP protocol and
          server push.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Conventions and Terminology">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
          NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          All numeric values are in network byte order.  Values are unsigned unless otherwise
          indicated.  Literal values are provided in decimal or hexadecimal as appropriate.
          Hexadecimal literals are prefixed with <spanx style="verb">0x</spanx> to distinguish them
          from decimal literals.
        </t>
        <t>
          The following terms are used:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="client:">
              The endpoint initiating the HTTP session.
            </t>
            <t hangText="connection:">
              A transport-level connection between two endpoints.
            </t>
            <t hangText="endpoint:">
              Either the client or server of the connection.
            </t>
            <t hangText="frame:">
              The smallest unit of communication, each containing a frame header.
            </t>
            <t hangText="message:">
              A complete sequence of frames.
            </t>
            <t hangText="receiver:">
              An endpoint that is receiving frames.
            </t>
            <t hangText="sender:">
              An endpoint that is transmitting frames.
            </t>
            <t hangText="server:">
              The endpoint which did not initiate the HTTP session.
            </t>
            <t hangText="session:">
              A synonym for "connection".
            </t>
            <t hangText="session error:">
              An error on the HTTP/2.0 session.
            </t>
            <t hangText="stream:">
              A bi-directional flow of bytes across a virtual channel within the HTTP/2.0 session.
            </t>
            <t hangText="stream error:">
              An error on the individual HTTP/2.0 stream.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="starting" title="Starting HTTP/2.0">
      <t>
        Just as HTTP/1.1 does, HTTP/2.0 uses the "http:" and "https:" URI schemes.  An
        HTTP/2.0-capable client is therefore required to discover whether the upstream server (including intermediaries)
        supports HTTP/2.0.
      </t>
      <t>
        Different discovery mechanisms are defined for "http:" and "https:" URIs.  Discovery for
        "http:" URIs is described in <xref target="discover-http"/>; discovery for "https:" URIs is
        described in <xref target="discover-https"/>.
      </t>

      <section anchor="versioning" title="HTTP/2.0 Version Identification">
        <t>
          The protocol defined in this document is identified using the string "HTTP/2.0".  This identification is used in the
          HTTP/1.1 Upgrade header field, in the <xref target="TLSNPN">TLS-NPN</xref>
          <cref>TBD</cref> field and other places where protocol identification is required.
        </t>
        <t>
          Negotiating "HTTP/2.0" implies the use of the transport, security, framing and message
          semantics described in this document.
        </t>
        <t>
          <cref>Editor's Note: please remove the following text prior to the publication of a final
          version of this document.</cref>
        </t>
        <t>
          Only implementations of the final, published RFC can identify themselves as "HTTP/2.0".
          Until such an RFC exists, implementations MUST NOT identify themselves using "HTTP/2.0".
        </t>
        <t>
          Examples and text throughout the rest of this document use "HTTP/2.0" as a matter of
          editorial convenience only.  Implementations of draft versions MUST NOT identify using
          this string.
        </t>
        <t>
          Implementations of draft versions of the protocol MUST add the string "-draft-" and the
          corresponding draft number to the identifier before the separator ('/').  For example,
          draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-03 is identified using the string "HTTP-draft-03/2.0".
        </t>
        <t>
          Non-compatible experiments that are based on these draft versions MUST instead replace the
          string "draft" with a different identifier.  For example, an experimental implementation
          of packet mood-based encoding based on draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-07 might identify itself
          as "HTTP-emo-07/2.0".  Note that any label MUST conform with the "token" syntax defined in
          <xref target="HTTP-p1" x:fmt="of" x:rel="#field.components"/>.  Experimenters are
          encouraged to coordinate their experiments on the ietf-http-wg@w3.org mailing list.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="discover-http" title="Starting HTTP/2.0 for &quot;http:&quot; URIs">
        <t>
          A client that makes a request to an "http:" URI without prior knowledge about support for
          HTTP/2.0 uses the HTTP Upgrade mechanism (<xref target="HTTP-p1" x:fmt="of"
          x:rel="#header.upgrade"/>).  The client makes an HTTP/1.1 request that includes an Upgrade
          header field identifying HTTP/2.0.
        </t>
        <t>
          For example:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;request&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
GET /default.htm HTTP/1.1
Host: server.example.com
Connection: Upgrade
Upgrade: HTTP/2.0
</artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          A server that does not support HTTP/2.0 can respond to the request as though the Upgrade
          header field were absent:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;responset&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-length: 243
Content-type: text/html
      ...
</artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          A server that supports HTTP/2.0 can accept the upgrade with a 101 (Switching Protocols)
          status code.  After the empty line that terminates the 101 response, the server can begin
          sending HTTP/2.0 frames.  These frames MUST include a response to the request that
          initiated the Upgrade.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;response&#34;" x:indent-with="  ">
HTTP/1.1 101 Switching Protocols
Connection: Upgrade
Upgrade: HTTP/2.0

[ HTTP/2.0 session ...
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          Once the server returns the 101 response, both the client and the server send a <xref
          target="SessionHeader">session header</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="discover-https" title="Starting HTTP/2.0 for &quot;https:&quot; URIs">
        <t>
          A client that makes a request to an "https:" URI without prior knowledge about support for
          HTTP/2.0 uses <xref target="RFC5246">TLS</xref> with <xref target="TLSNPN">TLS-NPN</xref>
          extension.  <cref>TBD, maybe ALPN</cref>
        </t>

        <t>
          Once TLS negotiation is complete, both the client and the server send a <xref
          target="SessionHeader">session header</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="known-http" title="Starting HTTP/2.0 with Prior Knowledge">
        <t>
          A client can learn that a particular server supports HTTP/2.0 by other means.  A client
          MAY immediately send HTTP/2.0 frames to a server that is known to support HTTP/2.0.  This
          only affects the resolution of "http:" URIs, servers supporting HTTP/2.0 are required to
          support <xref target="TLSNPN">protocol negotiation in TLS</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Prior support for HTTP/2.0 is not a strong signal that a given server will support
          HTTP/2.0 for future sessions.  It is possible for server configurations to change or for
          configurations to differ between instances in clustered server.  Interception proxies
          (a.k.a. "transparent" proxies) are another source of variability.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="FramingLayer" title="HTTP/2.0 Framing Layer">
      <section title="Session">
        <t>
          The HTTP/2.0 session runs atop TCP (<xref target="RFC0793"/>). The client is the TCP
          connection initiator.
        </t>
        <t>
          HTTP/2.0 connections are persistent.  That is, for best performance, it is expected
          that clients will not close connections until the user navigates away from all Web
          pages referencing a connection, or until the server closes the connection. Servers are
          encouraged to leave connections open for as long as possible, but can terminate idle
          connections if necessary.  When either endpoint closes the transport-level connection, it
          MUST first send a <xref target="GOAWAY">GOAWAY</xref> frame so that the endpoints can
          reliably determine if messages were processed beforehand.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="SessionHeader" title="Session Header">
        <t>
          After opening a TCP connection and performing either an HTTP/1.1 Upgrade or TLS handshake,
          the client sends the client session header.  The server replies with a server session
          header.
        </t>
        <t>
          The session header provides a final confirmation that both peers agree to use the HTTP/2.0
          protocol.  The SETTINGS frame ensures that client or server configuration is known as
          quickly as possible.
        </t>
        <t>
          The client session header is the 25 byte sequence
          0x464f4f202a20485454502f322e300d0a0d0a4241520d0a0d0a (the string <spanx style="verb">FOO *
          HTTP/2.0\r\n\r\nBAR\r\n\r\n</spanx>) followed by a <xref target="SETTINGS">SETTINGS
          frame</xref>.  The client sends the client session header immediately upon receipt of a
          101 Switching Protocols response (indiciating a successful upgrade), or after receiving 
          a TLS Finished message from the server. If starting HTTP/2.0 with prior knowledge, the
          client session header is sent upon connection establishment.
        </t>
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>
              The client session header is selected so that a large proportion of HTTP/1.1 or
              HTTP/1.0 servers and intermediaries do not attempt to process further frames.  Note
              that this does not address the concerns raised in <xref target="TALKING"/>.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The server session header is a <xref target="SETTINGS">SETTINGS frame</xref>.  The server
          sends the server session header immediately after receiving and validating the client
          session header.
        </t>
        <t>
          The client sends requests immediately after sending the session header, without waiting to
          receive a server session header.  This ensures that confirming session headers does not
          add latency.
        </t>
        <t>
          Receivers MUST close the connection if it does not begin with a valid session
          header.  A <xref target="GOAWAY">GOAWAY frame</xref> MAY be omitted if it is clear that
          the peer is not using HTTP/2.0.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Framing">
        <t>
          Once the connection is established, clients and servers exchange HTTP/2.0 frames.  Frames
          are the basic unit of communication.
        </t>
        
        <section anchor="FrameHeader" title="Frame Header">
          <t>
            HTTP/2.0 frames share a common format, consisting of 8 byte of header with between
            0 and 65535 bytes of data.
          </t>
          <figure title="Frame Header">
            <artwork type="inline">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         Length (16)           |   Type (8)    |   Flags (8)   |
+-+-------------+---------------+-------------------------------+
|R|                 Stream Identifier (31)                      |
+-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
|                     Frame Data (0...)                       ...
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
</artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The fields of the frame header are defined as:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Length:">
                The 16-bit length of the frame data in bytes.  The length of the frame header is
                not included.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Type:">
                The 8-bit type of the frame.  The frame type determines how the remainder of the
                frame header and data are interpreted.  Implementations MUST ignore unsupported 
                and unrecognized frame types.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Flags:">
                An 8-bit field reserved for flags.  Bits that have undefined semantics are reserved.
                The following flags are defined for all frame types:
                <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="FINAL (0x1):">
                    Bit 1 (the least significant bit) indicates that this is the last frame in a
                    stream, placing it into a <xref
                    target="StreamHalfClose">half-closed state</xref>.  No further frames follow in
                    the direction of the carrying frame.
                  </t>
                </list>
                The remaining flags can be assigned semantics by the indicated frame type.
              </t>
              <t hangText="R:">
                A reserved 1-bit field.  The semantics of this bit are not defined.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Stream Identifier:">
                A 31-bit stream identifier (see <xref target="StreamCreation"/>).  A value 0 is
                reserved for frames that are directed at the session as a whole instead of a single
                stream.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Frame Data:">
                Frames contain between 0 and 65535 bytes of data.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            Reserved bits in the frame header MUST be set to zero when sending and MUST be ignored
            when receiving frames, unless the semantics of the bit are known.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="FrameSize" title="Frame Processing">
          <t>
            A frame of the maximum size might be too large for implementations with limited
            resources to process.  Implementations MAY choose to support frames smaller than the
            maximum possible size.  However, implementations MUST be able to receive frames
            containing at least 8192 octets of data.
          </t>
          <t>
            An implementation MUST immediately close a stream if it is unable to process a frame
            related to that stream due to it exceeding a size limit.  The implementation MUST send a
            <xref target="RST_STREAM">RST_STREAM frame</xref> containing FRAME_TOO_LARGE error code
            if the frame size limit is exceeded.
          </t>
          <t>
            <cref><eref target="https://github.com/http2/http2-spec/issues/28">Issue 28</eref>: Need
            a way to signal the maximum frame size; no way to RST_STREAM on non-stream-related
            frames.</cref>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>


      <section title="Streams">
        <t>
          Streams are independent sequences of bi-directional data divided into frames with several
          properties:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Streams can be created by either the client or server.
            </t>
            <t>
              Streams optionally carry a set of name-value header pairs.
            </t>
            <t>
              Streams can concurrently send data interleaved with other streams.
            </t>
            <t>
              Streams can be established and used unilaterally.
            </t>
            <t>
              Streams can be cancelled.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <section anchor="StreamCreation" title="Stream Creation">
          <t>
            Use of streams does not require negotiation.  A stream is not created, streams are used
            by sending a frame on the stream.
          </t>
          <t>
            Streams are identified by a 31-bit numeric identifier.  Streams initiated by a client
            use odd numbered stream identifiers; those initiated by the server use even numbered
            stream identifiers.  A stream identifier of zero MUST NOT be used to create a new
            stream.
          </t>
          <t>
            The stream identifier of a new stream MUST be greater than all previously streams from that
            endpoint, unless the stream identifier was reserved (such as the promised
            stream identifier in a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame).  An
            endpoint that receives an unexpected stream identifier MUST handle it as a <xref
            target="SessionErrorHandler">session error</xref> of type PROTOCOL_ERROR.
          </t>
          <t>
            A long-lived session can exhaust the available stream identifiers. An
            endpoint that is unable to create a new stream identifier can establish a new session
            for any new streams.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint can request the early
            termination of an unwanted stream.  Upon receipt of a frame, the receiver can terminate
            the corresponding stream by sending a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream
            error</xref> of type REFUSED_STREAM. This cannot prevent the initiating endpoint
            from sending frames for that stream prior to receiving this request.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="StreamPriority" title="Stream priority">
          <t>
            The creator of a stream can assign a priority for that stream.  Priority is represented as
            a 31 bit integer.  0 represents the highest priority and 2<x:sup>31</x:sup>-1 represents
            the lowest priority.
          </t>
          <t>
            Senders and receivers SHOULD use best-effort to process streams in the order of
            highest priority to lowest priority. <cref>ED: toothless, useless "SHOULD":
            reword</cref>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Stream headers">
          <t>
            Streams can carry optional sets of header fields containing metadata.
            After the stream has been created, and as long as the sender is not <xref
            target="StreamClose">closed</xref> or <xref target="StreamHalfClose">half-closed</xref>,
            each side may send HEADERS frame(s) containing header data.  Header data can be sent
            in multiple HEADERS frames, and HEADERS frames may be interleaved with data frames.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Stream data exchange">
          <t>
            Once a stream is created, it can be used to send arbitrary amounts of data.  Generally
            this means that a series of data frames will be sent on the stream until a frame
            containing the <xref target="FrameHeader">FINAL flag</xref> is set.  Once the FINAL flag
            has been set on any frame, the stream is considered to be half-closed.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="StreamHalfClose" title="Stream half-close">
          <t>
            When one side of the stream sends a frame with the FINAL flag set, the stream is
            half-closed from that endpoint. The sender of the FINAL flag MUST NOT send further
            frames on that stream. When both sides have half-closed, the stream is closed.
          </t>
          <t>
            Receivers of frames on a half-closed stream MUST handle them as a <xref
            target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type STREAM_CLOSED.
          </t>
          <t>
            Streams that have never received packets can be considered to be half-closed in the
            direction that is silent.  This allows either peer to create a unidirectional stream,
            which does not require an explicit close from the peer that does not transmit frames.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="StreamClose" title="Stream close">
          <t>
            Streams can be terminated in the following ways:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Normal termination:">
                Normal stream termination occurs when both client and server have half-closed the
                stream by sending a frame containing a <xref target="FrameHeader">FINAL flag</xref>.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Half-close on unidirectional stream:">
                A stream that only has frames sent in one direction can be tentatively considered to
                be closed once a frame containing a FINAL flag is sent.  The active sender on the
                stream MUST be prepared to receive frames after closing the stream.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Abrupt termination:">
                Either the peer can send a RST_STREAM control frame at any time to terminate an
                active stream. RST_STREAM contains an error code to indicate the reason for
                termination.  A RST_STREAM indicates that the sender will transmit no further data
                on the stream and that the receiver is advised to cease transmission on it.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                The sender of a RST_STREAM frame MUST allow for frames that have already been sent
                by the peer prior to the RST_STREAM being processed.  If in-transit frames alter
                session state, these frames cannot be safely discarded.  See <xref
                target="StreamErrorHandler">Stream Error Handling</xref> for more details.
              </t>
              <t hangText="TCP connection teardown:">
                If the TCP connection is torn down while un-closed streams
                exist, then the endpoint MUST assume that the stream was abnormally interrupted and
                may be incomplete.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            If an endpoint receives a frame on a stream after it is closed, it MAY send a
            RST_STREAM to the sender with the status PROTOCOL_ERROR.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Error Handling">
        <t>
          HTTP/2.0 framing permits two classes of error: 
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              An error condition that renders the entire session unusable is a session error.
            </t>
            <t>
              An error in an individual stream is a stream error.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <section anchor="SessionErrorHandler" title="Session Error Handling">
          <t>
            A session error is any error which prevents further processing of the framing layer or
            which corrupts any session state.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint that encounters a session error MUST first send a <xref
            target="GOAWAY">GOAWAY</xref> frame with the stream identifier of the last stream that
            it successfully received from its peer.  The GOAWAY frame includes an error code that
            indicates why the session is terminating.  After sending the GOAWAY frame, the endpoint
            MUST close the TCP connection.
          </t>
          <t>
            It is possible that the GOAWAY will not be reliably received by the receiving endpoint.
            In the event of a session error, GOAWAY only provides a best-effort attempt to
            communicate with the peer about why the session is going down.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint can end a session at any time.  In particular, an endpoint MAY choose to
            treat a stream error as a session error if the error is recurrent.  Endpoints SHOULD
            send a GOAWAY frame when ending a session, as long as circumstances permit it.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="StreamErrorHandler" title="Stream Error Handling">
          <t>
            A stream error is an error related to a specific stream identifier that does not affect
            processing of other streams at the framing layer.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint that detects a stream error sends a <xref
            target="RST_STREAM">RST_STREAM</xref> frame that contains the stream identifier of the
            stream where the error occurred.  The RST_STREAM frame includes an error code that
            indicates the type of error.
          </t>
          <t>
            A RST_STREAM is the last frame that an endpoint can send on a stream.  The peer that
            sends the RST_STREAM frame MUST be prepared to receive any frames that were sent or
            enqueued for sending by the remote peer.  These frames can be ignored, except where they
            modify session state (such as that for header compression).
          </t>
          <t>
            Normally, an endpoint SHOULD NOT send more than one RST_STREAM frame for any stream. However, an endpoint
            MAY send additional RST_STREAM frames if it receives frames on a closed stream after
            more than a round trip time.  This behaviour is permitted to deal with misbehaving
            implementations.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint MUST NOT send a RST_STREAM in response to an RST_STREAM frame, to avoid looping. 
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ErrorCodes" title="Error Codes">
          <t>
            Error codes are 32-bit fields that are used in RST_STREAM and GOAWAY frames to convey
            the reasons for the stream or session error.
          </t>

          <t>
            Error codes share a common code space.  Some error codes only apply to specific
            conditions and have no defined semantics in certain frame types.
          </t>

          <t>
            The following error codes are defined:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="NO_ERROR (0):">
                The associated condition is not as a result of an error.  For example, a GOAWAY
                might include this code to indicate graceful shutdown of a session.
              </t>
              <t hangText="PROTOCOL_ERROR (1):">
                The endpoint detected an unspecific protocol error.  This error is for use when a more
                specific error code is not available.
              </t>
              <t hangText="INTERNAL_ERROR (2):">
                The endpoint encountered an unexpected internal error.
              </t>
              <t hangText="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR (3):">
                The endpoint detected that its peer violated the flow control protocol.
              </t>
              <t hangText="INVALID_STREAM (4):">
                The endpoint received a frame for an inactive stream.
              </t>
              <t hangText="STREAM_CLOSED (5):">
                The endpoint received a frame after a stream was half-closed.
              </t>
              <t hangText="FRAME_TOO_LARGE (6):">
                The endpoint received a frame that was larger than the maximum size that it
                supports.
              </t>
              <t hangText="REFUSED_STREAM (7):">
                The endpoint is refusing the stream before processing its payload.
              </t>
              <t hangText="CANCEL (8):">
                Used by the creator of a stream to indicate that the stream is no longer needed.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="flowcontrol" title="Stream Flow Control">
        <t>
          Using streams for multiplexing introduces contention over use of the TCP connection,
          resulting in blocked streams.  A flow control
          scheme ensures that streams on the same connection do not destructively interfere with each other.
        </t>
        <t>
          HTTP/2.0 provides for flow control through use of the 
          <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> frame type.
        </t>

        <section anchor="fc-principles" title="Flow Control Principles">
          <t>
            Experience with TCP congestion control has shown that algorithms can evolve over time to
            become more sophisticated without requiring protocol changes.  TCP congestion control
            and its evolution is clearly different from HTTP/2.0 flow control, though the evolution
            of TCP congestion control algorithms shows that a similar approach could be feasible for
            HTTP/2.0 flow control.
          </t>
          <t>
            HTTP/2.0 stream flow control aims to allow for future improvements to flow control
            algorithms without requiring protocol changes.  Flow control in HTTP/2.0 has the
            following characteristics:
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                Flow control is hop-by-hop, not end-to-end.
              </t>
              <t>
                Flow control is based on window update messages.  Receivers advertise how many
                octets they are prepared to receive on a stream.  This is a credit-based scheme.
              </t>
              <t>
                Flow control is directional with overall control provided by the receiver.  A
                receiver MAY choose to set any window size that it desires for each stream and for
                the entire connection.  A sender MUST respect flow control limits imposed by a
                receiver.  Clients, servers and intermediaries all independently advertise their
                flow control preferences as a receiver and abide by the flow control limits set by
                their peer when sending.
              </t>
              <t>
                The initial value for the flow control window is 65536 bytes for both new streams
                and the overall connection.
              </t>
              <t>
                The frame type determines whether flow control applies to a frame.  Of the frames
                specified in this document, only data frames are subject to flow control; all other
                frame types do not consume space in the advertised flow control window.  This
                ensures that important control frames are not blocked by flow control.
              </t>
              <t>
                Flow control can be disabled by a receiver.  A receiver can choose to either disable
                flow control for a stream or connection by declaring an infinite flow control limit.
              </t>
              <t>
                HTTP/2.0 standardizes only the format of the <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE">window
                update message</xref>.  This does not stipulate how a receiver decides when to send
                this message or the value that it sends.  Nor does it specify how a sender chooses
                to send packets.  Implementations are able to select any algorithm that suits their
                needs.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            Implementations are also responsible for managing how requests and responses are sent
            based on priority; choosing how to avoid head of line blocking for requests; and
            managing the creation of new streams.  Algorithm choices for these could interact with
            any flow control algorithm.
          </t>

        </section>
        <section title="Appropriate Use of Flow Control">
          <t>
            Flow control is defined to protect endpoints (client, server or intermediary) that are
            operating under resource constraints.  For example, a proxy needs to share memory between many
            connections, and also might have a slow upstream connection and a fast downstream one.  
            Flow control addresses cases where the receiver is unable process data on
            one stream, yet wants to be continue to process other streams in the same connection.
          </t>
          <t>
            Deployments that do not require this capability SHOULD disable flow control for data
            that is being received.  Note that flow control cannot be disabled for sending.
            Sending data is always subject to the flow control window advertised by the receiver.
          </t>
          <t>
            Deployments with constrained resources (for example, memory) MAY employ flow control to
            limit the amount of memory a peer can consume.  Note, however, that this can lead to suboptimal use of
            available network resources if flow control is enabled without knowledge of the
            bandwidth-delay product (see <xref target="RFC1323"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            Even with full awareness of the current bandwidth-delay product, implementation of flow control 
            is difficult. However, it can ensure that constrained resources are protected without any
            reduction in connection utilization.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Frame Types">
        <section anchor="DataFrames" title="DATA Frames">
          <t>
            DATA frames (type=0) are used to convey HTTP message bodies.  The payload of a data
            frame contains a portion of the body's payload, or the complete body if there is only
            one DATA frame in the stream.
          </t>
          <t>
            No frame-specific flags are defined for DATA frames.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="HEADERS_PRIORITY" title="HEADERS+PRIORITY">
          <t>
            The HEADERS+PRIORITY frame (type=1) allows the sender to set header fields and stream
            priority at the same time.  It MUST be used for each stream that is created.
          </t>
          <figure title="HEADERS+PRIORITY Frame Payload">
            <artwork type="inline">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|X|                   Priority (31)                             |
+-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
|                    Header Block (*)                         ...
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
</artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>
            The HEADERS+PRIORITY frame is identical to the <xref target="HEADERS">HEADERS
            frame</xref>, preceded by a single reserved bit and a 31-bit priority; see
            <xref target="StreamPriority"/>.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="RST_STREAM" title="RST_STREAM">
          <t>
            The RST_STREAM frame (type=3) allows for abnormal termination of a stream.  When sent by
            the creator of a stream, it indicates that they wish to cancel the stream.  When
            sent by the receiver of a stream, it indicates an error or that the receiver did not
            want to accept the stream, so the stream should be closed.
          </t>
          <figure title="RST_STREAM Frame Payload">
            <artwork type="inline">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Error Code (32)                       |
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
</artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The RST_STREAM frame does not define any valid flags.
          </t>

          <t>
            The RST_STREAM frame contains a single 32-bit <xref target="ErrorCodes">error
            code</xref>.  The error code indicates why the stream is being terminated.
          </t>
          <t>
            After receiving a RST_STREAM on a stream, the receiver must not send additional frames
            for that stream, and the stream moves into the closed state.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="SETTINGS" title="SETTINGS">
          <t>
            A SETTINGS frame (type=4) contains a set of id/value pairs for communicating
            configuration data regarding how the two endpoints can communicate. SETTINGS frames MUST be
            sent at the start of a session, and additionally they can be sent at any other time by either
            endpoint.  Settings are declarative, not negotiated; each peer indicates their own
            configuration.
          </t>
          <section title="Settings Persistence">
            <t>
              When the server is the sender, the sender can request that configuration data be
              persisted by the client across HTTP/2.0 sessions and returned to the server in future
              communications.
            </t>
            <t>
              <cref>Note that persistence of settings is under discussion in the WG and might be
              removed in a future version of this document.</cref>
            </t>
            <t>
              Clients persist settings on a per origin basis (see <xref target="RFC6454"/> for a
              definition of web origins).  That is, when a client connects to a server, and the server
              persists settings within the client, the client SHOULD return the persisted settings on
              future connections to the same origin AND IP address and TCP port. Clients MUST NOT
              request servers to use the persistence features of the SETTINGS frames, and servers MUST
              ignore persistence related flags sent by a client.
            </t>
            <t>
              For example, if the server sends IDs 1, 2, and 3 with the 
              FLAG_SETTINGS_PERSIST_VALUE in a first SETTINGS frame, and then sends IDs 4 and 5 with the FLAG_SETTINGS_PERSIST_VALUE,
              when the client returns the persisted state on its next SETTINGS frame, it SHOULD send
              all 5 settings (1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 in this example) to the server.
            </t>          
          </section>
          <t>
            Valid frame-specific flags for the SETTINGS frame are:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="CLEAR_PERSISTED (0x2):">
                Bit 2 being set indicates a request to clear any previously persisted settings
                before processing the settings.  Clients MUST NOT set this flag.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            SETTINGS frames always apply to a session, never a single stream.  The stream identifier
            for a settings frame MUST be zero.
          </t>
          
          <figure title="SETTINGS ID/Value Pair Format">
            <artwork type="inline">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|SettingFlags(8)|             Setting Identifier (24)           |
+---------------+-----------------------------------------------+
|                        Value (32)                             |
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
</artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The payload of a SETTINGS frame contains zero or more settings.  Each setting is
            comprised of the following
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Settings Flags:">
                An 8-bit flags field containing per-setting instructions.  The following flags are
                valid:
                <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="PERSIST_VALUE (0x1):">
                    Bit 1 (the least significant bit) being set indicates a request from the server
                    to the client to persist this setting.  A client MUST NOT set this flag.
                  </t>
                  <t hangText="PERSISTED (0x2):">
                    Bit 2 being set indicates that this setting is a persisted setting being
                    returned by the client to the server.  This also indicates that this setting is
                    not a client setting, but a value previously set by the server.  A server MUST
                    NOT set this flag.
                  </t>
                </list>
                All other settings flags are reserved.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Setting Identifier:">
                A 24-bit field that identifies the setting.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Value:">
                A 32-bit value for the setting.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            The following settings are defined:
            <list style="hanging">
              <x:lt hangText="SETTINGS_UPLOAD_BANDWIDTH (1):">
                <t>
                  indicates the sender's estimated upload bandwidth for this session. The value 
                  is an the integral number of kilobytes per
                  second that the sender predicts as an expected maximum upload channel capacity.
                </t>
              </x:lt>
              <x:lt hangText="SETTINGS_DOWNLOAD_BANDWIDTH (2):">
                <t>
                  indicates the sender's estimated download bandwidth for this session. The value 
                  is an integral number of kilobytes per
                  second that the sender predicts as an expected maximum download channel capacity.
                </t>
              </x:lt>
              <x:lt hangText="SETTINGS_ROUND_TRIP_TIME (3):">
                <t>
                  indicates the sender's estimated round-trip-time for this session. The round
                  trip time is defined as the minimum amount of time to send a control frame from
                  this client to the remote and receive a response. The value is represented in
                  milliseconds.
                </t>
              </x:lt>
              <x:lt hangText="SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS (4):">
                <t>
                  indicates the maximum number of concurrent streams that the sender will allow. 
                  This limit is directional: it applies to the number
                  of streams that the sender permits the receiver to create. By default there is no
                  limit.  It is recommended that this value be no smaller than 100,
                  so as to not unnecessarily limit parallelism.
                </t>
              </x:lt>
              <x:lt hangText="SETTINGS_CURRENT_CWND (5):">
                <t>
                  indicates the sender's current TCP CWND value.
                </t>
              </x:lt>
              <x:lt hangText="SETTINGS_DOWNLOAD_RETRANS_RATE (6):">
                <t>
                  indicates the sender's retransmission rate (bytes retransmitted / total bytes transmitted).
                </t>
              </x:lt>
              <x:lt hangText="SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE (7):">
                <t>
                  indicates the sender's initial stream window size (in bytes) for new streams.
                </t>
              </x:lt>
              <x:lt hangText="SETTINGS_FLOW_CONTROL_OPTIONS (10):">
                <t>
                  indicates that streams directed to the sender will not
                  be subject to flow control.  The least significant bit (0x1) is set to indicate
                  that new streams are not flow controlled.  Bit 2 (0x2) is set to indicate that the
                  session is not flow controlled.  All other bits are reserved.
                </t>
                <t>
                  This setting applies to all streams, including existing streams.
                </t>
                <t>
                  These bits cannot be cleared once set, see <xref target="EndFlowControl"/>.
                </t>
              </x:lt>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            The SETTINGS frame is extensible for future information which may improve
            client-server communications.
          </t>
          <t>
            SETTINGS does not need to include every defined setting; senders MUST only include 
            those for which it has accurate values to convey. When
            multiple ID/value pairs are sent, they SHOULD be sent in order of lowest id to highest
            id.  A single SETTINGS frame MUST NOT contain multiple values for the same ID.  If the
            receiver of a SETTINGS frame discovers multiple values for the same ID, it MUST ignore
            all values for that ID except the first one.
          </t>
          <t>
            Over the lifetime of a session, a server MAY send multiple SETTINGS frames containing 
            different ID/Value pairs.  When the same ID/Value is sent twice, the most recent value 
            overrides any previously sent values.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="PUSH_PROMISE" title="PUSH_PROMISE">

          <t>
            The PUSH_PROMISE frame (type=5) allows the sender to signal a promise to create a stream
            and serve the referenced resource.  Minimal data allowing the receiver to understand
            which resource(s) are to be pushed are to be included.
          </t>

          <t>
            PUSH_PROMISE frames are sent on an existing stream.  They declare the intent to use
            another stream for the pushing of a resource.  The PUSH_PROMISE allows the client an
            opportunity to reject pushed resources.
          </t>

          <figure title="PUSH_PROMISE Payload Format">
            <artwork type="inline">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|X|                Promised-Stream-ID (31)                      |
+-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
|                    Header Block (*)                         ...
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
</artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>
            There are no frame-specific flags for the PUSH_PROMISE frame.
          </t>

          <t>
            The body of a PUSH_PROMISE includes a "Promised-Stream-ID".  This 31-bit identifier
            indicates the stream on which the resource will be pushed.  The promised stream
            identifier MUST be a valid choice for the next stream sent by the sender (see <xref
            target="StreamCreation">new stream identifier</xref>).
          </t>

          <t>
            There is no requirement that the streams referred to by this frame are created in the
            order referenced.  The PUSH_PROMISE reserves stream identifiers for later use; these
            reserved identifiers can be used as prioritization needs dictate.
          </t>

          <t>
            The PUSH_PROMISE also includes a <xref target="HeaderBlock">header block</xref>, which
            describes the resource that will be pushed.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="PING" title="PING">
          <t>
            The PING frame (type=6) is a mechanism for measuring a minimal round-trip time from the
            sender.  PING frames can be sent from the client or the server.
          </t>
          <t>
            Receivers of a PING frame send an identical frame to the sender as soon as possible.
            PING should take highest priority if there is other data waiting to be sent.
          </t>
          <t>
            The PING frame defines a frame-specific flag:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="PONG (0x2):">
                Bit 2 being set indicates that this ping frame is a ping response.  An endpoint MUST
                set this flag in ping responses.  An endpoint MUST NOT respond to ping frames
                containing this flag.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            The payload of a PING frame contains any value.  A PING response MUST contain the
            contents of the PING request.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="GOAWAY" title="GOAWAY">
          <t>
            The GOAWAY frame (type=7) informs the remote side of the connection to stop creating
            streams on this session.  It can be sent from the client or the server. Once sent, the
            sender will ignore frames sent on new streams for the remainder of the
            session. Receivers of a GOAWAY frame MUST NOT open additional streams on the session,
            although a new session can be established for new streams.  The purpose of this message
            is to allow an endpoint to gracefully stop accepting new streams (perhaps for a reboot
            or maintenance), while still finishing processing of previously established streams.
          </t>
          <t>
            There is an inherent race condition between an endpoint starting new streams and the
            remote sending a GOAWAY message.  To deal with this case, the GOAWAY contains the stream
            identifier of the last stream which was processed on the sending endpoint in this
            session.  If the receiver of the GOAWAY used streams that are newer than the indicated
            stream identifier, they were not processed by the sender and the receiver may treat the
            streams as though they had never been created at all (hence the receiver may want to
            re-create the streams later on a new session).
          </t>
          <t>
            Endpoints should always send a GOAWAY message before closing a connection so that the
            remote can know whether a stream has been partially processed or not.  (For example, if
            an HTTP client sends a POST at the same time that a server closes a connection, the
            client cannot know if the server started to process that POST request if the server does
            not send a GOAWAY frame to indicate where it stopped working).
          </t>

          <t>
            After sending a GOAWAY message, the sender can ignore frames for new streams.
          </t>
          <t>
            <cref>Issue: session state that is established by those "ignored" messages cannot be
            ignored without the state in the two peers becoming unsynchronized.</cref>
          </t>

          <figure title="GOAWAY Payload Format">
            <artwork type="inline">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|X|                  Last-Stream-ID (31)                        |
+-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
|                      Error Code (32)                          |
+---------------------------------------------------------------+
</artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The GOAWAY frame does not define any valid flags.
          </t>
          <t>
            The GOAWAY frame applies to the session, not a specific stream.  The stream identifier
            MUST be zero.
          </t>
          <t>
            The GOAWAY frame contains an identifier of the last stream that the sender of the GOAWAY
            is prepared to act upon, which can include processing and replies.  This allows an
            endpoint to discover what streams might have had some effect or what might be safe to
            automatically retry.  If no streams were acted upon, the last stream ID MUST be 0.
          </t>
          <t>
            The GOAWAY frame contains a 32-bit <xref target="ErrorCodes">error code</xref> that
            contains the reason for closing the session.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="HEADERS" title="HEADERS">
          <t>
            The HEADERS frame (type=8) provides header fields for a stream. It may be optionally
            sent on an existing stream at any time.  Specific application of the headers in this
            frame is application-dependent.
          </t>
          <t>
            No frame-specific flags are defined for the HEADERS frame.
          </t>
          <t>
            The body of a HEADERS frame contains a <xref target="HeaderBlock">Headers Block</xref>.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="WINDOW_UPDATE" title="WINDOW_UPDATE">
          <t>
            The WINDOW_UPDATE frame (type=9) is used to implement flow control in HTTP/2.0.
          </t>
          <t>
            Flow control in HTTP/2.0 operates at two levels: on each individual stream and on the
            entire session.
          </t>
          <t>
            Flow control in HTTP/2.0 is hop by hop, that is, only between the two endpoints of a
            HTTP/2.0 connection. Intermediaries do not forward WINDOW_UPDATE messages between
            dependent sessions.  However, throttling of data transfer by any receiver can
            indirectly cause the propagation of flow control information toward the original
            sender.
          </t>
          <t>
            Flow control only applies to frames that are identified as being subject to flow
            control. Of the frames defined in this document, only data frames are subject to flow
            control.  Receivers MUST either buffer or process all other frames, terminate the
            corresponding stream, or terminate the session.  The stream or session is terminated
            with a FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR code.
          </t>
          <t>
            Valid flags for the WINDOW_UPDATE frame are:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="END_FLOW_CONTROL (0x2):">
                Bit 2 being set indicates that flow control for the identified stream or session is
                ended and subsequent frames do not need to be flow controlled.
              </t>
            </list>
        </t>
          <t>
             The WINDOW_UPDATE frame can be stream related or session related.  The stream
             identifier in the WINDOW_UPDATE frame header identifies the affected stream, or
             includes a value of 0 to indicate that the session flow control window is updated.
          </t>
          <t>
            The payload of a WINDOW_UPDATE frame contains a 32-bit value.  This value is the
            additional number of bytes that the sender can transmit in addition to the existing flow
            control window.  The legal range for this field is 1 to 2<x:sup>31</x:sup> - 1
            (0x7fffffff) bytes; the most significant bit of this value is reserved.
          </t>

          <section title="The Flow Control Window">
            <t>
              Flow control in HTTP/2.0 is implemented by a flow control window kept by the sender of
              each stream. The flow control window is a simple integer value that indicates how many
              bytes of data the sender is permitted to transmit.  The flow control window size is a
              measure of the buffering capability of the receiver.
            </t>
            <t>
              Two flow control windows apply to the sending of every message: the stream flow
              control window and the session flow control window.  The sender MUST NOT send a flow
              controlled frame with a length that exceeds the space available in either of the flow
              control windows advertised by the receiver.  Frames with zero length with the FINAL
              flag set (for example, an empty data frame) MAY be sent if there is no available space
              in either flow control window.
            </t>
            <t>
              For flow control calculations, the 8 byte frame header is not counted.
            </t>
            <t>
              After sending a flow controlled frame, the sender reduces the space available in both
              windows by the length of the transmitted frame.
            </t>
            <t>
              The receiver of a message sends a WINDOW_UPDATE frame as it consumes data and frees up
              space in flow control windows.  Separate WINDOW_UPDATE messages are sent for the
              stream and session level flow control windows.
            </t>
            <t>
              A sender that receives a WINDOW_UPDATE frame updates the corresponding window by the
              amount specified in the frame.
            </t>
            <t>
              A sender MUST NOT allow a flow control window to exceed 2<x:sup>31</x:sup> - 1 bytes.
              If a sender receives a WINDOW_UPDATE that causes a flow control window to exceed this
              maximum it MUST terminate either the stream or the session, as appropriate.  For
              streams, the sender sends a RST_STREAM with the error code of FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR code;
              for the session, a GOAWAY message with a FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR code.
            </t>
            <t>
              Flow controlled frames from the sender and WINDOW_UPDATE frames from the receiver are
              completely asynchronous with respect to each other. This property allows a receiver to
              aggressively update the window size kept by the sender to prevent streams from
              stalling.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Initial Flow Control Window Size">
            <t>
              When a HTTP/2.0 connection is first established, new streams are created with an
              initial flow control window size of 65535 bytes. The session flow control window is
              65536 bytes.  Both endpoints can adjust the initial window size for new streams by
              including a value for SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE in the SETTINGS frame that forms
              part of the session header.
            </t>
            <t>
              Prior to receiving a SETTINGS frame that sets a value for
              SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE, a client can only use the default initial window size
              when sending flow controlled frames.  Similarly, the session flow control window is
              set to the default initial window size until a WINDOW_UPDATE message is received.
            </t>
            <t>
              A SETTINGS frame can alter the initial flow control window size for all current
              streams. When the value of SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE changes, a receiver MUST
              adjust the size of all flow control windows that it maintains by the difference
              between the new value and the old value.
            </t>
            <t>
              A change to SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE could cause the available space in a flow
              control window to become negative.  A sender MUST track the negative flow control
              window and not send new flow controlled frames until it receives WINDOW_UPDATE
              messages that cause the flow control window to become positive.
            </t>
            <t>
              For example, if the server sets the initial window size to be 16KB, and the client
              sends 64KB immediately on connection establishment, the client will recalculate the
              available flow control window to be -48KB on receipt of the SETTINGS frame.  The
              client retains a negative flow control window until WINDOW_UPDATE frames restore the
              window to being positive, after which the client can resume sending.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Reducing the Stream Window Size">
            <t>
              A receiver that wishes to use a smaller flow control window than the current size
              sends a new SETTINGS frame.  However, the receiver MUST be prepared to receive data
              that exceeds this window size, since the sender might send data that exceeds the lower
              limit prior to processing the SETTINGS frame.
            </t>
            <t>
              A receiver has two options for handling streams that exceed flow control limits:
              <list style="numbers">
                <t>
                  The receiver can immediately send RST_STREAM with FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR error code
                  for the affected streams.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The receiver can accept the streams and tolerate the resulting head of line
                  blocking, sending WINDOW_UPDATE messages as it consumes data.
                </t>
              </list>
              If a receiver decides to accept streams, both sides must recompute the available flow
              control window based on the initial window size sent in the SETTINGS. 
            </t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="EndFlowControl" title="Ending Flow Control">
            <t>
              After a receiver reads in a frame that marks the end of a stream (for example, a data
              stream with a FINAL flag set), it ceases transmission of WINDOW_UPDATE frames. A
              sender is not required to maintain the available flow control window for streams that
              it is no longer sending on.
            </t>
            <t>
              Flow control can be disabled for all streams or the session using the
              SETTINGS_FLOW_CONTROL_OPTIONS setting.  An implementation that does not wish to
              perform flow control can use this in the initial SETTINGS exchange.
            </t>
            <t>
              Flow control can be disabled for an individual stream or the overall session by
              sending a WINDOW_UPDATE with the END_FLOW_CONTROL flag set.  The payload of a
              WINDOW_UPDATE frame that has the END_FLOW_CONTROL flag set is ignored.
            </t>
            <t>
              Flow control cannot be enabled again once disabled.  Any attempt to re-enable flow
              control - by sending a WINDOW_UPDATE or by clearing the bits on the
              SETTINGS_FLOW_CONTROL_OPTIONS setting - MUST be rejected with a FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR
              error code.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="HeaderBlock" title="Header Block">
          <t>
            The header block is found in the HEADERS, HEADERS+PRIORITY and PUSH_PROMISE frames.  The
            header block consists of a set of header fields, which are name-value pairs.  Headers
            are compressed using black magic.
          </t>
          <t>
            Compression of header fields is a work in progress, as is the format of this block.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="HTTPLayer" title="HTTP Message Exchanges">
      <t>
        HTTP/2.0 is intended to be as compatible as possible with current web-based
        applications. This means that, from the perspective of the server business logic or
        application API, the features of HTTP are unchanged. To achieve this, all of the application
        request and response header semantics are preserved, although the syntax of conveying those
        semantics has changed.  Thus, the rules from HTTP/1.1 (<xref target="HTTP-p1"/>, <xref
        target="HTTP-p2"/>, <xref target="HTTP-p4"/>, <xref target="HTTP-p5"/>, <xref
        target="HTTP-p6"/>, and <xref target="HTTP-p7"/>) apply with the changes in the sections
        below.
      </t>

      <section title="Connection Management">
        <t>
          Clients SHOULD NOT open more than one HTTP/2.0 session to a given origin
          (<xref target="RFC6454"/>) concurrently.
        </t>
        <t>
          Note that it is possible for one HTTP/2.0 session to be finishing (e.g. a GOAWAY message
          has been sent, but not all streams have finished), while another HTTP/2.0 session is
          starting.
        </t>

        <section title="Use of GOAWAY">
          <t>
            HTTP/2.0 provides a GOAWAY message which can be used when closing a connection from
            either the client or server.  Without a server GOAWAY message, HTTP has a race condition
            where the client sends a request just as the server is closing the connection, and the
            client cannot know if the server received the stream or not.  By using the
            last-stream-id in the GOAWAY, servers can indicate to the client if a request was
            processed or not.
          </t>

          <t>
            Note that some servers will choose to send the GOAWAY and immediately terminate the
            connection without waiting for active streams to finish.  The client will be able to
            determine this because HTTP/2.0 streams are deterministically closed.  This abrupt
            termination will force the client to heuristically decide whether to retry the pending
            requests.  Clients always need to be capable of dealing with this case because they must
            deal with accidental connection termination cases, which are the same as the server
            never having sent a GOAWAY.
          </t>

          <t>
            More sophisticated servers will use GOAWAY to implement a graceful teardown. They will
            send the GOAWAY and provide some time for the active streams to finish before
            terminating the connection.
          </t>

          <t>
            If a HTTP/2.0 client closes the connection, it should also send a GOAWAY message.  This
            allows the server to know if any server-push streams were received by the client.
          </t>

          <t>
            If the endpoint closing the connection has not received frames on any stream, the GOAWAY
            will contain a last-stream-id of 0.
          </t>

        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="HTTP Request/Response">

        <section title="HTTP Header Fields and HTTP/2.0 Headers">
          <t>
            At the application level, HTTP uses name-value pairs in its header fields.  Because
            HTTP/2.0 merges the existing HTTP header fields with HTTP/2.0 headers, there is a
            possibility that some HTTP applications already use a particular header field name.  To
            avoid any conflicts, all header fields introduced for layering HTTP over HTTP/2.0 are
            prefixed with ":".  ":" is not a valid sequence in HTTP/1.* header field naming,
            preventing any possible conflict.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="HttpRequest" title="Request">
          <t>
            The client initiates a request by sending a HEADERS+PRIORITY frame.  Requests that do
            not contain a body MUST set the FINAL flag, indicating that the client intends to send
            no further data on this stream, unless the server intends to push resources (see <xref
            target="PushResources"/>).  HEADERS+PRIORITY frame does not contain the FINAL flag for
            requests that contain a body.  The body of a request follows as a series of DATA
            frames. The last DATA frame sets the FINAL flag to indicate the end of the body.
          </t>

          <t>
            The header fields included in the HEADERS+PRIORITY frame contain all of the HTTP header
            fields that are associated with an HTTP request. The header block in HTTP/2.0 is mostly
            unchanged from today's HTTP header block, with the following differences:
            <list>
              <t>
                The following fields that are carried in the request line in HTTP/1.1 (<xref
                target="HTTP-p1" x:fmt="," x:rel="#request.line"/>) are defined as special-valued
                name-value pairs:
                <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="&quot;:method&quot;:">
                    the HTTP method for this request (e.g. "GET", "POST", "HEAD", etc)
                    (<xref target="HTTP-p2" x:fmt="," x:rel="#methods"/>)
                  </t>
                  <t hangText="&quot;:path&quot;:">
                    ":path" - the request-target for this URI with "/" prefixed (see <xref
                    target="HTTP-p1" x:fmt="," x:rel="#request.line"/>).  For example, for
                    "http://www.google.com/search?q=dogs" the path would be
                    "/search?q=dogs". <cref>what forms of the HTTPbis request-target are allowed
                    here?</cref>
                  </t>
                </list>
                These header fields MUST be present in HTTP requests.
              </t>
              <t>
                In addition, the following two name-value pairs MUST be present in every request:
                <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="&quot;:host&quot;:">
                    the host and optional port portions (see <xref target="RFC3986" x:fmt=","
                    x:sec="3.2"/>) of the URI for this request (e.g. "www.google.com:1234"). This
                    header field is the same as the HTTP 'Host' header field (<xref target="HTTP-p1"
                    x:fmt="," x:rel="#header.host"/>).
                  </t>
                  <t hangText="&quot;:scheme&quot;:">
                    the scheme portion of the URI for this request (e.g. "https")
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>
              <t>
                All header field names starting with ":" (whether defined in this document or future
                extensions to this document) MUST appear before any other header fields.
              </t>
              <t>
                Header field names MUST be all lowercase.
              </t>
              <t>
                The Connection, Host, Keep-Alive, Proxy-Connection, and Transfer-Encoding header
                fields are not valid and MUST not be sent.
              </t>
              <t>
                User-agents MUST support gzip compression. Regardless of the Accept-Encoding sent by
                the user-agent, the server may always send content encoded with gzip or deflate
                encoding.  <cref>Still valid?</cref>
              </t>
              <t>
                If a server receives a request where the sum of the data frame payload lengths does
                not equal the size of the Content-Length header field, the server MUST return a 400
                (Bad Request) error.
              </t>
              <t>
                Although POSTs are inherently chunked, POST requests SHOULD also be accompanied by a
                Content-Length header field.  First, it informs the server of how much data to
                expect, which the server can used to track overall progress and provide appropriate
                user feedback.  More importantly, some HTTP server implementations fail to correctly
                process requests that omit the Content-Length header field.  Many existing clients
                send a Content-Length header field, which caused server implementations have come to
                depend upon its presence.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            The user-agent is free to prioritize requests as it sees fit. If the user-agent cannot
            make progress without receiving a resource, it should attempt to raise the priority of
            that resource. Resources such as images, SHOULD generally use the lowest priority.
          </t>
          <t>
            If a client sends a HEADERS+PRIORITY frame that omits a mandatory header, the server
            MUST reply with a HTTP 400 Bad Request reply.  <cref>Ed: why PROTOCOL_ERROR on missing
            ":status" in the response, but HTTP 400 here?</cref>
          </t>
          <t>
            If the server receives a data frame prior to a HEADERS or HEADERS+PRIORITY frame the
            server MUST treat this as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of
            type PROTOCOL_ERROR.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="HttpResponse" title="Response">
          <t>
            The server responds to a client request with a HEADERS frame. Symmetric to the client's
            upload stream, server will send any response body in a series of DATA frames.  The last
            data frame will contain the FINAL flag to indicate the end of the stream and the end of
            the response.  A response that contains no body (such as a 204 or 304 response) consists
            only of a HEADERS frame that contains the FINAL flag to indicate no further data will be
            sent on the stream.
          </t>

          <t>
            <list>
              <t>
                The response status line is unfolded into name-value pairs like other HTTP header
                fields and must be present:
                <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="&quot;:status&quot;:">
                    The HTTP response status code (e.g. "200" or "200 OK")
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>
              <t>
                All header field names starting with ":" (whether defined in this document or future
                extensions to this document) MUST appear before any other header fields.
              </t>
              <t>
                All header field names MUST be all lowercase.
              </t>
              <t>
                The Connection, Keep-Alive, Proxy-Connection, and Transfer-Encoding header fields
                are not valid and MUST not be sent.
              </t>
              <t>
                Responses MAY be accompanied by a Content-Length header field for advisory purposes.
                This allows clients to learn the full size of an entity prior to receiving all the
                data frames.  This can help in, for example, reporting progress.
              </t>
              <t>
                If a client receives a response where the sum of the data frame payload length does
                not equal the size of the Content-Length header field, the client MUST ignore the
                content length header field. <cref>Ed: See <eref
                target="https://github.com/http2/http2-spec/issues/46">issue 46</eref>.</cref>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            If a client receives a response with an absent or duplicated status header, the client
            MUST treat this as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type
            PROTOCOL_ERROR.
          </t>

          <t>
            If the client receives a data frame prior to a HEADERS or HEADERS+PRIORITY frame the
            client MUST treat this as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of
            type PROTOCOL_ERROR.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="PushResources" title="Server Push Transactions">
        <t>
          HTTP/2.0 enables a server to send multiple replies to a client for a single request.  The
          rationale for this feature is that sometimes a server knows that it will need to send
          multiple resources in response to a single request.  Without server push features, the
          client must first download the primary resource, then discover the secondary resource(s),
          and request them.  Pushing of resources avoids the round-trip delay, but also creates a
          potential race where a server can be pushing content which a user-agent is in the process
          of requesting.  The following mechanics attempt to prevent the race condition while
          enabling the performance benefit.
        </t>

        <t>
          Server push is an optional feature.  Server push can be disabled by clients that do not
          wish to receive pushed resources by advertising a SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS <xref
          target="SETTINGS">SETTING</xref> of zero.  This prevents servers from creating the streams
          necessary to push resources.
        </t>

        <t>
          Browsers receiving a pushed response MUST validate that the server is authorized to push
          the resource using the same-origin policy (<xref target="RFC6454" x:fmt="," x:sec="3"/>).
          For example, a HTTP/2.0 connection to <spanx style="verb">example.com</spanx> is generally
          <cref>Ed: weaselly use of "generally", needs better definition</cref> not permitted to
          push a response for <spanx style="verb">www.example.org</spanx>.
        </t>

        <t>
          A client that accepts pushed resources caches those resources as though they were
          responses to GET requests.
        </t>

        <t>
           Pushed responses are associated with a request at the HTTP/2.0 framing layer.  The
           PUSH_PROMISE includes a stream identifier for an associated request/response exchange
           that supplies request header fields.  The pushed stream inherits all of the request
           header fields from the associated stream with the exception of resource identification
           header fields (<spanx style="verb">:host</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">:scheme</spanx>,
           and <spanx style="verb">:path</spanx>), which are provided as part of the PUSH_PROMISE
           frame.  Pushed resources always have an associated <spanx style="verb">:method</spanx> of
           <spanx style="verb">GET</spanx>.  A cache MUST store these inherited and implied request
           header fields with the cached resource.
        </t>

        <t>
          Implementation note: With server push, it is theoretically possible for servers to push
          unreasonable amounts of content or resources to the user-agent.  Browsers MUST implement
          throttles to protect against unreasonable push attacks.  <cref>Ed: insufficiently
          specified to implement; would like to remove</cref>
        </t>

        <section title="Server implementation">
          <t>
            A server pushes resources in association with a request from the client.  Prior to
            closing the response stream, the server sends a PUSH_PROMISE for each resource that it
            intends to push.  The PUSH_PROMISE includes header fields that allow the client to
            identify the resource (<spanx style="verb">:scheme</spanx>, <spanx
            style="verb">:host</spanx>, and <spanx style="verb">:port</spanx>).  
          </t>
          <t>
            A server can push multiple resources in response to a request, but these can only be
            sent while the response stream remains open.  A server MUST NOT send a PUSH_PROMISE on a
            half-closed stream.
          </t>
          <t>
            The server SHOULD include any header fields in a PUSH_PROMISE that would allow a cache
            to determine if the resource is already cached (see <xref target="HTTP-p6" x:fmt=","
            x:sec="4"/>).
          </t>
          
          <t>
            After sending a PUSH_PROMISE, the server commences transmission of a pushed resource.  A
            pushed resource uses a server-initiated stream.  The server sends frames on this stream
            in the same order as an <xref target="HttpResponse">HTTP response</xref>: a HEADERS
            frame followed by DATA frames.
          </t>

          <t>
            Many uses of server push are to send content that a client is likely to discover a need
            for based on the content of a response representation.  To minimize the chances that a
            client will make a request for resources that are being pushed - causing duplicate
            copies of a resource to be sent by the server - a PUSH_PROMISE frame SHOULD be sent
            prior to any content in the response representation that might allow a client to
            discover the pushed resource and request it.
          </t>

          <t>
            The server MUST only push resources that could have been returned from a GET request.
          </t>

          <t>
            Note: A server does not need to have all response header fields available at the time it
            issues a PUSH_PROMISE frame.  All remaining header fields are included in the HEADERS
            frame.  The HEADERS frame MUST NOT duplicate header fields from the PUSH_PROMISE frames.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Client implementation">
          <t>
            When fetching a resource the client has 3 possibilities:
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                the resource is not being pushed
              </t>
              <t>
                the resource is being pushed, but the data has not yet arrived
              </t>
              <t>
                the resource is being pushed, and the data has started to arrive
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>
            When a HEADERS+PRIORITY frame that contains an Associated-To-Stream-ID is received, the
            client MUST NOT<cref>SHOULD NOT?</cref> issue GET requests for the resource in the
            pushed stream, and instead wait for the pushed stream to arrive.
          </t>


          <t>
            A server MUST NOT push a resource with an Associated-To-Stream-ID of 0.  Clients MUST
            treat this as a <xref target="SessionErrorHandler">session error</xref> of type
            PROTOCOL_ERROR.
          </t>

          <t>
            When a client receives a PUSH_PROMISE frame from the server without a the <spanx
            style="verb">:host</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">:scheme</spanx>, and <spanx
            style="verb">:path</spanx> header fields, it MUST treat this as a <xref
            target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type PROTOCOL_ERROR.
          </t>

          <t>
            To cancel individual server push streams, the client can issue a <xref
            target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type CANCEL.  Upon receipt, the
            server ceases transmission of the pushed data.
          </t> 

          <t>
            To cancel all server push streams related to a request, the client may issue a <xref
            target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type CANCEL on the
            associated-stream-id.  By cancelling that stream, the server MUST immediately stop
            sending frames for any streams with in-association-to for the original stream.
            <cref>Ed: Triggering side-effects on stream reset is going to be problematic for the
            framing layer.  Purely from a design perspective, it's a layering violation.  More
            practically speaking, the base request stream might already be removed.  Special
            handling logic would be required.</cref>
          </t>

          <t>
            If the server sends a HEADERS frame containing header fields that duplicate values on a
            previous HEADERS or PUSH_PROMISE frames on the same stream, the client MUST treat this
            as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type PROTOCOL_ERROR.
          </t>

          <t>
            If the server sends a HEADERS frame after sending a data frame for the same stream, the
            client MAY ignore the HEADERS frame.  Ignoring the HEADERS frame after a data frame
            prevents handling of HTTP's trailing header fields (<xref target="HTTP-p1" x:fmt="of"
            x:rel="#header.trailer"/>).
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Design Rationale and Notes">
      <t>
        Authors' notes: The notes in this section have no bearing on the HTTP/2.0 protocol as
        specified within this document, and none of these notes should be considered authoritative
        about how the protocol works.  However, these notes may prove useful in future debates about
        how to resolve protocol ambiguities or how to evolve the protocol going forward.  They may
        be removed before the final draft.
      </t>

      <section title="Separation of Framing Layer and Application Layer">
        <t>
          Readers may note that this specification sometimes blends the <xref
          target="FramingLayer">framing layer</xref> with requirements of a specific application -
          <xref target="HTTPLayer">HTTP</xref>.  This is reflected in the request/response nature of
          the streams and the definition of the HEADERS which are very similar to HTTP, and other
          areas as well.
        </t>

        <t>
          This blending is intentional - the primary goal of this protocol is to create a
          low-latency protocol for use with HTTP.  Isolating the two layers is convenient for
          description of the protocol and how it relates to existing HTTP implementations.  However,
          the ability to reuse the HTTP/2.0 framing layer is a non goal.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Error handling - Framing Layer">
        <t>
          Error handling at the HTTP/2.0 layer splits errors into two groups: Those that affect an
          individual HTTP/2.0 stream, and those that do not.
        </t>

        <t>
          When an error is confined to a single stream, but general framing is in tact, HTTP/2.0
          attempts to use the RST_STREAM as a mechanism to invalidate the stream but move forward
          without aborting the connection altogether.
        </t>

        <t>
          For errors occurring outside of a single stream context, HTTP/2.0 assumes the entire
          session is hosed.  In this case, the endpoint detecting the error should initiate a
          connection close.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="One Connection Per Domain">
        <t>
          HTTP/2.0 attempts to use fewer connections than other protocols have traditionally used.
          The rationale for this behavior is because it is very difficult to provide a consistent
          level of service (e.g. TCP slow-start), prioritization, or optimal compression when the
          client is connecting to the server through multiple channels.
        </t>

        <t>
          Through lab measurements, we have seen consistent latency benefits by using fewer
          connections from the client.  The overall number of packets sent by HTTP/2.0 can be as
          much as 40% less than HTTP.  Handling large numbers of concurrent connections on the
          server also does become a scalability problem, and HTTP/2.0 reduces this load.
        </t>

        <t>
          The use of multiple connections is not without benefit, however.  Because HTTP/2.0
          multiplexes multiple, independent streams onto a single stream, it creates a potential for
          head-of-line blocking problems at the transport level.  In tests so far, the negative
          effects of head-of-line blocking (especially in the presence of packet loss) is outweighed
          by the benefits of compression and prioritization.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Fixed vs Variable Length Fields">
        <t>
          HTTP/2.0 favors use of fixed length 32bit fields in cases where smaller, variable length
          encodings could have been used.  To some, this seems like a tragic waste of bandwidth.
          HTTP/2.0 chooses the simple encoding for speed and simplicity.
        </t>

        <t>
          The goal of HTTP/2.0 is to reduce latency on the network.  The overhead of HTTP/2.0 frames
          is generally quite low.  Each data frame is only an 8 byte overhead for a 1452 byte
          payload (~0.6%).  At the time of this writing, bandwidth is already plentiful, and there
          is a strong trend indicating that bandwidth will continue to increase.  With an average
          worldwide bandwidth of 1Mbps, and assuming that a variable length encoding could reduce
          the overhead by 50%, the latency saved by using a variable length encoding would be less
          than 100 nanoseconds.  More interesting are the effects when the larger encodings force a
          packet boundary, in which case a round-trip could be induced.  However, by addressing
          other aspects of HTTP/2.0 and TCP interactions, we believe this is completely mitigated.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Server Push">
        <t>
          A subtle but important point is that server push streams must be declared before the
          associated stream is closed.  The reason for this is so that proxies have a lifetime for
          which they can discard information about previous streams.  If a pushed stream could
          associate itself with an already-closed stream, then endpoints would not have a specific
          lifecycle for when they could disavow knowledge of the streams which went before.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <section title="Use of Same-origin constraints">
        <t>
          This specification uses the same-origin policy (<xref target="RFC6454" x:fmt=","
          x:sec="3"/>) in all cases where verification of content is required.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Cross-Protocol Attacks">
        <t>
          By utilizing TLS, we believe that HTTP/2.0 introduces no new cross-protocol attacks.  TLS
          encrypts the contents of all transmission (except the handshake itself), making it
          difficult for attackers to control the data which could be used in a cross-protocol
          attack.  <cref>Issue: This is no longer true</cref>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Cacheability of Pushed Resources">
        <t>
          Pushed resources do not have an associated request.  In order for existing HTTP cache
          control validations (such as the Vary header field) to work, all cached resources must
          have a set of request header fields.  For this reason, caches MUST be careful to inherit
          request header fields from the associated stream for the push.  This includes the Cookie
          header field.
        </t>
        <t>
          Caching resources that are pushed is possible, based on the guidance provided by the
          origin server in the Cache-Control header field.  However, this can cause issues if a
          single server hosts more than one tenant.  For example, a server might offer multiple
          users each a small portion of its URI space.
        </t>
        <t>
          Where multiple tenants share space on the same server, that server MUST ensure that
          tenants are not able to push representations of resources that they do not have authority
          over.  Failure to enforce this would allow a tenant to provide a representation that would
          be served out of cache, overriding the actual representation that the authoritative tenant
          provides.
        </t>
        <t>
          Pushed resources for which an origin server is not authoritative are never cached or used.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Privacy Considerations">
      <section title="Long Lived Connections">
        <t>
          HTTP/2.0 aims to keep connections open longer between clients and servers in order to
          reduce the latency when a user makes a request.  The maintenance of these connections over
          time could be used to expose private information.  For example, a user using a browser
          hours after the previous user stopped using that browser may be able to learn about what
          the previous user was doing.  This is a problem with HTTP in its current form as well,
          however the short lived connections make it less of a risk.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="SETTINGS frame">
        <t>
          The HTTP/2.0 SETTINGS frame allows servers to store out-of-band transmitted information
          about the communication between client and server on the client.  Although this is
          intended only to be used to reduce latency, renegade servers could use it as a mechanism
          to store identifying information about the client in future requests.
        </t>

        <t>
          Clients implementing privacy modes can disable client-persisted SETTINGS storage.
        </t>

        <t>
          Clients MUST clear persisted SETTINGS information when clearing the cookies.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This document establishes registries for frame types, error codes and settings.
      </t>
      <section title="Frame Type Registry">
        <t>
          This document establishes a registry for HTTP/2.0 frame types.  The "HTTP/2.0 Frame Type"
          registry operates under the <xref target="RFC5226">"IETF Review" policy</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Frame types are an 8-bit value.  When reviewing new frame type registrations, special
          attention is advised for any frame type-specific flags that are defined.  Frame flags can
          interact with existing flags and could prevent the creation of globally applicable flags.
        </t>
        <t>
          Initial values for the "HTTP/2.0 Frame Type" registry are shown in <xref
          target="IanaInitialFrameType"/>.
        </t>
        <texttable anchor="IanaInitialFrameType">
          <ttcol>Frame Type</ttcol><ttcol>Name</ttcol><ttcol>Flags</ttcol>
          <c>0</c><c>DATA</c><c>-</c>
          <c>1</c><c>HEADERS+PRIORITY</c><c>-</c>
          <c>3</c><c>RST_STREAM</c><c>-</c>
          <c>4</c><c>SETTINGS</c><c>CLEAR_PERSISTED(2)</c>
          <c>5</c><c>PUSH_PROMISE</c><c>-</c>
          <c>6</c><c>PING</c><c>PONG(2)</c>
          <c>7</c><c>GOAWAY</c><c>-</c>
          <c>8</c><c>HEADERS</c><c>-</c>
          <c>9</c><c>WINDOW_UPDATE</c><c>END_FLOW_CONTROL(2)</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="Error Code Registry">
        <t>
          This document establishes a registry for HTTP/2.0 error codes.  The "HTTP/2.0 Error Code"
          registry manages a 32-bit space.  The "HTTP/2.0 Error Code" registry operates under the
          <xref target="RFC5226">"Expert Review" policy</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Registrations for error codes are required to include a description of the error code.  An
          expert reviewer is advised to examine new registrations for possible duplication with
          existing error codes.  Use of existing registrations is to be encouraged, but not
          mandated.
        </t>
        <t>
          New registrations are advised to provide the following information:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Error Code:">
              The 32-bit error code value.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Name:">
              A name for the error code.  Specifying an error code name is optional.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Description:">
              A description of the conditions where the error code is applicable.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Specification:">
              An optional reference for a specification that defines the error code.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          An initial set of error code registrations can be found in <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Settings Registry">
        <t>
          This document establishes a registry for HTTP/2.0 settings.  The "HTTP/2.0 Settings"
          registry manages a 24-bit space.  The "HTTP/2.0 Settings" registry operates under the
          <xref target="RFC5226">"Expert Review" policy</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Registrations for settings are required to include a description of the setting.  An
          expert reviewer is advised to examine new registrations for possible duplication with
          existing settings.  Use of existing registrations is to be encouraged, but not mandated.
        </t>
        <t>
          New registrations are advised to provide the following information:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Setting:">
              The 24-bit setting value.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Name:">
              A name for the setting.  Specifying a name is optional.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Flags:">
              Any setting-specific flags that apply, including their value and semantics.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Description:">
              A description of the setting.  This might include the range of values, any applicable
              units and how to act upon a value when it is provided.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Specification:">
              An optional reference for a specification that defines the setting.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          An initial set of settings registrations can be found in <xref target="SETTINGS"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        This document includes substantial input from the following individuals:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Adam Langley, Wan-Teh Chang, Jim Morrison, Mark Nottingham, Alyssa Wilk, Costin
            Manolache, William Chan, Vitaliy Lvin, Joe Chan, Adam Barth, Ryan Hamilton, Gavin
            Peters, Kent Alstad, Kevin Lindsay, Paul Amer, Fan Yang, Jonathan Leighton (SPDY
            contributors).
          </t>
          <t>
            Gabriel Montenegro and Willy Tarreau (Upgrade mechanism)
          </t>
          <t>
            William Chan, Salvatore Loreto, Osama Mazahir, Gabriel Montenegro, Jitu Padhye, Roberto
            Peon, Rob Trace (Flow control)
          </t>
          <t>
            Mark Nottingham and Julian Reschke
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

      <reference anchor="RFC0793">
        <front>
          <title abbrev='Transmission Control Protocol'>
            Transmission Control Protocol
          </title>
          <author initials='J.' surname='Postel' fullname='Jon Postel'>
            <organization>University of Southern California (USC)/Information Sciences
            Institute</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='1981' month='September' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='STD' value='7' />
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='793' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>
            Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels
          </title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
            <address><email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1997"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3986">
        <front>
          <title abbrev='URI Generic Syntax'>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic
          Syntax</title>
          <author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'></author>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'></author>
          <author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'></author>
          <date year='2005' month='January' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='STD' value='66' />
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5226">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Narten" fullname="T. Narten">
          <organization /></author>
          <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="H. Alvestrand">
          <organization /></author>
          <date year="2008" month="May" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="26" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5226" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5246">
        <front>
          <title>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Dierks" fullname="Tim Dierks"/>
          <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="Eric Rescorla"/>
          <date year="2008" month="August" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5246" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC6454">
        <front>
          <title>The Web Origin Concept</title>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Barth' fullname='A. Barth'/>
          <date year='2011' month='December' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6454' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TLSNPN">
        <front>
          <title>Transport Layer Security (TLS) Next Protocol Negotiation Extension</title>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Langley' fullname='Adam Langley'></author>
          <date month='May' year='2012' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-agl-tls-nextprotoneg-04' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='HTTP-p1'>
        <front>
          <title>
          Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Message Syntax and Routing</title>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy Fielding'></author>
          <author initials='J.' surname='Reschke' fullname='Julian Reschke'></author>
          <date month='February' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging-22' />
        <x:source href="refs/draft-ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging-22.xml" basename="https://svn.tools.ietf.org/svn/wg/httpbis/draft-ietf-httpbis/22/p1-messaging"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor='HTTP-p2'>
        <front>
          <title>
          Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Semantics and Content</title>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy Fielding'></author>
          <author initials='J.' surname='Reschke' fullname='Julian Reschke'></author>
          <date month='February' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-httpbis-p2-semantics-22' />
        <x:source href="refs/draft-ietf-httpbis-p2-semantics-22.xml" basename="https://svn.tools.ietf.org/svn/wg/httpbis/draft-ietf-httpbis/22/p2-semantics"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="HTTP-p4">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Conditional Requests</title>
          <author fullname="Roy T. Fielding" initials="R." role="editor" surname="Fielding">
            <organization abbrev="Adobe">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
            <address><email>fielding@gbiv.com</email></address>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Julian F. Reschke" initials="J. F." role="editor" surname="Reschke">
            <organization abbrev="greenbytes">greenbytes GmbH</organization>
            <address><email>julian.reschke@greenbytes.de</email></address>
          </author>
          <date month='February' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-p4-conditional-22" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="HTTP-p5">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Range Requests</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding" role="editor">
            <organization abbrev="Adobe">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
            <address><email>fielding@gbiv.com</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Lafon" fullname="Yves Lafon" role="editor">
            <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
            <address><email>ylafon@w3.org</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="J. F." surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian F. Reschke" role="editor">
            <organization abbrev="greenbytes">greenbytes GmbH</organization>
            <address><email>julian.reschke@greenbytes.de</email></address>
          </author>
          <date month='February' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-p5-range-22"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="HTTP-p6">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Caching</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding" role="editor">
            <organization abbrev="Adobe">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
            <address><email>fielding@gbiv.com</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham" role="editor">
            <organization>Akamai</organization>
            <address><email>mnot@mnot.net</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="J. F." surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian F. Reschke" role="editor">
            <organization abbrev="greenbytes">greenbytes GmbH</organization>
            <address><email>julian.reschke@greenbytes.de</email></address>
          </author>
          <date month='February' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-p6-cache-22"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="HTTP-p7">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Authentication</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding" role="editor">
            <organization abbrev="Adobe">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
            <address><email>fielding@gbiv.com</email></address>
          </author>
          <author initials="J. F." surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian F. Reschke" role="editor">
            <organization abbrev="greenbytes">greenbytes GmbH</organization>
            <address><email>julian.reschke@greenbytes.de</email></address>
          </author>
          <date month='February' year='2013' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-p7-auth-22"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC1323">
        <front>
          <title>
            TCP Extensions for High Performance
          </title>
          <author initials='V.' surname='Jacobson' fullname='Van Jacobson'></author>
          <author initials='B.' surname='Braden' fullname='Bob Braden'></author>
          <author initials='D.' surname='Borman' fullname='Dave Borman'></author>
          <date year='1992' month='May' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1323' />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="TALKING" target="http://w2spconf.com/2011/papers/websocket.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>
            Talking to Yourself for Fun and Profit
          </title>
          <author initials="L-S." surname="Huang"/>
          <author initials="E." surname="Chen"/>
          <author initials="A." surname="Barth"/>
          <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla"/>
          <author initials="C." surname="Jackson"/>
          <date year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Change Log (to be removed by RFC Editor before publication)" anchor="change.log">

      <section title="Since draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-02" anchor="changes.since.draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-02">
        <t>
          None yet...
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Since draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-01" anchor="changes.since.draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-01">
        <t>
          Added IANA considerations section for frame types, error codes and settings.
        </t>
        <t>
          Removed data frame compression.
        </t>
        <t>
          Added PUSH_PROMISE.
        </t>
        <t>
          Added globally applicable flags to framing.
        </t>
        <t>
          Removed zlib-based header compression mechanism.
        </t>
        <t>
          Updated references.
        </t>
        <t>
          Clarified stream identifier reuse.
        </t>
        <t>
          Removed CREDENTIALS frame and associated mechanisms.
        </t>
        <t>
          Added advice against naive implementation of flow control.
        </t>
        <t>
          Added session header section.
        </t>
        <t>
          Restructured frame header.  Removed distinction between data and control frames.
        </t>
        <t>
          Altered flow control properties to include session-level limits.
        </t>
        <t>
          Added note on cacheability of pushed resources and multiple tenant servers.
        </t>
        <t>
          Changed protocol label form based on discussions.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Since draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-00" anchor="changes.since.draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-00">
        <t>
          Changed title throughout.
        </t>
        <t>
          Removed section on Incompatibilities with SPDY draft#2.
        </t>
        <t>
          Changed INTERNAL_ERROR on GOAWAY to have a value of 2 <eref
          target="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!topic/spdy-dev/cfUef2gL3iU"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Replaced abstract and introduction.
        </t>
        <t>
          Added section on starting HTTP/2.0, including upgrade mechanism.
        </t>
        <t>
          Removed unused references.
        </t>
        <t>
          Added <xref target="fc-principles">flow control principles</xref> based on <eref
          target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-montenegro-httpbis-http2-fc-principles-01"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Since draft-mbelshe-httpbis-spdy-00" anchor="changes.since.draft-mbelshe-httpbis-spdy-00">
        <t>
          Adopted as base for draft-ietf-httpbis-http2.
        </t>
        <t>
          Updated authors/editors list.
        </t>
        <t>
          Added status note.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>

