<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lib/rfc2629.xslt"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext" ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-httpbis-http2bis-latest" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3" submissionType="IETF" obsoletes="7540,8740">
  <!--
  <x:feedback template="mailto:ietf-http-wg@w3.org?subject={docname},%20%22{section}%22&amp;body=&lt;{ref}&gt;:"/>
  -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="HTTP/2">Hypertext Transfer Protocol Version 2 (HTTP/2)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-http2bis-latest"/>
    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson" role="editor">
      <organization>Mozilla</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mt@lowentropy.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Benfield" fullname="Cory Benfield" role="editor">
      <organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>cbenfield@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>
    <workgroup>HTTPbis</workgroup>
    <keyword>HTTP</keyword>
    <keyword>SPDY</keyword>
    <keyword>Web</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This specification describes an optimized expression of the semantics of the Hypertext
        Transfer Protocol (HTTP), referred to as HTTP version 2 (HTTP/2). HTTP/2 enables a more
        efficient use of network resources and a
        reduced perception of latency by introducing header field compression and allowing multiple
        concurrent exchanges on the same connection.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification is an alternative to, but does not obsolete, the HTTP/1.1 message syntax.
        HTTP's existing semantics remain unchanged.  This document obsoletes RFC 7540 and RFC 8740.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Discussion Venues" removeInRFC="true">
      <t>
        Discussion of this document takes place on the HTTPBIS Working Group mailing list
        (ietf-http-wg@w3.org), which is archived at <eref
        target="https://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/ietf-http-wg/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at
        <eref target="https://github.com/httpwg/http2-spec"/>.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a wildly successful protocol. However, the way
        HTTP/1.1 uses the underlying transport (<xref target="HTTP11"/>) has several
        characteristics that have a negative overall effect on application performance today.
      </t>
      <t>
        In particular, HTTP/1.0 allowed only one request to be outstanding at a time on a given TCP
        connection. HTTP/1.1 added request pipelining, but this only partially addressed request
        concurrency and still suffers from head-of-line blocking. Therefore, HTTP/1.0 and HTTP/1.1
        clients that need to make many requests use multiple connections to a server in order to
        achieve concurrency and thereby reduce latency.
      </t>
      <t>
        Furthermore, HTTP header fields are often repetitive and verbose, causing unnecessary
        network traffic as well as causing the initial TCP <xref target="TCP"/> congestion
        window to quickly fill. This can result in excessive latency when multiple requests are
        made on a new TCP connection.
      </t>
      <t>
        HTTP/2 addresses these issues by defining an optimized mapping of HTTP's semantics to an
        underlying connection. Specifically, it allows interleaving of request and response
        messages on the same connection and uses an efficient coding for HTTP header fields. It
        also allows prioritization of requests, letting more important requests complete more
        quickly, further improving performance.
      </t>
      <t>
        The resulting protocol is more friendly to the network because fewer TCP connections can
        be used in comparison to HTTP/1.x. This means less competition with other flows and
        longer-lived connections, which in turn lead to better utilization of available network
        capacity.
      </t>
      <t>
        Finally, HTTP/2 also enables more efficient processing of messages through use of binary
        message framing.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document obsoletes <xref target="RFC7540">RFC 7540</xref> and <xref
        target="RFC8740">RFC 8740</xref>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Overview">
      <name>HTTP/2 Protocol Overview</name>
      <t>
        HTTP/2 provides an optimized transport for HTTP semantics.  HTTP/2 supports all of the core
        features of HTTP but aims to be more efficient than HTTP/1.1.
      </t>
      <t>
        The basic protocol unit in HTTP/2 is a <xref target="FrameHeader">frame</xref>.  Each frame
        type serves a different purpose.  For example, <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> and
        <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames form the basis of <xref target="HttpSequence">HTTP requests and
        responses</xref>; other frame types like <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref>,
        <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref>, and <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> are used in support of other
        HTTP/2 features.
      </t>
      <t>
        Multiplexing of requests is achieved by having each HTTP request/response exchange
        associated with its own <xref target="StreamsLayer">stream</xref>. Streams are largely
        independent of each other, so a blocked or stalled request or response does not prevent
        progress on other streams.
      </t>
      <t>
        Flow control and prioritization ensure that it is possible to efficiently use multiplexed
        streams.  <xref target="FlowControl">Flow control</xref> helps to ensure that only data that
        can be used by a receiver is transmitted.  <xref target="StreamPriority">Prioritization</xref> ensures that limited resources can be directed
        to the most important streams first.
      </t>
      <t>
        Because HTTP header fields used in a connection can contain large amounts of redundant
        data, frames that contain them are <xref target="FieldBlock">compressed</xref>. This has
        especially advantageous impact upon request sizes in the common case, allowing many
        requests to be compressed into one packet.
      </t>
      <t>
        Finally, HTTP/2 adds a new, optional interaction mode whereby a server can <xref target="PushResources">push
        responses to a client</xref>.  This is intended to allow a server to speculatively send data to a
        client that the server anticipates the client will need, trading off some network usage
        against a potential latency gain.  The server does this by synthesizing a request, which it
        sends as a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame.  The server is then able to send a response to
        the synthetic request on a separate stream.
      </t>
      <section>
        <name>Document Organization</name>
        <t>
          The HTTP/2 specification is split into four parts:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li><xref target="starting">Starting HTTP/2</xref> covers how an HTTP/2 connection is
              initiated.
            </li>
          <li>
              The <xref target="FramingLayer">frame</xref> and <xref target="StreamsLayer">stream</xref> layers describe the way HTTP/2 frames are
              structured and formed into multiplexed streams.
            </li>
          <li><xref target="FrameTypes">Frame</xref> and <xref target="ErrorCodes">error</xref>
              definitions include details of the frame and error types used in HTTP/2.
            </li>
          <li><xref target="HTTPLayer">HTTP mappings</xref> and <xref target="HttpExtra">additional
              requirements</xref> describe how HTTP semantics are expressed using frames and
              streams.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          While some of the frame and stream layer concepts are isolated from HTTP, this
          specification does not define a completely generic frame layer. The frame and stream
          layers are tailored to the needs of the HTTP protocol and server push.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Conventions and Terminology</name>
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
          NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          All numeric values are in network byte order.  Values are unsigned unless otherwise
          indicated.  Literal values are provided in decimal or hexadecimal as appropriate.
          Hexadecimal literals are prefixed with <tt>0x</tt> to distinguish them
          from decimal literals.
        </t>
        <t>
          The following terms are used:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>client:</dt>
          <dd>
              The endpoint that initiates an HTTP/2 connection.  Clients send HTTP requests and
              receive HTTP responses.
            </dd>
          <dt>connection:</dt>
          <dd>
              A transport-layer connection between two endpoints.
            </dd>
          <dt>connection error:</dt>
          <dd>
              An error that affects the entire HTTP/2 connection.
            </dd>
          <dt>endpoint:</dt>
          <dd>
              Either the client or server of the connection.
            </dd>
          <dt>frame:</dt>
          <dd>
              The smallest unit of communication within an HTTP/2 connection, consisting of a header
              and a variable-length sequence of octets structured according to the frame type.
            </dd>
          <dt>peer:</dt>
          <dd>
              An endpoint.  When discussing a particular endpoint, "peer" refers to the endpoint
              that is remote to the primary subject of discussion.
            </dd>
          <dt>receiver:</dt>
          <dd>
              An endpoint that is receiving frames.
            </dd>
          <dt>sender:</dt>
          <dd>
              An endpoint that is transmitting frames.
            </dd>
          <dt>server:</dt>
          <dd>
              The endpoint that accepts an HTTP/2 connection.  Servers receive HTTP requests and
              send HTTP responses.
            </dd>
          <dt>stream:</dt>
          <dd>
              A bidirectional flow of frames within the HTTP/2 connection.
            </dd>
          <dt>stream error:</dt>
          <dd>
              An error on the individual HTTP/2 stream.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          Finally, the terms "gateway", "intermediary", "proxy", and "tunnel" are defined in
          <xref target="HTTP" section="3.7"/>.  Intermediaries act as both client
          and server at different times.
        </t>
        <t>
          The term "content" as it applies to message bodies is defined in <xref target="HTTP"
          section="6.4"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="starting">
      <name>Starting HTTP/2</name>
      <t>
        An HTTP/2 connection is an application-layer protocol running on top of a TCP connection
        (<xref target="TCP"/>). The client is the TCP connection initiator.
      </t>
      <t>
        HTTP/2 uses the "http" and "https" URI schemes defined in <xref target="HTTP" section="4.2"/>. HTTP/2 shares the same
        default port numbers: 80 for "http" URIs and 443 for "https" URIs.  As a result,
        implementations processing requests for target resource URIs like <tt>http://example.org/foo</tt> or <tt>https://example.com/bar</tt> are required to first discover whether the
        upstream server (the immediate peer to which the client wishes to establish a connection)
        supports HTTP/2.
      </t>
      <t>
        The means by which support for HTTP/2 is determined is different for "http" and "https"
        URIs. Discovery for "http" URIs is described in <xref target="discover-http"/>.  Discovery
        for "https" URIs is described in <xref target="discover-https"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="versioning">
        <name>HTTP/2 Version Identification</name>
        <t>
          The protocol defined in this document has two identifiers.
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>
                The string "h2" identifies the protocol where HTTP/2 uses <xref target="TLS13">Transport Layer Security (TLS)</xref>.  This identifier is used in the <xref target="TLS-ALPN">TLS application-layer protocol negotiation (ALPN) extension</xref>
                field and in any place where HTTP/2 over TLS is identified.
            </t>
            <t>
                The "h2" string is serialized into an ALPN protocol identifier as the two-octet
                sequence: 0x68, 0x32.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
                The string "h2c" identifies the protocol where HTTP/2 is run over cleartext TCP.
                This identifier is used in the HTTP/1.1 Upgrade header field and in any place where
                HTTP/2 over TCP is identified.
            </t>
            <t>
                The "h2c" string is reserved from the ALPN identifier space but describes a
                protocol that does not use TLS.
            </t>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          Negotiating "h2" or "h2c" implies the use of the transport, security, framing, and message
          semantics described in this document.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="discover-http">
        <name>Starting HTTP/2 for "http" URIs</name>
        <t>
          A client that makes a request for an "http" URI without prior knowledge about support for
          HTTP/2 on the next hop uses the HTTP Upgrade mechanism (<xref target="HTTP" section="7.8"/>). The client does so by making an HTTP/1.1 request that
          includes an Upgrade header field with the "h2c" token. Such an HTTP/1.1 request MUST
          include exactly one <xref target="Http2SettingsHeader">HTTP2-Settings</xref> header field.
        </t>
        <t keepWithNext="true">For example:</t>
        <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&quot;request&quot;"><![CDATA[
  GET / HTTP/1.1
  Host: server.example.com
  Connection: Upgrade, HTTP2-Settings
  Upgrade: h2c
  HTTP2-Settings: <base64url encoding of SETTINGS frame payload>

]]></artwork>
        <t>
          Requests that contain message content MUST be sent in their entirety before the client can
          send HTTP/2 frames.  This means that a large request can block the use of the connection
          until it is completely sent.
        </t>
        <t>
          If concurrency of an initial request with subsequent requests is important, an OPTIONS
          request can be used to perform the upgrade to HTTP/2, at the cost of an additional
          round trip.
        </t>
        <t>
          A server that does not support HTTP/2 can respond to the request as though the Upgrade
          header field were absent:
        </t>
        <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&quot;response&quot;"><![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK
  Content-Length: 243
  Content-Type: text/html

  ...
]]></artwork>
        <t>
          A server MUST ignore an "h2" token in an Upgrade header field.  Presence of a token with
          "h2" implies HTTP/2 over TLS, which is instead negotiated as described in <xref target="discover-https"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          A server that supports HTTP/2 accepts the upgrade with a 101 (Switching Protocols)
          response.  After the empty line that terminates the 101 response, the server can begin
          sending HTTP/2 frames.  These frames MUST include a response to the request that initiated
          the upgrade.
        </t>
        <t keepWithNext="true">
            For example:
        </t>
        <artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&quot;response&quot;"><![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 101 Switching Protocols
  Connection: Upgrade
  Upgrade: h2c

  [ HTTP/2 connection ...
]]></artwork>
        <t>
          The first HTTP/2 frame sent by the server MUST be a server connection preface
          (<xref target="ConnectionHeader"/>) consisting of a <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref>
          frame (<xref target="SETTINGS"/>). Upon receiving the 101 response, the client MUST send a
          <xref target="ConnectionHeader">connection preface</xref>, which includes a
          <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame.
        </t>
        <t>
          The HTTP/1.1 request that is sent prior to upgrade is assigned a stream identifier of 1
          (see <xref target="StreamIdentifiers"/>).  Stream 1 is implicitly "half-closed" from the
          client toward the server (see <xref target="StreamStates"/>), since the request is
          completed as an HTTP/1.1 request.  After commencing the HTTP/2 connection, stream 1 is
          used for the response.
        </t>
        <section anchor="Http2SettingsHeader">
          <name>HTTP2-Settings Header Field</name>
          <t>
            A request that upgrades from HTTP/1.1 to HTTP/2 MUST include exactly one <tt>HTTP2-Settings</tt> header field.  The <tt>HTTP2-Settings</tt> header field is a connection-specific header field
            that includes settings that govern the HTTP/2 connection, provided in anticipation of
            the server accepting the request to upgrade.
          </t>
          <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
  HTTP2-Settings    = token68
]]></artwork>
          <t>
            A server MUST NOT upgrade the connection to HTTP/2 if this header field is not present
            or if more than one is present. A server MUST NOT send this header field.
          </t>
          <t>
            The content of the <tt>HTTP2-Settings</tt> header field is the
            frame payload of a <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame (<xref target="SETTINGS"/>), encoded as a
            base64url string (that is, the URL- and filename-safe Base64 encoding described in
            <xref target="RFC4648" section="5"/>, with any trailing '=' characters omitted).  The
            <xref target="RFC5234">ABNF</xref> production for <tt>token68</tt> is
            defined in <xref target="HTTP" section="11.2"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Since the upgrade is only intended to apply to the immediate connection, a client
            sending the <tt>HTTP2-Settings</tt> header field MUST also send <tt>HTTP2-Settings</tt> as a connection option in the <tt>Connection</tt> header field to prevent it from being forwarded
            (see <xref target="HTTP" section="7.6.1"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            A server decodes and interprets these values as it would any other
            <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame.  Explicit <xref target="SettingsSync">acknowledgement of
            these settings</xref> is not necessary, since a 101 response serves as implicit
            acknowledgement.  Providing these values in the upgrade request gives a client an
            opportunity to provide settings prior to receiving any frames from the server.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="discover-https">
        <name>Starting HTTP/2 for "https" URIs</name>
        <t>
          A client that makes a request to an "https" URI uses <xref target="TLS13">TLS</xref> with
          the <xref target="TLS-ALPN">application-layer protocol negotiation (ALPN)
            extension</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          HTTP/2 over TLS uses the "h2" protocol identifier.  The "h2c" protocol identifier MUST NOT
          be sent by a client or selected by a server; the "h2c" protocol identifier describes a
          protocol that does not use TLS.
        </t>
        <t>
          Once TLS negotiation is complete, both the client and the server MUST send a <xref target="ConnectionHeader">connection preface</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="known-http">
        <name>Starting HTTP/2 with Prior Knowledge</name>
        <t>
          A client can learn that a particular server supports HTTP/2 by other means.  For example,
          <xref target="ALT-SVC"/> describes a mechanism for advertising this capability.
        </t>
        <t>
          A client MUST send the <xref target="ConnectionHeader">connection preface</xref> and
          then MAY immediately send HTTP/2 frames to such a server; servers can identify these
          connections by the presence of the connection preface. This only affects the
          establishment of HTTP/2 connections over cleartext TCP; implementations that support
          HTTP/2 over TLS MUST use <xref target="TLS-ALPN">protocol negotiation in TLS</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Likewise, the server MUST send a <xref target="ConnectionHeader">connection preface</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Without additional information, prior support for HTTP/2 is not a strong signal that a
          given server will support HTTP/2 for future connections. For example, it is possible for
          server configurations to change, for configurations to differ between instances in
          clustered servers, or for network conditions to change.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ConnectionHeader">
        <name>HTTP/2 Connection Preface</name>
        <t>
          In HTTP/2, each endpoint is required to send a connection preface as a final confirmation
          of the protocol in use and to establish the initial settings for the HTTP/2 connection.
          The client and server each send a different connection preface.
        </t>
        <t>
          The client connection preface starts with a sequence of 24 octets, which in hex notation
          is:
        </t>
        <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
  0x505249202a20485454502f322e300d0a0d0a534d0d0a0d0a
]]></artwork>
        <t>
          That is, the connection preface starts with the string <tt>PRI *
          HTTP/2.0\r\n\r\nSM\r\n\r\n</tt>. This sequence
          MUST be followed by a <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame (<xref target="SETTINGS"/>), which
          MAY be empty. The client sends the client connection preface immediately upon receipt of
          a 101 (Switching Protocols) response (indicating a successful upgrade) or as the first
          application data octets of a TLS connection. If starting an HTTP/2 connection with prior
          knowledge of server support for the protocol, the client connection preface is sent upon
          connection establishment.
        </t>
        <aside>
          <t>Note:
            The client connection preface is selected so that a large proportion of HTTP/1.1 or
            HTTP/1.0 servers and intermediaries do not attempt to process further frames.  Note
            that this does not address the concerns raised in <xref target="TALKING"/>.
        </t>
        </aside>
        <t>
          The server connection preface consists of a potentially empty <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref>
          frame (<xref target="SETTINGS"/>) that MUST be the first frame the server sends in the
          HTTP/2 connection.
        </t>
        <t>
          The <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frames received from a peer as part of the connection preface
          MUST be acknowledged (see <xref target="SettingsSync"/>) after sending the connection
          preface.
        </t>
        <t>
          To avoid unnecessary latency, clients are permitted to send additional frames to the
          server immediately after sending the client connection preface, without waiting to receive
          the server connection preface.  It is important to note, however, that the server
          connection preface <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame might include settings that necessarily
          alter how a client is expected to communicate with the server. Upon receiving the
          <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame, the client is expected to honor any settings established.
          In some configurations, it is possible for the server to transmit <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref>
          before the client sends additional frames, providing an opportunity to avoid this issue.
        </t>
        <t>
          Clients and servers MUST treat an invalid connection preface as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.  A <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frame (<xref target="GOAWAY"/>)
          MAY be omitted in this case, since an invalid preface indicates that the peer is not using
          HTTP/2.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="FramingLayer">
      <name>HTTP Frames</name>
      <t>
        Once the HTTP/2 connection is established, endpoints can begin exchanging frames.
      </t>
      <section anchor="FrameHeader">
        <name>Frame Format</name>
        <t>
          All frames begin with a fixed 9-octet header followed by a variable-length frame payload.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="FrameLayout">
          <name>Frame Layout</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +-----------------------------------------------+
 |                 Length (24)                   |
 +---------------+---------------+---------------+
 |   Type (8)    |   Flags (8)   |
 +-+-------------+---------------+-------------------------------+
 |R|                 Stream Identifier (31)                      |
 +=+=============================================================+
 |                   Frame Payload (0...)                      ...
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The fields of the frame header are defined as:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Length:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                The length of the frame payload expressed as an unsigned 24-bit integer.  Values
                greater than 2<sup>14</sup> (16,384) MUST NOT be sent unless the receiver has
                set a larger value for <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_FRAME_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_FRAME_SIZE</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
                The 9 octets of the frame header are not included in this value.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>Type:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                The 8-bit type of the frame.  The frame type determines the format and semantics of
                the frame.  Implementations MUST ignore and discard any frame that has a type that
                is unknown.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>Flags:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                An 8-bit field reserved for boolean flags specific to the frame type.
            </t>
            <t>
                Flags are assigned semantics specific to the indicated frame type.  Flags that have
                no defined semantics for a particular frame type MUST be ignored and MUST be left
                unset (0x0) when sending.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>R:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                A reserved 1-bit field.  The semantics of this bit are undefined, and the bit MUST
                remain unset (0x0) when sending and MUST be ignored when receiving.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>Stream Identifier:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                A stream identifier (see <xref target="StreamIdentifiers"/>) expressed as an
                unsigned 31-bit integer.  The value 0x0 is reserved for frames that are associated
                with the connection as a whole as opposed to an individual stream.
            </t>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The structure and content of the frame payload is dependent entirely on the frame type.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="FrameSize">
        <name>Frame Size</name>
        <t>
          The size of a frame payload is limited by the maximum size that a receiver advertises in
          the <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_FRAME_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_FRAME_SIZE</xref> setting.  This setting can have any value
          between 2<sup>14</sup> (16,384) and 2<sup>24</sup>-1 (16,777,215) octets,
          inclusive.
        </t>
        <t>
          All implementations MUST be capable of receiving and minimally processing frames up to
          2<sup>14</sup> octets in length, plus the 9-octet <xref target="FrameHeader">frame
          header</xref>.  The size of the frame header is not included when describing frame sizes.
        </t>
        <aside>
          <t>Note: Certain frame types, such as <xref target="PING">PING</xref>, impose additional limits
            on the amount of frame payload data allowed.
          </t>
        </aside>
        <t>
          An endpoint MUST send an error code of <xref target="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR" format="none">FRAME_SIZE_ERROR</xref> if a frame exceeds the size
          defined in <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_FRAME_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_FRAME_SIZE</xref>, exceeds any limit defined for the frame type,
          or is too small to contain mandatory frame data. A frame size error in a frame that
          could alter the state of the entire connection MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref>; this includes any frame carrying
          a <xref target="FieldBlock">field block</xref> (that is, <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>,
          <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>, and <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref>), <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref>,
          and any frame with a stream identifier of 0.
        </t>
        <t>
          Endpoints are not obligated to use all available space in a frame. Responsiveness can be
          improved by using frames that are smaller than the permitted maximum size. Sending large
          frames can result in delays in sending time-sensitive frames (such as
          <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>, <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref>, or <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref>),
          which, if blocked by the transmission of a large frame, could affect performance.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="FieldBlock">
        <name>Field Section Compression and Decompression</name>
        <t>
          Field section compression is the process of compressing a set of field lines to form a
          field block.  Field section decompression is the process of decoding a field block into a
          set of field lines.  Details of HTTP/2 field section compression and decompression is
          defined in <xref target="COMPRESSION"/>, which, for historical reasons, refers to these
          processes as header compression and decompression.
        </t>
        <t>
          Field blocks carry the compressed bytes of a field section, with header sections
          also carrying control data associated with the message in the form of <xref
          target="PseudoHeaderFields">pseudo-header fields</xref> that use the same format as a
          field line.
        </t>
        <aside>
          <t>
            Note: Previous versions of this specification used the term "header block" in place of
            the more generic "field block".
          </t>
        </aside>
        <t>
          Field blocks carry control data and header sections for requests, responses, promised
          requests, and pushed responses (see <xref target="PushResources"/>).  All these messages,
          except for interim responses and requests contained in <xref
          target="PUSH_PROMISE">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames can optionally include a field block that
          carries a trailer section.
        </t>
        <t>
          A field section is a collection of zero or more field lines.  Each of the field lines in a
          field block carry a single value.  The serialized field block is then divided into one or
          more octet sequences, called field block fragments, and transmitted within the frame
          payload of <xref target="HEADERS">HEADERS</xref> or <xref
          target="PUSH_PROMISE">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>, each of which could be followed by <xref
          target="CONTINUATION">CONTINUATION</xref> frames.
        </t>
        <t>
          The <xref target="COOKIE">Cookie header field</xref> is treated specially by the HTTP
          mapping (see <xref target="CompressCookie"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          A receiving endpoint reassembles the field block by concatenating its fragments and then
          decompresses the block to reconstruct the field section.
        </t>
        <t>
          A complete field section consists of either:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
              a single <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> or <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame,
              with the END_HEADERS flag set, or
            </li>
          <li>
              a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> or <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame with the END_HEADERS
              flag cleared and one or more <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames,
              where the last <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frame has the END_HEADERS flag set.
            </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          Field compression is stateful.  One compression context and one decompression context are
          used for the entire connection.  A decoding error in a field block MUST be treated as a
          <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="COMPRESSION_ERROR" format="none">COMPRESSION_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Each field block is processed as a discrete unit.
          Field blocks MUST be transmitted as a contiguous sequence of frames, with no interleaved
          frames of any other type or from any other stream.  The last frame in a sequence of
          <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> or <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames has the END_HEADERS flag set.
          The last frame in a sequence of <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> or <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref>
          frames has the END_HEADERS flag set.  This allows a field block to be logically
          equivalent to a single frame.
        </t>
        <t>
          Field block fragments can only be sent as the frame payload of <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>,
          <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>, or <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames because these frames
          carry data that can modify the compression context maintained by a receiver.  An endpoint
          receiving <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>, <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>, or
          <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames needs to reassemble field blocks and perform
          decompression even if the frames are to be discarded.  A receiver MUST terminate the
          connection with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="COMPRESSION_ERROR" format="none">COMPRESSION_ERROR</xref> if it does not decompress a field block.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="StreamsLayer">
      <name>Streams and Multiplexing</name>
      <t>
        A "stream" is an independent, bidirectional sequence of frames exchanged between the client
        and server within an HTTP/2 connection.  Streams have several important characteristics:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
            A single HTTP/2 connection can contain multiple concurrently open streams, with either
            endpoint interleaving frames from multiple streams.
          </li>
        <li>
            Streams can be established and used unilaterally or shared by either the client or
            server.
          </li>
        <li>
            Streams can be closed by either endpoint.
          </li>
        <li>
            The order in which frames are sent on a stream is significant. Recipients process frames
            in the order they are received.  In particular, the order of <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>
            and <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames is semantically significant.
          </li>
        <li>
            Streams are identified by an integer.  Stream identifiers are assigned to streams by the
            endpoint initiating the stream.
          </li>
      </ul>
      <section anchor="StreamStates">
        <name>Stream States</name>
        <t>
          The lifecycle of a stream is shown in <xref target="StreamStatesFigure"/>.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="StreamStatesFigure">
          <name>Stream States</name>
          <artwork type="drawing"><![CDATA[
                             +--------+
                     send PP |        | recv PP
                    ,--------|  idle  |--------.
                   /         |        |         \
                  v          +--------+          v
           +----------+          |           +----------+
           |          |          | send H /  |          |
    ,------| reserved |          | recv H    | reserved |------.
    |      | (local)  |          |           | (remote) |      |
    |      +----------+          v           +----------+      |
    |          |             +--------+             |          |
    |          |     recv ES |        | send ES     |          |
    |   send H |     ,-------|  open  |-------.     | recv H   |
    |          |    /        |        |        \    |          |
    |          v   v         +--------+         v   v          |
    |      +----------+          |           +----------+      |
    |      |   half   |          |           |   half   |      |
    |      |  closed  |          | send R /  |  closed  |      |
    |      | (remote) |          | recv R    | (local)  |      |
    |      +----------+          |           +----------+      |
    |           |                |                 |           |
    |           | send ES /      |       recv ES / |           |
    |           | send R /       v        send R / |           |
    |           | recv R     +--------+   recv R   |           |
    | send R /  `----------->|        |<-----------'  send R / |
    | recv R                 | closed |               recv R   |
    `----------------------->|        |<----------------------'
                             +--------+

       send:   endpoint sends this frame
       recv:   endpoint receives this frame

       H:  HEADERS frame (with implied CONTINUATIONs)
       ES: END_STREAM flag
       R:  RST_STREAM frame
       PP: PUSH_PROMISE frame (with implied CONTINUATIONs)
           Note: State transitions are for the promised stream.
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          Note that this diagram shows stream state transitions and the frames and flags that affect
          those transitions only.  In this regard, <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames do not result
          in state transitions; they are effectively part of the <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> or
          <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> that they follow.  For the purpose of state transitions, the
          END_STREAM flag is processed as a separate event to the frame that bears it; a
          <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame with the END_STREAM flag set can cause two state transitions.
        </t>
        <t>
          Both endpoints have a subjective view of the state of a stream that could be different
          when frames are in transit.  Endpoints do not coordinate the creation of streams; they are
          created unilaterally by either endpoint.  The negative consequences of a mismatch in
          states are limited to the "closed" state after sending <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>, where
          frames might be received for some time after closing.
        </t>
        <t>
          Streams have the following states:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>idle:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                All streams start in the "idle" state.
            </t>
            <t>
                The following transitions are valid from this state:
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>
                    Sending or receiving a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame causes the stream to become
                    "open".  The stream identifier is selected as described in <xref target="StreamIdentifiers"/>.  The same <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame can also
                    cause a stream to immediately become "half-closed".
                  </li>
              <li>
                    Sending a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame on another stream reserves the idle
                    stream that is identified for later use.  The stream state for the reserved
                    stream transitions to "reserved (local)".
                  </li>
              <li>
                    Receiving a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame on another stream reserves an idle
                    stream that is identified for later use.  The stream state for the reserved
                    stream transitions to "reserved (remote)".
                  </li>
              <li>
                    Note that the <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame is not sent on the idle
                    stream but references the newly reserved stream in the Promised Stream ID
                    field.
                  </li>
            </ul>
            <t>
                Receiving any frame other than <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> or <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> on
                a stream in this state MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
                <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>reserved (local):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>

                A stream in the "reserved (local)" state is one that has been promised by sending a
                <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame.  A <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame reserves an
                idle stream by associating the stream with an open stream that was initiated by the
                remote peer (see <xref target="PushResources"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
                In this state, only the following transitions are possible:
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>
                    The endpoint can send a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame.  This causes the stream to
                    open in a "half-closed (remote)" state.
                  </li>
              <li>
                    Either endpoint can send a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame to cause the stream
                    to become "closed".  This releases the stream reservation.
                  </li>
            </ul>
            <t>
                An endpoint MUST NOT send any type of frame other than <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>,
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>, or <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> in this state.
            </t>
            <t>
                A <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> or <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> frame MAY be received in
                this state.  Receiving any type of frame other than <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>,
                <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref>, or <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> on a stream in this state
                MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref>
                of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>reserved (remote):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>

                A stream in the "reserved (remote)" state has been reserved by a remote peer.
            </t>
            <t>
                In this state, only the following transitions are possible:
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>
                    Receiving a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame causes the stream to transition to
                    "half-closed (local)".
                  </li>
              <li>
                    Either endpoint can send a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame to cause the stream
                    to become "closed".  This releases the stream reservation.
                  </li>
            </ul>
            <t>
                An endpoint MUST NOT send any type of frame other than <xref target="RST_STREAM"
                format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>, <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE"
                format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref>, or <xref target="PRIORITY"
                format="none">PRIORITY</xref> in this state.
            </t>
            <t>
                Receiving any type of frame other than <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>,
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>, or <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> on a stream in this state MUST
                be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of
                type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>open:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>

                A stream in the "open" state may be used by both peers to send frames of any type.
                In this state, sending peers observe advertised <xref target="FlowControl">stream-level
                flow-control limits</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
                From this state, either endpoint can send a frame with an END_STREAM flag set, which
                causes the stream to transition into one of the "half-closed" states. An endpoint
                sending an END_STREAM flag causes the stream state to become "half-closed (local)";
                an endpoint receiving an END_STREAM flag causes the stream state to become "half-closed
                (remote)".
            </t>
            <t>
                Either endpoint can send a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame from this state, causing
                it to transition immediately to "closed".
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>half-closed (local):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>

                A stream that is in the "half-closed (local)" state cannot be used for sending
                frames other than <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref>, <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref>, and
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
                A stream transitions from this state to "closed" when a frame that contains an
                END_STREAM flag is received or when either peer sends a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>
                frame.
            </t>
            <t>
                An endpoint can receive any type of frame in this state.  Providing flow-control
                credit using <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> frames is necessary to continue receiving
                flow-controlled frames.  In this state, a receiver can ignore <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> frames,
                which might arrive for a short period after a frame bearing the
                END_STREAM flag is sent.
            </t>
            <t><xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> frames can be received in this state.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>half-closed (remote):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>

                A stream that is "half-closed (remote)" is no longer being used by the peer to send
                frames.  In this state, an endpoint is no longer obligated to maintain a receiver
                flow-control window.
            </t>
            <t>
                If an endpoint receives additional frames, other
                than <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref>, <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref>, or
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>,  for a stream that is in this state, it MUST respond with a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type
                <xref target="STREAM_CLOSED" format="none">STREAM_CLOSED</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
                A stream that is "half-closed (remote)" can be used by the endpoint to send frames
                of any type. In this state, the endpoint continues to observe advertised <xref target="FlowControl">stream-level flow-control limits</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
                A stream can transition from this state to "closed" by sending a frame that contains
                an END_STREAM flag or when either peer sends a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>closed:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>

                The "closed" state is the terminal state.
            </t>
            <t>
                An endpoint MUST NOT send frames other than <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> on a closed
                stream.  An endpoint that receives any frame other than <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref>
                after receiving a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> MUST treat that as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type
                <xref target="STREAM_CLOSED" format="none">STREAM_CLOSED</xref>.  Similarly, an endpoint that receives any frames after
                receiving a frame with the END_STREAM flag set MUST treat that as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
                <xref target="STREAM_CLOSED" format="none">STREAM_CLOSED</xref>, unless the frame is permitted as described below.
            </t>
            <t><xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> or <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frames can be received in
                this state for a short period after a <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> or <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>
                frame containing an END_STREAM flag is sent.  Until the remote peer receives and
                processes <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> or the frame bearing the END_STREAM flag, it
                might send frames of these types.  Endpoints MUST ignore
                <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> or <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frames received in this
                state, though endpoints MAY choose to treat frames that arrive a significant time
                after sending END_STREAM as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection
                error</xref> of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </t>
            <t><xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> frames can be sent on closed streams.
            </t>
            <t>
                If this state is reached as a result of sending a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame,
                the peer that receives the <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> might have already sent -- or
                enqueued for sending -- frames on the stream that cannot be withdrawn.  An endpoint
                MUST ignore frames that it receives on closed streams after it has sent a
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame.  An endpoint MAY choose to limit the period over
                which it ignores frames and treat frames that arrive after this time as being in
                error.
            </t>
            <t>
                Flow-controlled frames (i.e., <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref>) received after sending
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> are counted toward the connection flow-control window.
                Even though these frames might be ignored, because they are sent before the sender
                receives the <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>, the sender will consider the frames to count
                against the flow-control window.
            </t>
            <t>
                An endpoint might receive a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame after it sends
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>.  <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> causes a stream to become
                "reserved" even if the associated stream has been reset.  Therefore, a
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> is needed to close an unwanted promised stream.
            </t>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          In the absence of more specific guidance elsewhere in this document, implementations
          SHOULD treat the receipt of a frame that is not expressly permitted in the description of
          a state as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.  Note that <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> can be sent and received
          in any stream state.  Frames of unknown types are ignored.
        </t>
        <t>
          An example of the state transitions for an HTTP request/response exchange can be found in
          <xref target="HttpSequence"/>.  An example of the state transitions for server push can be
          found in Sections <xref target="PushRequests" format="counter"/> and <xref target="PushResponses" format="counter"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="StreamIdentifiers">
          <name>Stream Identifiers</name>
          <t>
            Streams are identified with an unsigned 31-bit integer.  Streams initiated by a client
            MUST use odd-numbered stream identifiers; those initiated by the server MUST use
            even-numbered stream identifiers.  A stream identifier of zero (0x0) is used for
            connection control messages; the stream identifier of zero cannot be used to establish a
            new stream.
          </t>
          <t>
            HTTP/1.1 requests that are upgraded to HTTP/2 (see <xref target="discover-http"/>) are
            responded to with a stream identifier of one (0x1).  After the upgrade
            completes, stream 0x1 is "half-closed (local)" to the client.  Therefore, stream 0x1
            cannot be selected as a new stream identifier by a client that upgrades from HTTP/1.1.
          </t>
          <t>
            The identifier of a newly established stream MUST be numerically greater than all
            streams that the initiating endpoint has opened or reserved.  This governs streams that
            are opened using a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame and streams that are reserved using
            <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>.  An endpoint that receives an unexpected stream identifier
            MUST respond with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of
            type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>
            A <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame will transition the client-initiated stream identified
            by the stream identifier in the frame header from "idle" to "open". A <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>
            frame will transition the server-initiated stream identified by the "Promised Stream ID" field in the frame payload from "idle" to "reserved". When
            a stream transitions out of the "idle" state, all streams that might have been initiated by that peer with a lower-valued
            stream identifier are implicitly transitioned to "closed". That is, an endpoint may skip a stream identifier, with the
            effect being that the skipped stream is immediately closed.
          </t>
          <t>
            Stream identifiers cannot be reused.  Long-lived connections can result in an endpoint
            exhausting the available range of stream identifiers.  A client that is unable to
            establish a new stream identifier can establish a new connection for new streams.  A
            server that is unable to establish a new stream identifier can send a
            <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frame so that the client is forced to open a new connection for
            new streams.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Stream Concurrency</name>
          <t>
            A peer can limit the number of concurrently active streams using the
            <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS</xref> parameter (see <xref target="SettingValues"/>) within a <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame. The maximum concurrent
            streams setting is specific to each endpoint and applies only to the peer that receives
            the setting. That is, clients specify the maximum number of concurrent streams the
            server can initiate, and servers specify the maximum number of concurrent streams the
            client can initiate.
          </t>
          <t>
            Streams that are in the "open" state or in either of the "half-closed" states count toward
            the maximum number of streams that an endpoint is permitted to open.  Streams in any of
            these three states count toward the limit advertised in the
            <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS</xref> setting.  Streams in either of the
            "reserved" states do not count toward the stream limit.
          </t>
          <t>
            Endpoints MUST NOT exceed the limit set by their peer.  An endpoint that receives a
            <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame that causes its advertised concurrent stream limit to be
            exceeded MUST treat this as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of
            type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref> or <xref target="REFUSED_STREAM" format="none">REFUSED_STREAM</xref>.  The choice of
            error code determines whether the endpoint wishes to enable automatic retry (see <xref target="Reliability"/>) for details).
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint that wishes to reduce the value of
            <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS</xref> to a value that is below the current
            number of open streams can either close streams that exceed the new value or allow
            streams to complete.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="FlowControl">
        <name>Flow Control</name>
        <t>
          Using streams for multiplexing introduces contention over use of the TCP connection,
          resulting in blocked streams.  A flow-control scheme ensures that streams on the same
          connection do not destructively interfere with each other.  Flow control is used for both
          individual streams and for the connection as a whole.
        </t>
        <t>
          HTTP/2 provides for flow control through use of the <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE">WINDOW_UPDATE frame</xref>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="fc-principles">
          <name>Flow-Control Principles</name>
          <t>
            HTTP/2 stream flow control aims to allow a variety of flow-control algorithms to be
            used without requiring protocol changes. Flow control in HTTP/2 has the following
            characteristics:
          </t>
          <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
            <li>
                Flow control is specific to a connection.  Both types of flow control are between
                the endpoints of a single hop and not over the entire end-to-end path.
              </li>
            <li>
                Flow control is based on <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> frames.  Receivers advertise how many octets
                they are prepared to receive on a stream and for the entire connection.  This is a
                credit-based scheme.
              </li>
            <li>
                Flow control is directional with overall control provided by the receiver.  A
                receiver MAY choose to set any window size that it desires for each stream and for
                the entire connection.  A sender MUST respect flow-control limits imposed by a
                receiver.  Clients, servers, and intermediaries all independently advertise their
                flow-control window as a receiver and abide by the flow-control limits set by
                their peer when sending.
              </li>
            <li>
                The initial value for the flow-control window is 65,535 octets for both new streams
                and the overall connection.
              </li>
            <li>
                The frame type determines whether flow control applies to a frame.  Of the frames
                specified in this document, only <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames are subject to flow
                control; all other frame types do not consume space in the advertised flow-control
                window.  This ensures that important control frames are not blocked by flow control.
              </li>
            <li>
                Flow control cannot be disabled.
              </li>
            <li>
                HTTP/2 defines only the format and semantics of the <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref>
                frame (<xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE"/>).  This document does not stipulate how a
                receiver decides when to send this frame or the value that it sends, nor does it
                specify how a sender chooses to send packets.  Implementations are able to select
                any algorithm that suits their needs.
              </li>
          </ol>
          <t>
            Implementations are also responsible for prioritizing the sending of requests and
            responses, choosing how to avoid head-of-line blocking for requests, and managing the
            creation of new streams.  Algorithm choices for these could interact with any
            flow-control algorithm.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="DisableFlowControl">
          <name>Appropriate Use of Flow Control</name>
          <t>
            Flow control is defined to protect endpoints that are operating under resource
            constraints.  For example, a proxy needs to share memory between many connections and
            also might have a slow upstream connection and a fast downstream one.  Flow-control
            addresses cases where the receiver is unable to process data on one stream yet wants to
            continue to process other streams in the same connection.
          </t>
          <t>
            Deployments that do not require this capability can advertise a flow-control window of
            the maximum size (2<sup>31</sup>-1) and can maintain this window by sending a
            <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> frame when any data is received.  This effectively disables
            flow control for that receiver.  Conversely, a sender is always subject to the
            flow-control window advertised by the receiver.
          </t>
          <t>
            Deployments with constrained resources (for example, memory) can employ flow control to
            limit the amount of memory a peer can consume.  Note, however, that this can lead to
            suboptimal use of available network resources if flow control is enabled without
            knowledge of the bandwidth-delay product (see <xref target="RFC7323"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            Even with full awareness of the current bandwidth-delay product, implementation of flow
            control can be difficult.  When using flow control, the receiver MUST read from the TCP
            receive buffer in a timely fashion.  Failure to do so could lead to a deadlock when
            critical frames, such as <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref>, are not read and acted upon.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="StreamPriority">
        <name>Prioritization</name>
        <t>
          In a multiplexed protocol like HTTP/2, prioritizing allocation of bandwidth and
          computation resources to streams can be critical to attaining good performance.  A poor
          prioritization scheme can result in HTTP/2 providing poor performance.  With no parallelism
          at the TCP layer, performance could be significantly worse than HTTP/1.1.
        </t>
        <t>
          A good prioritization scheme benefits from the application of contextual knowledge such as
          the content of resources, how resources are interrelated, and how those resources will be
          used by a peer.  In particular, clients can possess knowledge about the priority of
          requests that is relevant to server prioritization.  In those cases, having clients
          provide priority information can improve performance.
        </t>
        <section anchor="PriorityHistory">
          <name>Background of Priority in HTTP/2</name>
          <t>
            HTTP/2 included a rich system for signaling priority of requests.  However, this system
            proved to be complex and it was not uniformly implemented.
          </t>
          <t>
            The flexible scheme meant that it was possible for clients to express priorities in very
            different ways, with little consistency in the approaches that were adopted.  For
            servers, implementing generic support for the scheme was complex.  Implementation of
            priorities was uneven in both clients and servers.  Many server deployments ignored
            client signals when prioritizing their handling of requests.
          </t>
          <t>
            In short, the prioritization signaling in <xref target="RFC7540">RFC7540</xref> was not
            successful.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="PriorityHere">
          <name>Priority Signaling in this Document</name>
          <t>
            This update to HTTP/2 deprecates the priority signaling defined in <xref
            target="RFC7540">RFC 7540</xref>.  The bulk of the text related to priority signals is
            not included in this document.  The description of frame fields and some of the
            mandatory handling is retained to ensure that implementations of this document remain
            interoperable with implementations that use the priority signaling described in RFC
            7540.
          </t>
          <t>
            A thorough description of the RFC 7540 priority scheme remains in <xref target="RFC7540"
            section="5.3"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Signaling priority information is necessary to attain good performance in many cases.
            Where signaling priority information is important, endpoints are encouraged to use an
            alternative scheme, such as <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-priority"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Though the priority signaling from RFC 7540 was not widely adopted, the information it
            provides can still be useful in the absence of better information.  Endpoints that
            receive priority signals in <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> or <xref
            target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> frames can benefit from applying that
            information.  In particular, implementations that consume these signals would not
            benefit from discarding these priority signals in the absence of alternatives.
          </t>
          <t>
            Servers SHOULD use other contextual information in determining priority of requests in
            the absence of any priority signals.  Servers MAY interpret the complete absence of
            signals as an indication that the client has not implemented the feature.  The defaults
            described in <xref target="RFC7540" section="5.3.5"/> are known to have poor performance
            under most conditions and their use is unlikely to be deliberate.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ErrorHandler">
        <name>Error Handling</name>
        <t>
          HTTP/2 framing permits two classes of error:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
              An error condition that renders the entire connection unusable is a connection error.
            </li>
          <li>
              An error in an individual stream is a stream error.
            </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          A list of error codes is included in <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is possible that an endpoint will encounter frames that would cause multiple errors. Implementations MAY discover
          multiple errors during processing, but they SHOULD report at most one stream and one connection error as a result.
        </t>
        <t>
          The first stream error reported for a given stream prevents any other errors on that stream from being reported.
          In comparison, the protocol permits multiple <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frames, though an
          endpoint SHOULD report just one type of connection error unless an error is encountered during graceful shutdown.
          If this occurs, an endpoint MAY send an additional GOAWAY frame with the new error code, in addition to any prior
          GOAWAY that contained <xref target="NO_ERROR" format="none">NO_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          If an endpoint detects multiple different errors,
          it MAY choose to report any one of those errors. If a frame causes a connection error, that error MUST be reported.
        </t>
        <section anchor="ConnectionErrorHandler">
          <name>Connection Error Handling</name>
          <t>
            A connection error is any error that prevents further processing of the frame
            layer or corrupts any connection state.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint that encounters a connection error SHOULD first send a <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref>
            frame (<xref target="GOAWAY"/>) with the stream identifier of the last stream that it
            successfully received from its peer.  The <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frame includes an error
            code that indicates why the connection is terminating.  After sending the
            <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frame for an error condition, the endpoint MUST close the TCP
            connection.
          </t>
          <t>
            It is possible that the <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> will not be reliably received by the
            receiving endpoint.  In the event of a connection error,
            <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> only provides a best-effort attempt to communicate with the peer
            about why the connection is being terminated.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint can end a connection at any time.  In particular, an endpoint MAY choose to
            treat a stream error as a connection error.  Endpoints SHOULD send a
            <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frame when ending a connection, providing that circumstances
            permit it.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="StreamErrorHandler">
          <name>Stream Error Handling</name>
          <t>
            A stream error is an error related to a specific stream that does not affect processing
            of other streams.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint that detects a stream error sends a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame (<xref target="RST_STREAM"/>) that contains the stream identifier of the stream where the error
            occurred.  The <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame includes an error code that indicates the
            type of error.
          </t>
          <t>
            A <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> is the last frame that an endpoint can send on a stream.
            The peer that sends the <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame MUST be prepared to receive any
            frames that were sent or enqueued for sending by the remote peer.  These frames can be
            ignored, except where they modify connection state (such as the state maintained for
            <xref target="FieldBlock">field section compression</xref> or flow control).
          </t>
          <t>
            Normally, an endpoint SHOULD NOT send more than one <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame for
            any stream. However, an endpoint MAY send additional <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frames if
            it receives frames on a closed stream after more than a round-trip time.  This behavior
            is permitted to deal with misbehaving implementations.
          </t>
          <t>
            To avoid looping, an endpoint MUST NOT send a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> in response to a
            <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Connection Termination</name>
          <t>
            If the TCP connection is closed or reset while streams remain in "open" or "half-closed"
            state, then the affected streams cannot be automatically retried (see <xref target="Reliability"/> for details).
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="extensibility">
        <name>Extending HTTP/2</name>
        <t>
          HTTP/2 permits extension of the protocol.  Within the limitations described in this
          section, protocol extensions can be used to provide additional services or alter
          any aspect of the protocol. Extensions are effective only within the scope of a single HTTP/2
          connection.
        </t>
        <t>
          This applies to the protocol elements defined in this document.  This does not affect the
          existing options for extending HTTP, such as defining new methods, status codes, or fields
          (see <xref target="HTTP" section="16"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          Extensions are permitted to use new <xref target="FrameHeader">frame types</xref>, new
          <xref target="SettingValues">settings</xref>, or new <xref target="ErrorCodes">error
          codes</xref>.  Registries are established for managing these extension points: <xref target="iana-frames">frame types</xref>, <xref target="iana-settings">settings</xref>, and
          <xref target="iana-errors">error codes</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Implementations MUST ignore unknown or unsupported values in all extensible protocol
          elements.  Implementations MUST discard frames that have unknown or unsupported types.
          This means that any of these extension points can be safely used by extensions without
          prior arrangement or negotiation.  However, extension frames that appear in the middle of
          a <xref target="FieldBlock">field block</xref> are not permitted; these MUST be treated
          as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Extensions SHOULD avoiding changing protocol elements defined in this document or
          elements for which no extension mechanism is defined.  This includes changes to the
          layout of frames, additions or changes to the way that frames are composed into <xref
          target="HTTPLayer">HTTP messages</xref>, the definition of pseudo-header fields, or
          changes to any protocol element that a compliant endpoint might treat as a <xref
          target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          An extension that changes existing elements MUST be negotiated before being used.  For
          example, an extension that changes the layout of the <xref target="HEADERS"
          format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame cannot be used until the peer has given a positive
          signal that this is acceptable.  In this case, it could also be necessary to coordinate
          when the revised layout comes into effect.  For example, treating frames other than
          <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames as flow controlled requires a
          change in semantics that both endpoints need to understand, so this can only be done
          through negotiation.
        </t>
        <t>
          This document doesn't mandate a specific method for negotiating the use of an extension
          but notes that a <xref target="SettingValues">setting</xref> could be used for that
          purpose.  If both peers set a value that indicates willingness to use the extension, then
          the extension can be used.  If a setting is used for extension negotiation, the initial
          value MUST be defined in such a fashion that the extension is initially disabled.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="FrameTypes">
      <name>Frame Definitions</name>
      <t>
        This specification defines a number of frame types, each identified by a unique 8-bit type
        code. Each frame type serves a distinct purpose in the establishment and management either
        of the connection as a whole or of individual streams.
      </t>
      <t>
        The transmission of specific frame types can alter the state of a connection. If endpoints
        fail to maintain a synchronized view of the connection state, successful communication
        within the connection will no longer be possible. Therefore, it is important that endpoints
        have a shared comprehension of how the state is affected by the use any given frame.
      </t>
      <section anchor="DATA">
        <name>DATA</name>
        <t>
          DATA frames (type=0x0) convey arbitrary, variable-length sequences of octets associated
          with a stream. One or more DATA frames are used, for instance, to carry HTTP request or
          response message contents.
        </t>
        <t>
          DATA frames MAY also contain padding.  Padding can be added to DATA frames to obscure the
          size of messages.  Padding is a security feature; see <xref target="padding"/>.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="DATAFramePayload">
          <name>DATA Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +---------------+
 |Pad Length? (8)|
 +---------------+-----------------------------------------------+
 |                            Data (*)                         ...
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                           Padding (*)                       ...
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The DATA frame contains the following fields:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Pad Length:</dt>
          <dd>
              An 8-bit field containing the length of the frame padding in units of octets.  This
              field is conditional (as signified by a "?" in the diagram) and is only present
              if the PADDED flag is set.
            </dd>
          <dt>Data:</dt>
          <dd>
              Application data.  The amount of data is the remainder of the frame payload after
              subtracting the length of the other fields that are present.
            </dd>
          <dt>Padding:</dt>
          <dd>
              Padding octets that contain no application semantic value.  Padding octets MUST be set
              to zero when sending.  A receiver is not obligated to verify padding but MAY treat
              non-zero padding as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of
              type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The DATA frame defines the following flags:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>END_STREAM (0x1):</dt>
          <dd>
              When set, bit 0 indicates that this frame is the last that the endpoint will send for
              the identified stream.  Setting this flag causes the stream to enter one of <xref target="StreamStates">the "half-closed" states or the "closed" state</xref>.
            </dd>
          <dt>PADDED (0x8):</dt>
          <dd>
              When set, bit 3 indicates that the Pad Length field and any padding that it describes
              are present.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          DATA frames MUST be associated with a stream. If a DATA frame is received whose stream
          identifier field is 0x0, the recipient MUST respond with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          DATA frames are subject to flow control and can only be sent when a stream is in the
          "open" or "half-closed (remote)" state. The entire DATA frame payload is included in flow
          control, including the Pad Length and Padding fields if present.  If a DATA frame is received
          whose stream is not in "open" or "half-closed (local)" state, the recipient MUST respond
          with a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type
          <xref target="STREAM_CLOSED" format="none">STREAM_CLOSED</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The total number of padding octets is determined by the value of the Pad Length field. If
          the length of the padding is the length of the frame payload or greater, the recipient
          MUST treat this as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of
          type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <aside>
          <t>Note:
            A frame can be increased in size by one octet by including a Pad Length field with a
            value of zero.
          </t>
        </aside>
      </section>
      <section anchor="HEADERS">
        <name>HEADERS</name>
        <t>
          The HEADERS frame (type=0x1) is used to <xref target="StreamStates">open a stream</xref>,
          and additionally carries a field block fragment. Despite the name, a HEADERS frame can carry
          a header section or a trailer section. HEADERS frames can be sent on a stream
          in the "idle", "reserved (local)", "open", or "half-closed (remote)" state.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="HEADERSFramePayload">
          <name>HEADERS Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +---------------+
 |Pad Length? (8)|
 +-+-------------+-----------------------------------------------+
 |E|                 Stream Dependency? (31)                     |
 +-+-------------+-----------------------------------------------+
 |  Weight? (8)  |
 +-+-------------+-----------------------------------------------+
 |                    Field Block Fragment (*)                 ...
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                           Padding (*)                       ...
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The HEADERS frame payload has the following fields:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Pad Length:</dt>
          <dd>
            An 8-bit field containing the length of the frame padding in units of octets.  This
            field is only present if the PADDED flag is set.
          </dd>
          <dt>E:</dt>
          <dd>
            A single-bit flag.  This field is only present if the PRIORITY flag is set.
          </dd>
          <dt>Stream Dependency:</dt>
          <dd>
            A 31-bit stream identifier.  This field is only present if the PRIORITY flag is set.
          </dd>
          <dt>Weight:</dt>
          <dd>
            An unsigned 8-bit integer.  This field is only present if the PRIORITY flag is set.
          </dd>
          <dt>Field Block Fragment:</dt>
          <dd>
              A <xref target="FieldBlock">field block fragment</xref>.
            </dd>
          <dt>Padding:</dt>
          <dd>
              Padding octets.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The HEADERS frame defines the following flags:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>END_STREAM (0x1):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                When set, bit 0 indicates that the <xref target="FieldBlock">field block</xref> is
                the last that the endpoint will send for the identified stream.
            </t>
            <t>
                A HEADERS frame carries the END_STREAM flag that signals the end of a stream.
                However, a HEADERS frame with the END_STREAM flag set can be followed by
                <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames on the same stream.  Logically, the
                <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames are part of the HEADERS frame.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>END_HEADERS (0x4):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                When set, bit 2 indicates that this frame contains an entire <xref target="FieldBlock">field block</xref> and is not followed by any
                <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames.
            </t>
            <t>
                A HEADERS frame without the END_HEADERS flag set MUST be followed by a
                <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frame for the same stream.  A receiver MUST treat the
                receipt of any other type of frame or a frame on a different stream as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
                <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>PADDED (0x8):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                When set, bit 3 indicates that the Pad Length field and any padding that it
                describes are present.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>PRIORITY (0x20):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
              When set, bit 5 indicates that the Exclusive Flag (E), Stream Dependency, and Weight
              fields are present.
            </t>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The frame payload of a HEADERS frame contains a <xref target="FieldBlock">field block
          fragment</xref>.  A field block that does not fit within a HEADERS frame is continued in
          a <xref target="CONTINUATION">CONTINUATION frame</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          HEADERS frames MUST be associated with a stream. If a HEADERS frame is received whose
          stream identifier field is 0x0, the recipient MUST respond with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The HEADERS frame changes the connection state as described in <xref target="FieldBlock"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The HEADERS frame can include padding.  Padding fields and flags are identical to those
          defined for <xref target="DATA">DATA frames</xref>.  Padding that exceeds the size
          remaining for the field block fragment MUST be treated as a
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="PRIORITY">
        <name>PRIORITY</name>
        <t>
          The PRIORITY frame (type=0x2) is deprecated; see <xref target="PriorityHere"/>.  A
          PRIORITY frame can be sent in any stream state, including idle or closed streams.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="PRIORITYFramePayload">
          <name>PRIORITY Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
 |E|                  Stream Dependency (31)                     |
 +-+-------------+-----------------------------------------------+
 |   Weight (8)  |
 +-+-------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The frame payload of a PRIORITY frame contains the following fields:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>E:</dt>
          <dd>
            A single-bit flag.
          </dd>
          <dt>Stream Dependency:</dt>
          <dd>
            A 31-bit stream identifier.
          </dd>
          <dt>Weight:</dt>
          <dd>
            An unsigned 8-bit integer.
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The PRIORITY frame does not define any flags.
        </t>
        <t>
          The PRIORITY frame always identifies a stream.  If a PRIORITY frame is received with a
          stream identifier of 0x0, the recipient MUST respond with a <xref
          target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type <xref
          target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Sending or receiving a PRIORITY frame does not affect the state of any stream (<xref
          target="StreamStates"/>).  The PRIORITY frame can be sent on a stream in any state,
          including "idle" or "closed".  A PRIORITY frame cannot be sent between consecutive frames
          that comprise a single <xref target="FieldBlock">field block</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          A PRIORITY frame with a length other than 5 octets MUST be treated as a <xref
          target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type <xref target="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR"
          format="none">FRAME_SIZE_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="RST_STREAM">
        <name>RST_STREAM</name>
        <t>
          The RST_STREAM frame (type=0x3) allows for immediate termination of a stream.  RST_STREAM
          is sent to request cancellation of a stream or to indicate that an error condition has
          occurred.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="RST_STREAMFramePayload">
          <name>RST_STREAM Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                        Error Code (32)                        |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The RST_STREAM frame contains a single unsigned, 32-bit integer identifying the <xref target="ErrorCodes">error code</xref>.  The error code indicates why the stream is being
          terminated.
        </t>
        <t>
          The RST_STREAM frame does not define any flags.
        </t>
        <t>
          The RST_STREAM frame fully terminates the referenced stream and causes it to enter the
          "closed" state. After receiving a RST_STREAM on a stream, the receiver MUST NOT send
          additional frames for that stream, with the exception of <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref>. However,
          after sending the RST_STREAM, the sending endpoint MUST be prepared to receive and process
          additional frames sent on the stream that might have been sent by the peer prior to the
          arrival of the RST_STREAM.
        </t>
        <t>
          RST_STREAM frames MUST be associated with a stream.  If a RST_STREAM frame is received
          with a stream identifier of 0x0, the recipient MUST treat this as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          RST_STREAM frames MUST NOT be sent for a stream in the "idle" state.  If a RST_STREAM
          frame identifying an idle stream is received, the recipient MUST treat this as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          A RST_STREAM frame with a length other than 4 octets MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR" format="none">FRAME_SIZE_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="SETTINGS">
        <name>SETTINGS</name>
        <t>
          The SETTINGS frame (type=0x4) conveys configuration parameters that affect how endpoints
          communicate, such as preferences and constraints on peer behavior.  The SETTINGS frame is
          also used to acknowledge the receipt of those settings.  Individually, a configuration
          parameter from a SETTINGS frame is referred to as a "setting".
        </t>
        <t>
          Settings are not negotiated; they describe characteristics of the sending peer,
          which are used by the receiving peer. Different values for the same setting can be
          advertised by each peer. For example, a client might set a high initial flow-control
          window, whereas a server might set a lower value to conserve resources.
        </t>
        <t>
          A SETTINGS frame MUST be sent by both endpoints at the start of a connection and MAY be
          sent at any other time by either endpoint over the lifetime of the connection.
          Implementations MUST support all of the settings defined by this specification.
        </t>
        <t>
          Each parameter in a SETTINGS frame replaces any existing value for that parameter.
          Settings are processed in the order in which they appear, and a receiver of a SETTINGS
          frame does not need to maintain any state other than the current value of each setting.
          Therefore, the value of a SETTINGS parameter is the last value that is seen by
          a receiver.
        </t>
        <t>
          SETTINGS frames are acknowledged by the receiving peer. To enable this, the SETTINGS
          frame defines the ACK flag:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>ACK (0x1):</dt>
          <dd>
              When set, bit 0 indicates that this frame acknowledges receipt and application of the
              peer's SETTINGS frame.  When this bit is set, the frame payload of the SETTINGS frame MUST
              be empty.  Receipt of a SETTINGS frame with the ACK flag set and a length field value
              other than 0 MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection
              error</xref> of type <xref target="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR" format="none">FRAME_SIZE_ERROR</xref>.  For more information, see <xref target="SettingsSync"/> ("<xref target="SettingsSync" format="title"/>").
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          SETTINGS frames always apply to a connection, never a single stream.  The stream
          identifier for a SETTINGS frame MUST be zero (0x0). If an endpoint receives a SETTINGS
          frame whose stream identifier field is anything other than 0x0, the endpoint MUST respond
          with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The SETTINGS frame affects connection state.  A badly formed or incomplete SETTINGS frame
          MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          A SETTINGS frame with a length other than a multiple of 6 octets MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR" format="none">FRAME_SIZE_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="SettingFormat">
          <name>SETTINGS Format</name>
          <t>
            The frame payload of a SETTINGS frame consists of zero or more settings, each consisting of
            an unsigned 16-bit setting identifier and an unsigned 32-bit value.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="SettingFormatFigure">
            <name>Setting Format</name>
            <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +-------------------------------+
 |       Identifier (16)         |
 +-------------------------------+-------------------------------+
 |                        Value (32)                             |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="SettingValues">
          <name>Defined Settings</name>
          <t>
            The following settings are defined:
          </t>
          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt anchor="SETTINGS_HEADER_TABLE_SIZE">SETTINGS_HEADER_TABLE_SIZE (0x1):</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                  Allows the sender to inform the remote endpoint of the maximum size of the
                  compression table used to decode field blocks, in octets. The encoder can select
                  any size equal to or less than this value by using signaling specific to the
                  compression format inside a field block (see <xref target="COMPRESSION"/>). The initial value is 4,096 octets.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt anchor="SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH">SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH (0x2):</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                This setting can be used to disable <xref target="PushResources">server
                push</xref>. A server MUST NOT send a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE"
                format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame if it receives this parameter set to a value
                of 0. A client that has both set this parameter to 0 and had it acknowledged MUST
                treat the receipt of a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>
                frame as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
                <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
              </t>
              <t>
                The initial value of SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH is 1, which indicates that server push is
                permitted.  Any value other than 0 or 1 MUST be treated as a <xref
                target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type <xref
                target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
              </t>
              <t>
                A server MUST NOT explicitly set this value to 1.  A server MAY choose to omit this
                setting when it sends a SETTINGS frame, but if a server does include a value it MUST
                be 0.  A client MUST treat receipt of a SETTINGS frame with SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH set
                to 1 as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
                <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt anchor="SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS">SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS (0x3):</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                  Indicates the maximum number of concurrent streams that the sender will allow.
                  This limit is directional: it applies to the number of streams that the sender
                  permits the receiver to create. Initially, there is no limit to this value.  It is
                  recommended that this value be no smaller than 100, so as to not unnecessarily
                  limit parallelism.
              </t>
              <t>
                  A value of 0 for SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS SHOULD NOT be treated as special
                  by endpoints.  A zero value does prevent the creation of new streams; however, this
                  can also happen for any limit that is exhausted with active streams.  Servers
                  SHOULD only set a zero value for short durations; if a server does not wish to
                  accept requests, closing the connection is more appropriate.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt anchor="SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE">SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE (0x4):</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                  Indicates the sender's initial window size (in octets) for stream-level flow
                  control.  The initial value is 2<sup>16</sup>-1 (65,535) octets.
              </t>
              <t>
                  This setting affects the window size of all streams (see <xref target="InitialWindowSize"/>).
              </t>
              <t>
                  Values above the maximum flow-control window size of 2<sup>31</sup>-1 MUST
                  be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of
                  type <xref target="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR" format="none">FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR</xref>.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt anchor="SETTINGS_MAX_FRAME_SIZE">SETTINGS_MAX_FRAME_SIZE (0x5):</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                  Indicates the size of the largest frame payload that the sender is willing to
                  receive, in octets.
              </t>
              <t>
                  The initial value is 2<sup>14</sup> (16,384) octets.  The value advertised by
                  an endpoint MUST be between this initial value and the maximum allowed frame size
                  (2<sup>24</sup>-1 or 16,777,215 octets), inclusive.  Values outside this range
                  MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref>
                  of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt anchor="SETTINGS_MAX_HEADER_LIST_SIZE">SETTINGS_MAX_HEADER_LIST_SIZE (0x6):</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                  This advisory setting informs a peer of the maximum size of field section that the
                  sender is prepared to accept, in octets. The value is based on the uncompressed
                  size of field lines, including the length of the name and value in octets plus
                  an overhead of 32 octets for each field line.
              </t>
              <t>
                  For any given request, a lower limit than what is advertised MAY be enforced.  The
                  initial value of this setting is unlimited.
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
            An endpoint that receives a SETTINGS frame with any unknown or unsupported identifier
            MUST ignore that setting.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="SettingsSync">
          <name>Settings Synchronization</name>
          <t>
            Most values in SETTINGS benefit from or require an understanding of when the peer has
            received and applied the changed parameter values. In order to provide
            such synchronization timepoints, the recipient of a SETTINGS frame in which the ACK flag
            is not set MUST apply the updated settings as soon as possible upon receipt.
          </t>
          <t>
            The values in the SETTINGS frame MUST be processed in the order they appear, with no
            other frame processing between values.  Unsupported settings MUST be ignored.  Once
            all values have been processed, the recipient MUST immediately emit a SETTINGS frame
            with the ACK flag set. Upon receiving a SETTINGS frame with the ACK flag set, the sender
            of the altered settings can rely on the value having been applied.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the sender of a SETTINGS frame does not receive an acknowledgement within a
            reasonable amount of time, it MAY issue a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
            <xref target="SETTINGS_TIMEOUT" format="none">SETTINGS_TIMEOUT</xref>.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="PUSH_PROMISE">
        <name>PUSH_PROMISE</name>
        <t>
          The PUSH_PROMISE frame (type=0x5) is used to notify the peer endpoint in advance of
          streams the sender intends to initiate.  The PUSH_PROMISE frame includes the unsigned
          31-bit identifier of the stream the endpoint plans to create along with a field section
          that provides additional context for the stream.  <xref target="PushResources"/> contains a
          thorough description of the use of PUSH_PROMISE frames.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="PUSH_PROMISEPayloadFormat">
          <name>PUSH_PROMISE Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +---------------+
 |Pad Length? (8)|
 +-+-------------+-----------------------------------------------+
 |R|                  Promised Stream ID (31)                    |
 +-+-----------------------------+-------------------------------+
 |                    Field Block Fragment (*)                 ...
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                           Padding (*)                       ...
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The PUSH_PROMISE frame payload has the following fields:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Pad Length:</dt>
          <dd>
              An 8-bit field containing the length of the frame padding in units of octets.  This
              field is only present if the PADDED flag is set.
            </dd>
          <dt>R:</dt>
          <dd>
              A single reserved bit.
            </dd>
          <dt>Promised Stream ID:</dt>
          <dd>
              An unsigned 31-bit integer that identifies the stream that is reserved by the
              PUSH_PROMISE.  The promised stream identifier MUST be a valid choice for the next
              stream sent by the sender (see "new stream identifier" in <xref target="StreamIdentifiers"/>).
            </dd>
          <dt>Field Block Fragment:</dt>
          <dd>
              A <xref target="FieldBlock">field block fragment</xref> containing request control data and
              header section.
            </dd>
          <dt>Padding:</dt>
          <dd>
              Padding octets.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The PUSH_PROMISE frame defines the following flags:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>END_HEADERS (0x4):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                When set, bit 2 indicates that this frame contains an entire <xref target="FieldBlock">field block</xref> and is not followed by any
                <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames.
            </t>
            <t>
                A PUSH_PROMISE frame without the END_HEADERS flag set MUST be followed by a
                CONTINUATION frame for the same stream.  A receiver MUST treat the receipt of any
                other type of frame or a frame on a different stream as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
                <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>PADDED (0x8):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                When set, bit 3 indicates that the Pad Length field and any padding that it
                describes are present.
            </t>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          PUSH_PROMISE frames MUST only be sent on a peer-initiated stream that is in either the
          "open" or "half-closed (remote)" state. The stream identifier of a PUSH_PROMISE frame
          indicates the stream it is associated with.  If the stream identifier field specifies the
          value 0x0, a recipient MUST respond with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Promised streams are not required to be used in the order they are promised.  The
          PUSH_PROMISE only reserves stream identifiers for later use.
        </t>
        <t>
          PUSH_PROMISE MUST NOT be sent if the <xref target="SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH" format="none">SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH</xref> setting of the
          peer endpoint is set to 0.  An endpoint that has set this setting and has received
          acknowledgement MUST treat the receipt of a PUSH_PROMISE frame as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Recipients of PUSH_PROMISE frames can choose to reject promised streams by returning a
          <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> referencing the promised stream identifier back to the sender of
          the PUSH_PROMISE.
        </t>
        <t>
          A PUSH_PROMISE frame modifies the connection state in two ways.  First, the inclusion of a <xref target="FieldBlock">field block</xref> potentially modifies the state maintained for
          field section compression.  Second, PUSH_PROMISE also reserves a stream for later use, causing the
          promised stream to enter the "reserved" state.  A sender MUST NOT send a PUSH_PROMISE on a
          stream unless that stream is either "open" or "half-closed (remote)"; the sender MUST
          ensure that the promised stream is a valid choice for a <xref target="StreamIdentifiers">new stream identifier</xref> (that is, the promised stream MUST
          be in the "idle" state).
        </t>
        <t>
          Since PUSH_PROMISE reserves a stream, ignoring a PUSH_PROMISE frame causes the stream
          state to become indeterminate.  A receiver MUST treat the receipt of a PUSH_PROMISE on a
          stream that is neither "open" nor "half-closed (local)" as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.  However, an endpoint that has sent
          <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> on the associated stream MUST handle PUSH_PROMISE frames that
          might have been created before the <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame is received and
          processed.
        </t>
        <t>
          A receiver MUST treat the receipt of a PUSH_PROMISE that promises an <xref target="StreamIdentifiers">illegal stream identifier</xref> as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>. Note that an illegal stream identifier
          is an identifier for a stream that is not currently in the "idle" state.
        </t>
        <t>
          The PUSH_PROMISE frame can include padding.  Padding fields and flags are identical to
          those defined for <xref target="DATA">DATA frames</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="PING">
        <name>PING</name>
        <t>
          The PING frame (type=0x6) is a mechanism for measuring a minimal round-trip time from the
          sender, as well as determining whether an idle connection is still functional.  PING
          frames can be sent from any endpoint.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="PINGPayloadFormat">
          <name>PING Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                                                               |
 |                      Opaque Data (64)                         |
 |                                                               |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          In addition to the frame header, PING frames MUST contain 8 octets of opaque data in the frame payload.
          A sender can include any value it chooses and use those octets in any fashion.
        </t>
        <t>
          Receivers of a PING frame that does not include an ACK flag MUST send a PING frame with
          the ACK flag set in response, with an identical frame payload.  PING responses SHOULD be given
          higher priority than any other frame.
        </t>
        <t>
          The PING frame defines the following flags:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>ACK (0x1):</dt>
          <dd>
              When set, bit 0 indicates that this PING frame is a PING response.  An endpoint MUST
              set this flag in PING responses.  An endpoint MUST NOT respond to PING frames
              containing this flag.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          PING frames are not associated with any individual stream. If a PING frame is received
          with a stream identifier field value other than 0x0, the recipient MUST respond with a
          <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Receipt of a PING frame with a length field value other than 8 MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR" format="none">FRAME_SIZE_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="GOAWAY">
        <name>GOAWAY</name>
        <t>
          The GOAWAY frame (type=0x7) is used to initiate shutdown of a connection or to signal
          serious error conditions.  GOAWAY allows an endpoint to gracefully stop accepting new
          streams while still finishing processing of previously established streams.  This enables
          administrative actions, like server maintenance.
        </t>
        <t>
          There is an inherent race condition between an endpoint starting new streams and the
          remote sending a GOAWAY frame.  To deal with this case, the GOAWAY contains the stream
          identifier of the last peer-initiated stream that was or might be processed on the
          sending endpoint in this connection.  For instance, if the server sends a GOAWAY frame,
          the identified stream is the highest-numbered stream initiated by the client.
        </t>
        <t>
          Once sent, the sender will ignore frames sent on streams initiated by the receiver if the
          stream has an identifier higher than the included last stream identifier.  Receivers of a
          GOAWAY frame MUST NOT open additional streams on the connection, although a new connection
          can be established for new streams.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the receiver of the GOAWAY has sent data on streams with a higher stream identifier
          than what is indicated in the GOAWAY frame, those streams are not or will not be
          processed.  The receiver of the GOAWAY frame can treat the streams as though they had
          never been created at all, thereby allowing those streams to be retried later on a new
          connection.
        </t>
        <t>
          Endpoints SHOULD always send a GOAWAY frame before closing a connection so that the remote
          peer can know whether a stream has been partially processed or not.  For example, if an
          HTTP client sends a POST at the same time that a server closes a connection, the client
          cannot know if the server started to process that POST request if the server does not send
          a GOAWAY frame to indicate what streams it might have acted on.
        </t>
        <t>
          An endpoint might choose to close a connection without sending a GOAWAY for misbehaving
          peers.
        </t>
        <t>
          A GOAWAY frame might not immediately precede closing of the connection; a receiver of a
          GOAWAY that has no more use for the connection SHOULD still send a GOAWAY frame before
          terminating the connection.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="GOAWAYPayloadFormat">
          <name>GOAWAY Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
 |R|                  Last-Stream-ID (31)                        |
 +-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                      Error Code (32)                          |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                  Additional Debug Data (*)                    |
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The GOAWAY frame does not define any flags.
        </t>
        <t>
          The GOAWAY frame applies to the connection, not a specific stream.  An endpoint MUST treat
          a <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frame with a stream identifier other than 0x0 as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The last stream identifier in the GOAWAY frame contains the highest-numbered stream
          identifier for which the sender of the GOAWAY frame might have taken some action on or
          might yet take action on.  All streams up to and including the identified stream might
          have been processed in some way.  The last stream identifier can be set to 0 if no streams
          were processed.
        </t>
        <aside>
          <t>Note:
            In this context, "processed" means that some data from the stream was passed to some
            higher layer of software that might have taken some action as a result.
          </t>
        </aside>
        <t>
          If a connection terminates without a GOAWAY frame, the last stream identifier is
          effectively the highest possible stream identifier.
        </t>
        <t>
          On streams with lower- or equal-numbered identifiers that were not closed completely prior
          to the connection being closed, reattempting requests, transactions, or any protocol
          activity is not possible, with the exception of idempotent actions like HTTP GET, PUT, or
          DELETE.  Any protocol activity that uses higher-numbered streams can be safely retried
          using a new connection.
        </t>
        <t>
          Activity on streams numbered lower or equal to the last stream identifier might still
          complete successfully.  The sender of a GOAWAY frame might gracefully shut down a
          connection by sending a GOAWAY frame, maintaining the connection in an "open" state until
          all in-progress streams complete.
        </t>
        <t>
          An endpoint MAY send multiple GOAWAY frames if circumstances change.  For instance, an
          endpoint that sends GOAWAY with <xref target="NO_ERROR" format="none">NO_ERROR</xref> during graceful shutdown could
          subsequently encounter a condition that requires immediate termination of the connection.
          The last stream identifier from the last GOAWAY frame received indicates which streams
          could have been acted upon.  Endpoints MUST NOT increase the value they send in the last
          stream identifier, since the peers might already have retried unprocessed requests on
          another connection.
        </t>
        <t>
          A client that is unable to retry requests loses all requests that are in flight when the
          server closes the connection.  This is especially true for intermediaries that might not
          be serving clients using HTTP/2.  A server that is attempting to gracefully shut down a
          connection SHOULD send an initial GOAWAY frame with the last stream identifier set to
          2<sup>31</sup>-1 and a <xref target="NO_ERROR" format="none">NO_ERROR</xref> code.  This signals to the client that
          a shutdown is imminent and that initiating further requests is prohibited.  After allowing
          time for any in-flight stream creation (at least one round-trip time),  the server can
          send another GOAWAY frame with an updated last stream identifier.  This ensures that a
          connection can be cleanly shut down without losing requests.
        </t>
        <t>
          After sending a GOAWAY frame, the sender can discard frames for streams initiated by the
          receiver with identifiers higher than the identified last stream.  However, any frames
          that alter connection state cannot be completely ignored.  For instance,
          <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>, <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>, and <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames
          MUST be minimally processed to ensure the state maintained for field section compression is
          consistent (see <xref target="FieldBlock"/>); similarly, DATA frames MUST be counted
          toward the connection flow-control window.  Failure to process these frames can cause flow
          control or field section compression state to become unsynchronized.
        </t>
        <t>
          The GOAWAY frame also contains a 32-bit <xref target="ErrorCodes">error code</xref> that
          contains the reason for closing the connection.
        </t>
        <t>
          Endpoints MAY append opaque data to the frame payload of any GOAWAY frame.  Additional debug
          data is intended for diagnostic purposes only and carries no semantic value.  Debug
          information could contain security- or privacy-sensitive data.  Logged or otherwise
          persistently stored debug data MUST have adequate safeguards to prevent unauthorized
          access.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="WINDOW_UPDATE">
        <name>WINDOW_UPDATE</name>
        <t>
          The WINDOW_UPDATE frame (type=0x8) is used to implement flow control; see <xref target="FlowControl"/> for an overview.
        </t>
        <t>
          Flow control operates at two levels: on each individual stream and on the entire
          connection.
        </t>
        <t>
          Both types of flow control are hop by hop, that is, only between the two endpoints.
          Intermediaries do not forward WINDOW_UPDATE frames between dependent connections.
          However, throttling of data transfer by any receiver can indirectly cause the propagation
          of flow-control information toward the original sender.
        </t>
        <t>
          Flow control only applies to frames that are identified as being subject to flow control.
          Of the frame types defined in this document, this includes only <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames.
          Frames that are exempt from flow control MUST be accepted and processed, unless the
          receiver is unable to assign resources to handling the frame.  A receiver MAY respond with
          a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> or <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR" format="none">FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR</xref> if it is unable to accept a frame.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="WINDOW_UPDATEPayloadFormat">
          <name>WINDOW_UPDATE Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
 |R|              Window Size Increment (31)                     |
 +-+-------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The frame payload of a WINDOW_UPDATE frame is one reserved bit plus an unsigned 31-bit integer
          indicating the number of octets that the sender can transmit in addition to the existing
          flow-control window.  The legal range for the increment to the flow-control window is 1 to
          2<sup>31</sup>-1 (2,147,483,647) octets.
        </t>
        <t>
          The WINDOW_UPDATE frame does not define any flags.
        </t>
        <t>
          The WINDOW_UPDATE frame can be specific to a stream or to the entire connection.  In the
          former case, the frame's stream identifier indicates the affected stream; in the latter,
          the value "0" indicates that the entire connection is the subject of the frame.
        </t>
        <t>
          A receiver MUST treat the receipt of a WINDOW_UPDATE frame with an flow-control window
          increment of 0 as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>; errors on the connection flow-control window MUST be
          treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          WINDOW_UPDATE can be sent by a peer that has sent a frame bearing the END_STREAM flag.
          This means that a receiver could receive a WINDOW_UPDATE frame on a "half-closed (remote)"
          or "closed" stream.  A receiver MUST NOT treat this as an error (see <xref target="StreamStates"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          A receiver that receives a flow-controlled frame MUST always account for its contribution
          against the connection flow-control window, unless the receiver treats this as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref>.  This is necessary even if the
          frame is in error.  The sender counts the frame toward the flow-control window, but if
          the receiver does not, the flow-control window at the sender and receiver can become
          different.
        </t>
        <t>
          A WINDOW_UPDATE frame with a length other than 4 octets MUST be treated as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR" format="none">FRAME_SIZE_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <section>
          <name>The Flow-Control Window</name>
          <t>
            Flow control in HTTP/2 is implemented using a window kept by each sender on every
            stream. The flow-control window is a simple integer value that indicates how many octets
            of data the sender is permitted to transmit; as such, its size is a measure of the
            buffering capacity of the receiver.
          </t>
          <t>
            Two flow-control windows are applicable: the stream flow-control window and the
            connection flow-control window.  The sender MUST NOT send a flow-controlled frame with a
            length that exceeds the space available in either of the flow-control windows advertised
            by the receiver.  Frames with zero length with the END_STREAM flag set (that is, an
            empty <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame) MAY be sent if there is no available space in either
            flow-control window.
          </t>
          <t>
            For flow-control calculations, the 9-octet frame header is not counted.
          </t>
          <t>
            After sending a flow-controlled frame, the sender reduces the space available in both
            windows by the length of the transmitted frame.
          </t>
          <t>
            The receiver of a frame sends a WINDOW_UPDATE frame as it consumes data and frees up
            space in flow-control windows.  Separate WINDOW_UPDATE frames are sent for the stream-
            and connection-level flow-control windows.
          </t>
          <t>
            A sender that receives a WINDOW_UPDATE frame updates the corresponding window by the
            amount specified in the frame.
          </t>
          <t>
            A sender MUST NOT allow a flow-control window to exceed 2<sup>31</sup>-1 octets.
            If a sender receives a WINDOW_UPDATE that causes a flow-control window to exceed this
            maximum, it MUST terminate either the stream or the connection, as appropriate.  For
            streams, the sender sends a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> with an error code of
            <xref target="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR" format="none">FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR</xref>; for the connection, a <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref>
            frame with an error code of <xref target="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR" format="none">FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR</xref> is sent.
          </t>
          <t>
            Flow-controlled frames from the sender and WINDOW_UPDATE frames from the receiver are
            completely asynchronous with respect to each other. This property allows a receiver to
            aggressively update the window size kept by the sender to prevent streams from stalling.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="InitialWindowSize">
          <name>Initial Flow-Control Window Size</name>
          <t>
            When an HTTP/2 connection is first established, new streams are created with an initial
            flow-control window size of 65,535 octets. The connection flow-control window is also 65,535
            octets. Both endpoints can adjust the initial window size for new streams by including
            a value for <xref target="SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE</xref> in the <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref>
            frame that forms part of the connection preface. The connection flow-control window can
            only be changed using WINDOW_UPDATE frames.
          </t>
          <t>
            Prior to receiving a <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame that sets a value for
            <xref target="SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE</xref>, an endpoint can only use the default
            initial window size when sending flow-controlled frames.  Similarly, the connection flow-control
            window is set to the default initial window size until a WINDOW_UPDATE frame is
            received.
          </t>
          <t>
            In addition to changing the flow-control window for streams that are not yet active, a
            <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame can alter the initial flow-control window size for streams
            with active flow-control windows (that is, streams in the "open" or "half-closed
            (remote)" state).  When the value of <xref target="SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE</xref>
            changes, a receiver MUST adjust the size of all stream flow-control windows that it
            maintains by the difference between the new value and the old value.
          </t>
          <t>
            A change to <xref target="SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE</xref> can cause the available space in
            a flow-control window to become negative.  A sender MUST track the negative flow-control
            window and MUST NOT send new flow-controlled frames until it receives WINDOW_UPDATE
            frames that cause the flow-control window to become positive.
          </t>
          <t>
            For example, if the client sends 60 KB immediately on connection establishment and the
            server sets the initial window size to be 16 KB, the client will recalculate the
            available flow-control window to be -44 KB on receipt of the <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref>
            frame.  The client retains a negative flow-control window until WINDOW_UPDATE frames
            restore the window to being positive, after which the client can resume sending.
          </t>
          <t>
            A <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame cannot alter the connection flow-control window.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint MUST treat a change to <xref target="SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE</xref> that
            causes any flow-control window to exceed the maximum size as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
            <xref target="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR" format="none">FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR</xref>.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Reducing the Stream Window Size</name>
          <t>
            A receiver that wishes to use a smaller flow-control window than the current size can
            send a new <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame.  However, the receiver MUST be prepared to
            receive data that exceeds this window size, since the sender might send data that
            exceeds the lower limit prior to processing the <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame.
          </t>
          <t>
            After sending a SETTINGS frame that reduces the initial flow-control window size, a
            receiver MAY continue to process streams that exceed flow-control limits.  Allowing
            streams to continue does not allow the receiver to immediately reduce the space it
            reserves for flow-control windows.  Progress on these streams can also stall, since
            <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> frames are needed to allow the sender to resume sending.
            The receiver MAY instead send a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> with an error code of
            <xref target="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR" format="none">FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR</xref> for the affected streams.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="CONTINUATION">
        <name>CONTINUATION</name>
        <t>
          The CONTINUATION frame (type=0x9) is used to continue a sequence of <xref target="FieldBlock">field block fragments</xref>.  Any number of CONTINUATION frames can
          be sent, as long as the preceding frame is on the same stream and is a
          <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>, <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>, or CONTINUATION frame without the
          END_HEADERS flag set.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="CONTINUATIONFramePayload">
          <name>CONTINUATION Frame Payload</name>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                    Field Block Fragment (*)                 ...
 +---------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The CONTINUATION frame payload contains a <xref target="FieldBlock">field block
          fragment</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The CONTINUATION frame defines the following flag:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>END_HEADERS (0x4):</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>
                When set, bit 2 indicates that this frame ends a <xref target="FieldBlock">field
                block</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
                If the END_HEADERS bit is not set, this frame MUST be followed by another
                CONTINUATION frame.  A receiver MUST treat the receipt of any other type of frame or
                a frame on a different stream as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection
                error</xref> of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </t>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The CONTINUATION frame changes the connection state as defined in <xref target="FieldBlock"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          CONTINUATION frames MUST be associated with a stream. If a CONTINUATION frame is received
          whose stream identifier field is 0x0, the recipient MUST respond with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type PROTOCOL_ERROR.
        </t>
        <t>
          A CONTINUATION frame MUST be preceded by a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>,
          <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> or CONTINUATION frame without the END_HEADERS flag set.  A
          recipient that observes violation of this rule MUST respond with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler"> connection error</xref> of type
          <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ErrorCodes">
      <name>Error Codes</name>
      <t>
        Error codes are 32-bit fields that are used in <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> and
        <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frames to convey the reasons for the stream or connection error.
      </t>
      <t>
        Error codes share a common code space.  Some error codes apply only to either streams or the
        entire connection and have no defined semantics in the other context.
      </t>
      <t>
        The following error codes are defined:
      </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>NO_ERROR (0x0):</dt>
        <dd anchor="NO_ERROR">
            The associated condition is not a result of an error.  For example, a
            <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> might include this code to indicate graceful shutdown of a
            connection.
          </dd>
        <dt>PROTOCOL_ERROR (0x1):</dt>
        <dd anchor="PROTOCOL_ERROR">
            The endpoint detected an unspecific protocol error.  This error is for use when a more
            specific error code is not available.
          </dd>
        <dt>INTERNAL_ERROR (0x2):</dt>
        <dd anchor="INTERNAL_ERROR">
            The endpoint encountered an unexpected internal error.
          </dd>
        <dt>FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR (0x3):</dt>
        <dd anchor="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR">
            The endpoint detected that its peer violated the flow-control protocol.
          </dd>
        <dt>SETTINGS_TIMEOUT (0x4):</dt>
        <dd anchor="SETTINGS_TIMEOUT">
            The endpoint sent a <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame but did not receive a response in a
            timely manner.  See <xref target="SettingsSync"/> ("Settings Synchronization").
          </dd>
        <dt>STREAM_CLOSED (0x5):</dt>
        <dd anchor="STREAM_CLOSED">
            The endpoint received a frame after a stream was half-closed.
          </dd>
        <dt>FRAME_SIZE_ERROR (0x6):</dt>
        <dd anchor="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR">
            The endpoint received a frame with an invalid size.
          </dd>
        <dt>REFUSED_STREAM (0x7):</dt>
        <dd anchor="REFUSED_STREAM">
            The endpoint refused the stream prior to performing any application processing (see
            <xref target="Reliability"/> for details).
          </dd>
        <dt>CANCEL (0x8):</dt>
        <dd anchor="CANCEL">
            Used by the endpoint to indicate that the stream is no longer needed.
          </dd>
        <dt>COMPRESSION_ERROR (0x9):</dt>
        <dd anchor="COMPRESSION_ERROR">
            The endpoint is unable to maintain the field section compression context for the
            connection.
          </dd>
        <dt>CONNECT_ERROR (0xa):</dt>
        <dd anchor="CONNECT_ERROR">
            The connection established in response to a <xref target="CONNECT">CONNECT
            request</xref> was reset or abnormally closed.
          </dd>
        <dt>ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM (0xb):</dt>
        <dd anchor="ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM">
            The endpoint detected that its peer is exhibiting a behavior that might be generating
            excessive load.
          </dd>
        <dt>INADEQUATE_SECURITY (0xc):</dt>
        <dd anchor="INADEQUATE_SECURITY">
            The underlying transport has properties that do not meet minimum security
            requirements (see <xref target="TLSUsage"/>).
          </dd>
        <dt>HTTP_1_1_REQUIRED (0xd):</dt>
        <dd anchor="HTTP_1_1_REQUIRED">
            The endpoint requires that HTTP/1.1 be used instead of HTTP/2.
          </dd>
      </dl>
      <t>
        Unknown or unsupported error codes MUST NOT trigger any special behavior.  These MAY be
        treated by an implementation as being equivalent to <xref target="INTERNAL_ERROR" format="none">INTERNAL_ERROR</xref>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="HTTPLayer">
      <name>HTTP Message Exchanges</name>
      <t>
        HTTP/2 defines a framing of the HTTP message abstraction
        (<xref target="HTTP" section="6"/>).
      </t>
      <section anchor="HttpSequence">
        <name>HTTP Message Framing</name>
        <t>
          A client sends an HTTP request on a new stream, using a previously unused <xref target="StreamIdentifiers">stream identifier</xref>.  A server sends an HTTP response on
          the same stream as the request.
        </t>
        <t>
          An HTTP message (request or response) consists of:
        </t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>
              one <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame (followed by zero or
              more <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames) containing
              the header section (see <xref target="HTTP" section="6.3"/>),
            </li>
          <li>
              zero or more <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames containing the
              message content (see <xref target="HTTP" section="6.4"/>), and
            </li>
          <li>
              optionally, one <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame, followed by
              zero or more <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames
              containing the trailer-part, if present (see <xref target="HTTP"
              section="6.5"/>).
            </li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          For a response only, a server MAY send any number of interim responses before the <xref
          target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame containing a final response.  An
          interim response consists of a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frames
          (which might be followed by zero or more <xref target="CONTINUATION"
          format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames) containing the control data and header section
          of an interim (1xx) HTTP response (see <xref target="HTTP" section="15"/>).  A <xref
          target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame with an END_STREAM flag that carries
          an informational status code is <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
        </t>

        <t>
          The last frame in the sequence bears an END_STREAM flag, noting that a
          <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame bearing the END_STREAM flag can be followed by
          <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames that carry any remaining fragments of the field block.
        </t>
        <t>
          Other frames (from any stream) MUST NOT occur between the <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame
          and any <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames that might follow.
        </t>
        <t>
          HTTP/2 uses DATA frames to carry message content.  The <tt>chunked</tt> transfer encoding
          defined in <xref target="HTTP11" section="7.1"/> cannot be used in HTTP/2.
        </t>
        <t>
          Trailer fields are carried in a field block that also terminates the stream.  That is,
          trailer fields comprise a sequence starting with a <xref target="HEADERS"
          format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame, followed by zero or more <xref target="CONTINUATION"
          format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames, where the <xref target="HEADERS"
          format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame bears an END_STREAM flag.  Trailers MUST NOT include
          <xref target="PseudoHeaderFields">pseudo-header fields</xref>.  An endpoint that receives
          pseudo-header fields in trailers MUST treat the request or response as <xref
          target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          An endpoint that receives a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame
          without the END_STREAM flag set after receiving the <xref target="HEADERS"
          format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame that opens a request or after receiving a final
          (non-informational) status code MUST treat the corresponding request or response as <xref
          target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          An HTTP request/response exchange fully consumes a single stream.  A request starts with
          the <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame that puts the stream into an "open" state. The request
          ends with a frame bearing END_STREAM, which causes the stream to become "half-closed
          (local)" for the client and "half-closed (remote)" for the server.  A response stream starts with
          zero or more interim responses in <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frames or
          a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame containing a final status code.
        </t>
        <t>
          An HTTP response is complete after the server sends -- or the client receives -- a frame
          with the END_STREAM flag set (including any <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames needed to
          complete a field block).  A server can send a complete response prior to the client
          sending an entire request if the response does not depend on any portion of the request
          that has not been sent and received.  When this is true, a server MAY request that the
          client abort transmission of a request without error by sending a
          <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> with an error code of <xref target="NO_ERROR" format="none">NO_ERROR</xref> after sending a
          complete response (i.e., a frame with the END_STREAM flag).  Clients MUST NOT discard
          responses as a result of receiving such a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>, though clients can
          always discard responses at their discretion for other reasons.
        </t>
        <section anchor="informational-responses">
          <name>Upgrading from HTTP/2</name>
          <t>
            HTTP/2 removes support for the 101 (Switching Protocols) informational status code
            (<xref target="HTTP" section="15.2.2"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            The semantics of 101 (Switching Protocols) aren't applicable to a multiplexed protocol.
            Alternative protocols are able to use the same mechanisms that HTTP/2 uses to negotiate
            their use (see <xref target="starting"/>).
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="HttpHeaders">
          <name>HTTP Fields</name>
          <t>
            HTTP fields carry information as a series of field lines, which are key-value pairs. For a listing of
            registered HTTP fields, see the "Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) Field Name Registry" registry maintained at <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/http-fields/"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Just as in HTTP/1.x, field names are strings of ASCII characters that are
            compared in a case-insensitive fashion. Field names MUST be converted
            to lowercase prior to their encoding in HTTP/2. A request or response containing
            uppercase header field names MUST be treated as <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
          </t>
          <section anchor="PseudoHeaderFields">
            <name>Pseudo-Header Fields</name>
            <t>
              HTTP/2 uses special pseudo-header fields beginning with ':' character (ASCII 0x3a) to
              convey message control data (see <xref target="HTTP" section="6.2"/>).
            </t>
            <t>
              Pseudo-header fields are not HTTP header fields.  Endpoints MUST NOT generate
              pseudo-header fields other than those defined in this document.  Note that an
              extension could negotiate the use of additional pseudo-header fields; see
              <xref target="extensibility"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
              Pseudo-header fields are only valid in the context in which they are defined.
              Pseudo-header fields defined for requests MUST NOT appear in responses; pseudo-header
              fields defined for responses MUST NOT appear in requests.  Pseudo-header fields MUST
              NOT appear in a trailer section.  Endpoints MUST treat a request or response that contains
              undefined or invalid pseudo-header fields as <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
              All pseudo-header fields MUST appear in a field block before all regular field lines.
              Any request or response that contains a pseudo-header field that appears in a field
              block after a regular field line MUST be treated as <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section>
            <name>Connection-Specific Header Fields</name>
            <t>
              HTTP/2 does not use the <tt>Connection</tt> header field to
              indicate connection-specific header fields; in this protocol, connection-specific
              metadata is conveyed by other means.  An endpoint MUST NOT generate an HTTP/2 message
              containing connection-specific header fields; any message containing
              connection-specific header fields MUST be treated as <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
              The only exception to this is the TE header field, which MAY be present in an HTTP/2
              request; when it is, it MUST NOT contain any value other than "trailers".
            </t>
            <t>
              An intermediary transforming a HTTP/1.x message to HTTP/2 MUST remove connection-specific
              header fields as discussed in <xref target="HTTP" section="7.6.1"/>,
              or their messages will be treated by other HTTP/2 endpoints as <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
            </t>
            <aside>
              <t>Note:
                HTTP/2 purposefully does not support upgrade to another protocol.  The handshake
                methods described in <xref target="starting"/> are believed sufficient to
                negotiate the use of alternative protocols.
              </t>
            </aside>
          </section>
          <section anchor="HttpRequest">
            <name>Request Pseudo-Header Fields</name>
            <t>
              The following pseudo-header fields are defined for HTTP/2 requests:
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>
                <t>
                    The <tt>:method</tt> pseudo-header field includes the HTTP
                    method (<xref target="HTTP" section="9"/>).
                </t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>
                  The <tt>:scheme</tt> pseudo-header field includes the scheme portion of the
                  request target.  The scheme is taken from the target URI (<xref target="RFC3986"
                  section="3.1"/>) when generating a request directly, or from the scheme of a
                  translated request (for example. see <xref target="HTTP11" section="3.3"/>).
                  Scheme is omitted for <xref target="CONNECT">CONNECT requests</xref>.
                </t>
                <t>
                  <tt>:scheme</tt> is not restricted to <tt>http</tt> and <tt>https</tt> schemed
                  URIs.  A proxy or gateway can translate requests for non-HTTP schemes, enabling
                  the use of HTTP to interact with non-HTTP services.
                </t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>
                    The <tt>:authority</tt> pseudo-header field includes the
                    authority portion of the target URI (<xref target="RFC3986" section="3.2"/>). The
                    authority MUST NOT include the deprecated <tt>userinfo</tt> subcomponent for
                    <tt>http</tt> or <tt>https</tt> schemed URIs.
                </t>
                <t>
                  Clients that generate HTTP/2 requests directly SHOULD use the <tt>:authority</tt>
                  pseudo-header field instead of the <tt>Host</tt> header field.
                </t>
                <t>
                  An intermediary that translates a request to HTTP/2 from another HTTP version MUST
                  translate any authority information from the request into an <tt>:authority</tt>
                  pseudo-header field.  If the control data in the original request contains
                  authority information, an intermediary MUST include a <tt>:authority</tt>
                  pseudo-header field.  If control data does not contain authority, an intermediary
                  MUST NOT add an <tt>:authority</tt> pseudo-header field.  For reference, an
                  HTTP/1.1 <xref target="HTTP11" section="3.2">request target</xref> in
                  authority-form always includes authority, a request target in absolute-form
                  includes authority if the target URI includes authority, and request targets in
                  origin- or asterisk-form do not include authority.
                </t>
                <t>
                  An intermediary that translates a request to another HTTP version from HTTP/2 can
                  construct a <tt>Host</tt> header field by copying the value of the
                  <tt>:authority</tt> pseudo-header field if that version requires that
                  <tt>Host</tt> be included in a request, as HTTP/1.1 does for some forms of request
                  target (see <xref target="HTTP11" section="3.2"/>).
                </t>
                <t>
                  An intermediary that translates a request to HTTP/2 from another HTTP version MUST
                  retain any <tt>Host</tt> header field, even if an authority is part of control
                  data.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The value of the <tt>Host</tt> header field MUST be ignored if control data
                  contains authority (that is, the <tt>:authority</tt> pseudo-header field is
                  present).
                </t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>
                    The <tt>:path</tt> pseudo-header field includes the path and
                    query parts of the target URI (the <tt>path-absolute</tt>
                    production and optionally a '?' character followed by the
                    <tt>query</tt> production (see Sections 3.3 and 3.4 of <xref target="RFC3986"/>).
                    A request in asterisk form includes the value '*' for the
                    <tt>:path</tt> pseudo-header field.
                </t>
                <t>
                    This pseudo-header field MUST NOT be empty for <tt>http</tt> or <tt>https</tt>
                    URIs; <tt>http</tt> or <tt>https</tt> URIs that do not contain a path component
                    MUST include a value of '/'. The exception to this rule is an OPTIONS request
                    for an <tt>http</tt> or <tt>https</tt> URI that does not include a path
                    component; these MUST include a <tt>:path</tt> pseudo-header field with a value
                    of '*' (see <xref target="HTTP" section="7.1"/>).
                </t>
              </li>
            </ul>
            <t>
              All HTTP/2 requests MUST include exactly one valid value for the <tt>:method</tt>, <tt>:scheme</tt>, and <tt>:path</tt> pseudo-header fields, unless it is a <xref target="CONNECT">CONNECT request</xref>. An HTTP request that omits mandatory
              pseudo-header fields is <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
              Individual HTTP/2 requests do not carry an explicit indicator of protocol version.
              All HTTP/2 messages implicitly have a protocol version of "2.0" (see
              <xref target="HTTP" section="6.2"/>).
            </t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="HttpResponse">
            <name>Response Pseudo-Header Fields</name>
            <t>
              For HTTP/2 responses, a single <tt>:status</tt> pseudo-header
              field is defined that carries the HTTP status code field (see
              <xref target="HTTP" section="15"/>). This pseudo-header field MUST be included in all
              responses, including interim responses; otherwise, the response is
              <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
              HTTP/2 responses implicitly have a protocol version of "2.0".
            </t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="CompressCookie">
            <name>Compressing the Cookie Header Field</name>
            <t>
              The <xref target="COOKIE">Cookie header field</xref> uses a semi-colon (";") to
              delimit cookie-pairs (or "crumbs").  This header field contains multiple values, but
              does not use a COMMA (",") as a separator, which prevents cookie-pairs from being sent
              on multiple field lines (see <xref target="HTTP" section="5.2"/>).  This can
              significantly reduce compression efficiency as updates to individual cookie-pairs
              would invalidate any field lines that are stored in the HPACK table.
            </t>
            <t>
              To allow for better compression efficiency, the Cookie header field MAY be split into
              separate header fields, each with one or more cookie-pairs.  If there are multiple
              Cookie header fields after decompression, these MUST be concatenated into a single
              octet string using the two-octet delimiter of 0x3B, 0x20 (the ASCII string "; ")
              before being passed into a non-HTTP/2 context, such as an HTTP/1.1 connection, or a
              generic HTTP server application.
            </t>
            <t keepWithNext="true">
                Therefore, the following two lists of Cookie header fields are semantically
                equivalent.
            </t>
            <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
  cookie: a=b; c=d; e=f

  cookie: a=b
  cookie: c=d
  cookie: e=f
]]></artwork>
          </section>
          <section anchor="malformed">
            <name>Malformed Requests and Responses</name>
            <t>
              A malformed request or response is one that is an otherwise valid sequence of HTTP/2
              frames but is invalid due to the presence of extraneous frames, prohibited
              fields or pseudo-header fields, the absence of mandatory fields or pseudo-header fields,
              or the inclusion of uppercase field names.
            </t>
            <t>
              A request or response that includes message content can include a <tt>content-length</tt> header field.  A request or response is also
              malformed if the value of a <tt>content-length</tt> header field
              does not equal the sum of the <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame payload lengths that form the
              content.  A response that is defined to have no content, as described in <xref target="HTTP" section="6.4"/>, can have a non-zero
              <tt>content-length</tt> header field, even though no content is
              included in <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames.
            </t>
            <t>
              Intermediaries that process HTTP requests or responses (i.e., any intermediary not
              acting as a tunnel) MUST NOT forward a malformed request or response.  Malformed
              requests or responses that are detected MUST be treated as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
              For malformed requests, a server MAY send an HTTP response prior to closing or
              resetting the stream.  Clients MUST NOT accept a malformed response. Note that these
              requirements are intended to protect against several types of common attacks against
              HTTP; they are deliberately strict because being permissive can expose
              implementations to these vulnerabilities.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Examples</name>
          <t>
            This section shows HTTP/1.1 requests and responses, with illustrations of equivalent
            HTTP/2 requests and responses.
          </t>
          <t>
            An HTTP GET request includes control data and a request header with no message content and is therefore
            transmitted as a single <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame, followed by zero or more
            <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames containing the serialized block of request header
            fields.  The <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame in the following has both the END_HEADERS and
            END_STREAM flags set; no <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames are sent.
          </t>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
  GET /resource HTTP/1.1           HEADERS
  Host: example.org          ==>     + END_STREAM
  Accept: image/jpeg                 + END_HEADERS
                                       :method = GET
                                       :scheme = https
                                       :path = /resource
                                       host = example.org
                                       accept = image/jpeg
]]></artwork>
          <t>
            Similarly, a response that includes only control data and a response header is transmitted as a
            <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame (again, followed by zero or more
            <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames) containing the serialized block of response header
            fields.
          </t>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 304 Not Modified        HEADERS
  ETag: "xyzzy"              ==>     + END_STREAM
  Expires: Thu, 23 Jan ...           + END_HEADERS
                                       :status = 304
                                       etag = "xyzzy"
                                       expires = Thu, 23 Jan ...
]]></artwork>
          <t>
            An HTTP POST request that includes control data and a request header and message content is transmitted
            as one <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame, followed by zero or more
            <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames containing the request header, followed by one
            or more <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames, with the last <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> (or
            <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>) frame having the END_HEADERS flag set and the final
            <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame having the END_STREAM flag set:
          </t>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
  POST /resource HTTP/1.1          HEADERS
  Host: example.org          ==>     - END_STREAM
  Content-Type: image/jpeg           - END_HEADERS
  Content-Length: 123                  :method = POST
                                       :path = /resource
  {binary data}                        :scheme = https

                                   CONTINUATION
                                     + END_HEADERS
                                       content-type = image/jpeg
                                       host = example.org
                                       content-length = 123

                                   DATA
                                     + END_STREAM
                                   {binary data}
]]></artwork>
          <t keepWithPrevious="true">
              Note that data contributing to any given field line could be spread between field
              block fragments.  The allocation of field lines to frames in this example is
              illustrative only.
          </t>
          <t>
            A response that includes control data and a response header and message content is transmitted as a
            <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame, followed by zero or more <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref>
            frames, followed by one or more <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames, with the last
            <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame in the sequence having the END_STREAM flag set:
          </t>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK                  HEADERS
  Content-Type: image/jpeg   ==>     - END_STREAM
  Content-Length: 123                + END_HEADERS
                                       :status = 200
  {binary data}                        content-type = image/jpeg
                                       content-length = 123

                                   DATA
                                     + END_STREAM
                                   {binary data}
]]></artwork>
          <t>
            An informational response using a 1xx status code other than 101 is transmitted as a
            <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame, followed by zero or more <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref>
            frames.
          </t>
          <t>
            A trailer section is sent as a field block after both the request or response
            field block and all the <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames have been sent.  The
            <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame starting the field block that comprises
            the trailer section has the END_STREAM flag set.
          </t>
          <t keepWithNext="true">
              The following example includes both a 100 (Continue) status code, which is sent in
              response to a request containing a "100-continue" token in the Expect header field,
              and a trailer section:
          </t>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 100 Continue            HEADERS
  Extension-Field: bar       ==>     - END_STREAM
                                     + END_HEADERS
                                       :status = 100
                                       extension-field = bar

  HTTP/1.1 200 OK                  HEADERS
  Content-Type: image/jpeg   ==>     - END_STREAM
  Transfer-Encoding: chunked         + END_HEADERS
  Trailer: Foo                         :status = 200
                                       content-length = 123
  123                                  content-type = image/jpeg
  {binary data}                        trailer = Foo
  0
  Foo: bar                         DATA
                                     - END_STREAM
                                   {binary data}

                                   HEADERS
                                     + END_STREAM
                                     + END_HEADERS
                                       foo = bar
]]></artwork>
        </section>
        <section anchor="Reliability">
          <name>Request Reliability Mechanisms in HTTP/2</name>
          <t>
            In general, an HTTP client is unable to retry a non-idempotent request when an error
            occurs because there is no means to determine the nature of the error.  It is possible
            that some server processing occurred prior to the error, which could result in
            undesirable effects if the request were reattempted.
          </t>
          <t>
            HTTP/2 provides two mechanisms for providing a guarantee to a client that a request has
            not been processed:
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
                The <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frame indicates the highest stream number that might have
                been processed.  Requests on streams with higher numbers are therefore guaranteed to
                be safe to retry.
              </li>
            <li>
                The <xref target="REFUSED_STREAM" format="none">REFUSED_STREAM</xref> error code can be included in a
                <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame to indicate that the stream is being closed prior to
                any processing having occurred.  Any request that was sent on the reset stream can
                be safely retried.
              </li>
          </ul>
          <t>
            Requests that have not been processed have not failed; clients MAY automatically retry
            them, even those with non-idempotent methods.
          </t>
          <t>
            A server MUST NOT indicate that a stream has not been processed unless it can guarantee
            that fact.  If frames that are on a stream are passed to the application layer for any
            stream, then <xref target="REFUSED_STREAM" format="none">REFUSED_STREAM</xref> MUST NOT be used for that stream, and a
            <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> frame MUST include a stream identifier that is greater than or
            equal to the given stream identifier.
          </t>
          <t>
            In addition to these mechanisms, the <xref target="PING" format="none">PING</xref> frame provides a way for a
            client to easily test a connection.  Connections that remain idle can become broken as
            some middleboxes (for instance, network address translators or load balancers) silently
            discard connection bindings.  The <xref target="PING" format="none">PING</xref> frame allows a client to safely
            test whether a connection is still active without sending a request.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="PushResources">
        <name>Server Push</name>
        <t>
          HTTP/2 allows a server to pre-emptively send (or "push") responses (along with
          corresponding "promised" requests) to a client in association with a previous
          client-initiated request.
        </t>
        <t>
          Server push was designed to allow a server to improve client-perceived performance by
          predicting what requests will follow those that it receives, thereby removing a round
          trip for them. For example, a request for HTML is often followed by requests
          for stylesheets and scripts referenced by that page. When these requests
          are pushed, the client does not need to wait to receive the references to them in the HTML
          and issue separate requests.
        </t>
        <t>
          In practice, server push is difficult to use effectively, because it requires the
          server to correctly anticipate the additional requests the client will make, taking into
          account factors such as caching, content negotiation, and user behavior. Errors in
          prediction can lead to performance degradation, due to the opportunity cost that the
          additional data on the wire represents. In particular, pushing any significant amount of
          data can cause contention issues with more-important responses.
        </t>
        <t>
          A client can request that server push be disabled, though this is negotiated for each hop
          independently. The <xref target="SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH" format="none">SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH</xref> setting can be set to 0 to indicate
          that server push is disabled.
        </t>
        <t>
          Promised requests MUST be safe (see <xref target="HTTP" section="9.2.1"/>) and cacheable
          (see <xref target="HTTP" section="9.2.3"/>).  Promised requests cannot include any content or a trailer section. Clients
          that receive a promised request that is not cacheable, that is not known to be safe, or
          that indicates the presence of request content MUST reset the promised stream with a <xref
          target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR"
          format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.  Note this could result in the promised stream being
          reset if the client does not recognize a newly defined method as being safe.
        </t>
        <t>
          Pushed responses that are cacheable (see <xref target="CACHE" section="3"/>) can be stored by the client, if it implements an HTTP
          cache.  Pushed responses are considered successfully validated on the origin server (e.g.,
          if the "no-cache" cache response directive is present; see <xref target="CACHE" section="5.2.2.3"/>) while the stream identified by the
          promised stream ID is still open.
        </t>
        <t>
          Pushed responses that are not cacheable MUST NOT be stored by any HTTP cache. They MAY
          be made available to the application separately.
        </t>
        <t>
          The server MUST include a value in the <tt>:authority</tt> pseudo-header field
          for which the server is authoritative (see <xref target="authority"/>).  A client MUST
          treat a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> for which the server is not authoritative as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          An intermediary can receive pushes from the server and choose not to forward them on to
          the client. In other words, how to make use of the pushed information is up to that
          intermediary. Equally, the intermediary might choose to make additional pushes to the
          client, without any action taken by the server.
        </t>
        <t>
          A client cannot push. Thus, servers MUST treat the receipt of a <xref
          target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame as a <xref
          target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type <xref
          target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>. A server cannot set the <xref
          target="SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH" format="none">SETTINGS_ENABLE_PUSH</xref> setting to a value
          other than 0 (see <xref target="SettingValues"/>).
        </t>
        <section anchor="PushRequests">
          <name>Push Requests</name>
          <t>
            Server push is semantically equivalent to a server responding to a request; however, in
            this case, that request is also sent by the server, as a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>
            frame.
          </t>
          <t>
            The <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame includes a
            field block that contains control data and a complete
            set of request header fields that the server attributes to the request. It is not
            possible to push a response to a request that includes message content.
          </t>
          <t>
            Promised requests are always associated with an explicit request from the client. The
            <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames sent by the server are sent on that explicit
            request's stream. The <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame also includes a promised stream
            identifier, chosen from the stream identifiers available to the server (see <xref target="StreamIdentifiers"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            The header fields in <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> and any subsequent
            <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames MUST be a valid and complete set of <xref target="HttpRequest">request header fields</xref>.  The server MUST include a method in
            the <tt>:method</tt> pseudo-header field that is safe and cacheable.  If a
            client receives a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> that does not include a complete and valid
            set of header fields or the <tt>:method</tt> pseudo-header field identifies
            a method that is not safe, it MUST respond with a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The server SHOULD send <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> (<xref target="PUSH_PROMISE"/>)
            frames prior to sending any frames that reference the promised responses. This avoids a
            race where clients issue requests prior to receiving any <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref>
            frames.
          </t>
          <t>
            For example, if the server receives a request for a document containing embedded links
            to multiple image files and the server chooses to push those additional images to the
            client, sending <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames before the <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames that contain the
            image links ensures that the client is able to see that a resource will be pushed
            before discovering embedded links. Similarly, if the server pushes responses referenced by the field block
            (for instance, in Link header fields), sending a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> before sending the
            header ensures that clients do not request those resources.
          </t>
          <t><xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames MUST NOT be sent by the client.
          </t>
          <t><xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames can be sent by the server in response to any
            client-initiated stream, but the stream MUST be in either the "open" or "half-closed
            (remote)" state with respect to the server.  <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames are
            interspersed with the frames that comprise a response, though they cannot be
            interspersed with <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> and <xref target="CONTINUATION" format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frames that
            comprise a single field block.
          </t>
          <t>
            Sending a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame creates a new stream and puts the stream
            into the "reserved (local)" state for the server and the "reserved (remote)" state for
            the client.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="PushResponses">
          <name>Push Responses</name>
          <t>
            After sending the <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame, the server can begin delivering the
            pushed response as a <xref target="HttpResponse">response</xref> on a server-initiated
            stream that uses the promised stream identifier.  The server uses this stream to
            transmit an HTTP response, using the same sequence of frames as defined in <xref target="HttpSequence"/>.  This stream becomes <xref target="StreamStates">"half-closed"
            to the client</xref> after the initial <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame is sent.
          </t>
          <t>
            Once a client receives a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame and chooses to accept the
            pushed response, the client SHOULD NOT issue any requests for the promised response
            until after the promised stream has closed.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the client determines, for any reason, that it does not wish to receive the pushed
            response from the server or if the server takes too long to begin sending the promised
            response, the client can send a <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frame, using either the
            <xref target="CANCEL" format="none">CANCEL</xref> or <xref target="REFUSED_STREAM" format="none">REFUSED_STREAM</xref> code and referencing the pushed
            stream's identifier.
          </t>
          <t>
            A client can use the <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS</xref> setting to limit the
            number of responses that can be concurrently pushed by a server.  Advertising a
            <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS</xref> value of zero disables server push by
            preventing the server from creating the necessary streams.  This does not prohibit a
            server from sending <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames; clients need to reset any
            promised streams that are not wanted.
          </t>
          <t>
            Clients receiving a pushed response MUST validate that either the server is
            authoritative (see <xref target="authority"/>) or the proxy that provided the pushed
            response is configured for the corresponding request. For example, a server that offers
            a certificate for only the <tt>example.com</tt> DNS-ID
            is not permitted to push a response for <tt>https://www.example.org/doc</tt>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The response for a <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> stream begins with a
            <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame, which immediately puts the stream into the "half-closed
            (remote)" state for the server and "half-closed (local)" state for the client, and ends
            with a frame bearing END_STREAM, which places the stream in the "closed" state.
          </t>
          <aside>
            <t>Note:
              The client never sends a frame with the END_STREAM flag for a server push.
            </t>
          </aside>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="CONNECT">
        <name>The CONNECT Method</name>
        <t>
          In HTTP/1.x, the pseudo-method CONNECT (<xref target="HTTP" section="9.3.6"/>) is
          used to convert an HTTP connection into a tunnel to a remote host.
          CONNECT is primarily used with HTTP proxies to establish a TLS session with an origin
          server for the purposes of interacting with <tt>https</tt> resources.
        </t>
        <t>
          In HTTP/2, the CONNECT method is used to establish a tunnel over a single HTTP/2 stream to
          a remote host for similar purposes. A CONNECT header section is constructed as defined in
          <xref target="HttpRequest"/> ("<xref target="HttpRequest" format="title"/>"), with a few
          differences. Specifically:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
              The <tt>:method</tt> pseudo-header field is set to <tt>CONNECT</tt>.
            </li>
          <li>
              The <tt>:scheme</tt> and <tt>:path</tt> pseudo-header
              fields MUST be omitted.
            </li>
          <li>
              The <tt>:authority</tt> pseudo-header field contains the host and port to
              connect to (equivalent to the authority-form of the request-target of CONNECT
              requests; see <xref target="HTTP11" section="3.2.3"/>).
            </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          A CONNECT request that does not conform to these restrictions is <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          A proxy that supports CONNECT establishes a <xref target="TCP">TCP connection</xref> to
          the host and port identified in the <tt>:authority</tt> pseudo-header field. Once
          this connection is successfully established, the proxy sends a <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref>
          frame containing a 2xx series status code to the client, as defined in <xref target="HTTP" section="9.3.6"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          After the initial <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> frame sent by each peer, all subsequent
          <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames correspond to data sent on the TCP connection.  The frame payload of
          any <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames sent by the client is transmitted by the proxy to the TCP
          server; data received from the TCP server is assembled into <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames by
          the proxy.  Frame types other than <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> or stream management frames
          (<xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>, <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE" format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref>, and <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref>)
          MUST NOT be sent on a connected stream and MUST be treated as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> if received.
        </t>
        <t>
          The TCP connection can be closed by either peer.  The END_STREAM flag on a
          <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame is treated as being equivalent to the TCP FIN bit.  A client is
          expected to send a <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame with the END_STREAM flag set after receiving
          a frame bearing the END_STREAM flag.  A proxy that receives a <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame
          with the END_STREAM flag set sends the attached data with the FIN bit set on the last TCP
          segment.  A proxy that receives a TCP segment with the FIN bit set sends a
          <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame with the END_STREAM flag set.  Note that the final TCP segment
          or <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frame could be empty.
        </t>
        <t>
          A TCP connection error is signaled with <xref target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref>.  A proxy treats any
          error in the TCP connection, which includes receiving a TCP segment with the RST bit set,
          as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream error</xref> of type
          <xref target="CONNECT_ERROR" format="none">CONNECT_ERROR</xref>.  Correspondingly, a proxy MUST send a TCP segment with the
          RST bit set if it detects an error with the stream or the HTTP/2 connection.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="HttpExtra">
      <name>Additional HTTP Requirements/Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This section outlines attributes of the HTTP protocol that improve interoperability, reduce
        exposure to known security vulnerabilities, or reduce the potential for implementation
        variation.
      </t>
      <section>
        <name>Connection Management</name>
        <t>
          HTTP/2 connections are persistent.  For best performance, it is expected that clients will not
          close connections until it is determined that no further communication with a server is
          necessary (for example, when a user navigates away from a particular web page) or until
          the server closes the connection.
        </t>
        <t>
          Clients SHOULD NOT open more than one HTTP/2 connection to a given host and port pair,
          where the host is derived from a URI, a selected <xref target="ALT-SVC">alternative
          service</xref>, or a configured proxy.
        </t>
        <t>
          A client can create additional connections as replacements, either to replace connections
          that are near to exhausting the available <xref target="StreamIdentifiers">stream
          identifier space</xref>, to refresh the keying material for a TLS connection, or to
          replace connections that have encountered <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">errors</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          A client MAY open multiple connections to the same IP address and TCP port using different
          <xref target="TLS-EXT">Server Name Indication</xref> values or to provide different TLS
          client certificates but SHOULD avoid creating multiple connections with the same
          configuration.
        </t>
        <t>
          Servers are encouraged to maintain open connections for as long as possible but are
          permitted to terminate idle connections if necessary.  When either endpoint chooses to
          close the transport-layer TCP connection, the terminating endpoint SHOULD first send a
          <xref target="GOAWAY" format="none">GOAWAY</xref> (<xref target="GOAWAY"/>) frame so that both endpoints can reliably
          determine whether previously sent frames have been processed and gracefully complete or
          terminate any necessary remaining tasks.
        </t>
        <section anchor="reuse">
          <name>Connection Reuse</name>
          <t>
            Connections that are made to an origin server, either directly or through a tunnel
            created using the <xref target="CONNECT">CONNECT method</xref>, MAY be reused for
            requests with multiple different URI authority components.  A connection can be reused
            as long as the origin server is <xref target="authority">authoritative</xref>.  For TCP
            connections without TLS, this depends on the host having resolved to the same IP
            address.
          </t>
          <t>
            For <tt>https</tt> resources, connection reuse additionally depends
            on having a certificate that is valid for the host in the URI.  The certificate
            presented by the server MUST satisfy any checks that the client would perform when
            forming a new TLS connection for the host in the URI.  A single certificate can be
            used to establish authority for multiple origins.  <xref target="HTTP" section="4.3"/>
            describes how a client determines whether a server is authoritative for a URI.
          </t>
          <t>
            In some deployments, reusing a connection for multiple origins can result in requests
            being directed to the wrong origin server.  For example, TLS termination might be
            performed by a middlebox that uses the TLS <xref target="TLS-EXT">Server Name Indication
            (SNI)</xref> extension to select an origin server.  This means that it is possible
            for clients to send requests to servers that might not be the intended
            target for the request, even though the server is otherwise authoritative.
          </t>
          <t>
            A server that does not wish clients to reuse connections can indicate that it is not
            authoritative for a request by sending a 421 (Misdirected Request) status code in response
            to the request (see <xref target="HTTP" section="15.5.20"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            A client that is configured to use a proxy over HTTP/2 directs requests to that proxy
            through a single connection.  That is, all requests sent via a proxy reuse the
            connection to the proxy.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="TLSUsage">
        <name>Use of TLS Features</name>
        <t>
          Implementations of HTTP/2 MUST use <xref target="TLS12">TLS version 1.2</xref> or higher
          for HTTP/2 over TLS.  The general TLS usage guidance in <xref target="TLSBCP"/> SHOULD be
          followed, with some additional restrictions that are specific to HTTP/2.
        </t>
        <t>
          The TLS implementation MUST support the <xref target="TLS-EXT">Server Name Indication
          (SNI)</xref> extension to TLS.  If the server is identified by a <xref
          target="DNS-TERMS">domain name</xref>, clients MUST send the server_name TLS extension
          unless an alternative mechanism to indicate the target host is used.
        </t>
        <t>
          Requirements for deployments of HTTP/2 that negotiate <xref target="TLS13">TLS 1.3</xref>
          are included in <xref target="tls13features"/>.  Deployments of TLS 1.2 are subject to
          the requirements in <xref target="tls12features"/> and <xref target="tls12ciphers"/>.
          Implementations are encouraged to provide defaults that comply, but it is recognized that
          deployments are ultimately responsible for compliance.
        </t>
        <section anchor="tls12features">
          <name>TLS 1.2 Features</name>
          <t>
            This section describes restrictions on the TLS 1.2 feature set that can be used with
            HTTP/2.  Due to deployment limitations, it might not be possible to fail TLS negotiation
            when these restrictions are not met.  An endpoint MAY immediately terminate an HTTP/2
            connection that does not meet these TLS requirements with a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
            <xref target="INADEQUATE_SECURITY" format="none">INADEQUATE_SECURITY</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>
            A deployment of HTTP/2 over TLS 1.2 MUST disable compression.  TLS compression can lead
            to the exposure of information that would not otherwise be revealed <xref target="RFC3749"/>.  Generic compression is unnecessary since HTTP/2 provides
            compression features that are more aware of context and therefore likely to be more
            appropriate for use for performance, security, or other reasons.
          </t>
          <t>
            A deployment of HTTP/2 over TLS 1.2 MUST disable renegotiation.  An endpoint MUST treat
            a TLS renegotiation as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref>
            of type <xref target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.  Note that disabling renegotiation can result in
            long-lived connections becoming unusable due to limits on the number of messages the
            underlying cipher suite can encipher.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint MAY use renegotiation to provide confidentiality protection for client
            credentials offered in the handshake, but any renegotiation MUST occur prior to sending
            the connection preface.  A server SHOULD request a client certificate if it sees a
            renegotiation request immediately after establishing a connection.
          </t>
          <t>
            This effectively prevents the use of renegotiation in response to a request for a
            specific protected resource.  A future specification might provide a way to support this
            use case. Alternatively, a server might use an <xref target="ErrorHandler">
            error</xref> of type <xref target="HTTP_1_1_REQUIRED" format="none">HTTP_1_1_REQUIRED</xref> to request the client
            use a protocol that supports renegotiation.
          </t>
          <t>
            Implementations MUST support ephemeral key exchange sizes of at least 2048 bits for
            cipher suites that use ephemeral finite field Diffie-Hellman (DHE) <xref target="TLS13"/> and 224 bits for cipher suites that use ephemeral elliptic curve
            Diffie-Hellman (ECDHE) <xref target="RFC4492"/>.  Clients MUST accept DHE sizes of up
            to 4096 bits.  Endpoints MAY treat negotiation of key sizes smaller than the lower
            limits as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
            <xref target="INADEQUATE_SECURITY" format="none">INADEQUATE_SECURITY</xref>.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="tls12ciphers">
          <name>TLS 1.2 Cipher Suites</name>
          <t>
            A deployment of HTTP/2 over TLS 1.2 SHOULD NOT use any of the cipher suites that are
            listed in the  <xref target="BadCipherSuites">list of prohibited cipher suites</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Endpoints MAY choose to generate a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection
            error</xref> of type <xref target="INADEQUATE_SECURITY" format="none">INADEQUATE_SECURITY</xref>
            if one of the prohibited cipher suites is negotiated.  A deployment that chooses to use a
            prohibited cipher suite risks triggering a connection error unless the set of potential
            peers is known to accept that cipher suite.
          </t>
          <t>
            Implementations MUST NOT generate this error in reaction to the negotiation of a cipher
            suite that is not prohibited.  Consequently, when clients offer a cipher suite
            that is not prohibited, they have to be prepared to use that cipher suite with
            HTTP/2.
          </t>
          <t>
            The list of prohibited cipher suites includes the cipher suite that TLS 1.2 makes mandatory,
            which means that TLS 1.2 deployments could have non-intersecting sets of permitted cipher
            suites.  To avoid this problem causing TLS handshake failures, deployments of HTTP/2 that use
            TLS 1.2 MUST support TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256 <xref target="TLS-ECDHE"/> with
            the P-256 elliptic curve <xref target="FIPS186"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Note that clients might advertise support of cipher suites that are prohibited in
            order to allow for connection to servers that do not support HTTP/2.  This allows
            servers to select HTTP/1.1 with a cipher suite that is prohibited in HTTP/2.
            However, this can result in HTTP/2 being negotiated with a prohibited cipher suite if
            the application protocol and cipher suite are independently selected.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="tls13features">
          <name>TLS 1.3 Features</name>
          <t>
            TLS 1.3 includes a number of features not available in earlier versions.  This section
            discusses the use of these features.
          </t>
          <t>
            HTTP/2 servers MUST NOT send post-handshake TLS 1.3 CertificateRequest messages.  HTTP/2
            clients MUST treat a TLS post-handshake CertificateRequest message as a <xref
            target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type <xref
            target="PROTOCOL_ERROR" format="none">PROTOCOL_ERROR</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The prohibition on post-handshake authentication applies even if the client offered the
            "post_handshake_auth" TLS extension.  Post-handshake authentication support might be
            advertised independently of <xref target="TLS-ALPN">ALPN</xref>.  Clients might offer
            the capability for use in other protocols, but inclusion of the extension cannot imply
            support within HTTP/2.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="TLS13"/> defines other post-handshake messages, NewSessionTicket and
            KeyUpdate, which can be used as they have no direct interaction with HTTP/2.  Unless the
            use of a new type of TLS message depends on an interaction with the application-layer
            protocol, that TLS message can be sent after the handshake completes.
          </t>
          <t>
            TLS early data MAY be used to send requests, provided that the guidance in <xref
            target="RFC8470"/> is observed.  Clients send requests in early data assuming initial
            values for all server settings.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="authority">
        <name>Server Authority</name>
        <t>
          HTTP/2 relies on the HTTP definition of authority for determining whether a server is
          authoritative in providing a given response (see <xref target="HTTP" section="4.3"/>).
          This relies on local name resolution for the "http" URI scheme and the authenticated server
          identity for the "https" scheme.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Cross-Protocol Attacks</name>
        <t>
          In a cross-protocol attack, an attacker causes a client to initiate a transaction in one
          protocol toward a server that understands a different protocol.  An attacker might be able
          to cause the transaction to appear as a valid transaction in the second protocol.  In
          combination with the capabilities of the web context, this can be used to interact with
          poorly protected servers in private networks.
        </t>
        <t>
          Completing a TLS handshake with an ALPN identifier for HTTP/2 can be considered sufficient
          protection against cross-protocol attacks.  ALPN provides a positive indication that a
          server is willing to proceed with HTTP/2, which prevents attacks on other TLS-based
          protocols.
        </t>
        <t>
          The encryption in TLS makes it difficult for attackers to control the data that could be
          used in a cross-protocol attack on a cleartext protocol.
        </t>
        <t>
          The cleartext version of HTTP/2 has minimal protection against cross-protocol attacks.
          The <xref target="ConnectionHeader">connection preface</xref> contains a string that is
          designed to confuse HTTP/1.1 servers, but no special protection is offered for other
          protocols.  A server that is willing to ignore parts of an HTTP/1.1 request containing an
          Upgrade header field in addition to the client connection preface could be exposed to a
          cross-protocol attack.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Intermediary Encapsulation Attacks</name>
        <t>
          The HTTP/2 field block encoding allows the expression of names that are not valid field
          names in HTTP.  Requests or responses containing
          invalid field names MUST be treated as <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.
          An intermediary therefore cannot translate an HTTP/2 request or response containing an
          invalid field name into an HTTP/1.1 message.
        </t>
        <t>
          Similarly, HTTP/2 allows field values that are not valid.  While most of the values
          that can be encoded will not alter header field parsing, carriage return (CR, ASCII 0xd),
          line feed (LF, ASCII 0xa), and the zero character (NUL, ASCII 0x0) might be exploited by
          an attacker if they are translated verbatim.  Any request or response that contains a
          character not permitted in a field value MUST be treated as <xref target="malformed">malformed</xref>.  Valid characters are defined by the <tt>field-content</tt> ABNF rule in <xref target="HTTP" section="5.5"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Cacheability of Pushed Responses</name>
        <t>
          Pushed responses do not have an explicit request from the client; the request
          is provided by the server in the <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frame.
        </t>
        <t>
          Caching responses that are pushed is possible based on the guidance provided by the origin
          server in the Cache-Control header field.  However, this can cause issues if a single
          server hosts more than one tenant.  For example, a server might offer multiple users each
          a small portion of its URI space.
        </t>
        <t>
          Where multiple tenants share space on the same server, that server MUST ensure that
          tenants are not able to push representations of resources that they do not have authority
          over.  Failure to enforce this would allow a tenant to provide a representation that would
          be served out of cache, overriding the actual representation that the authoritative tenant
          provides.
        </t>
        <t>
          Pushed responses for which an origin server is not authoritative (see
          <xref target="authority"/>) MUST NOT be used or cached.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="dos">
        <name>Denial-of-Service Considerations</name>
        <t>
          An HTTP/2 connection can demand a greater commitment of resources to operate than an
          HTTP/1.1 connection.  The use of field section compression and flow control depend on a
          commitment of resources for storing a greater amount of state.  Settings for these
          features ensure that memory commitments for these features are strictly bounded.
        </t>
        <t>
          The number of <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames is not
          constrained in the same fashion.  A client that accepts server push SHOULD limit the
          number of streams it allows to be in the "reserved (remote)" state.  An excessive number
          of server push streams can be treated as a <xref target="StreamErrorHandler">stream
          error</xref> of type <xref target="ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM"
          format="none">ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          A number of HTTP/2 implementations were found to be vulnerable to denial of service <xref
          target="NFLX-2019-002"/>.  The following lists known ways that implementations might be
          subject to denial of service attack:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            <t>
              Inefficient tracking of outstanding outbound frames can lead to overload if an adversary can
              cause large numbers of frames to be enqueued for sending.  A peer could use one of
              several techniques to cause large numbers of frames to be generated:
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                Providing tiny increments to flow control in <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE"
                format="none">WINDOW_UPDATE</xref> frames can cause a sender to generate a large
                number of <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames.
              </li>
              <li>
                An endpoint is required to respond to a <xref target="PING"
                format="none">PING</xref> frame.
              </li>
              <li>
                Each <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame requires
                acknowledgment.
              </li>
              <li>
                An invalid request (or server push) can cause a peer to send <xref
                target="RST_STREAM" format="none">RST_STREAM</xref> frames in response.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            Large numbers of small or empty frames can be abused to cause a peer to expend time
            processing frame headers.  Caution is required here as some uses of small frames are
            entirely legitimate, such as the sending of an empty <xref target="DATA"
            format="none">DATA</xref> or <xref target="CONTINUATION"
            format="none">CONTINUATION</xref> frame at the end of a stream.
          </li>
          <li>
            The <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> frame might also be abused to
            cause a peer to expend additional processing time.  This might be done by pointlessly
            changing settings, sending multiple undefined settings, or changing the
            same setting multiple times in the same frame.
          </li>
          <li>
            Handling reprioritization with <xref target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref>
            frames can require significant processing time and can lead to overload if many <xref
            target="PRIORITY" format="none">PRIORITY</xref> frames are sent.
          </li>
          <li>
            Field section compression also offers some opportunities to waste processing resources; see
            <xref target="COMPRESSION" section="7"/> for more details on potential abuses.
          </li>
          <li>
            Limits in <xref target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> cannot be reduced
            instantaneously, which leaves an endpoint exposed to behavior from a peer that could
            exceed the new limits. In particular, immediately after establishing a connection,
            limits set by a server are not known to clients and could be exceeded without being an
            obvious protocol violation.
          </li>
          <li>
            An attacker can provide large amounts of flow control credit at the HTTP/2 layer, but
            withhold credit at the TCP layer, preventing frames from being sent.  An endpoint that
            constructs and remembers frames for sending without considering TCP limits might be
            subject to resource exhaustion.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          Most of the features that might be exploited for denial of service -- i.e., <xref
          target="SETTINGS" format="none">SETTINGS</xref> changes, small frames, field section
          compression -- have legitimate uses.  These features become a burden only when they are
          used unnecessarily or to excess.
        </t>
        <t>
          An endpoint that doesn't monitor use of these features exposes itself to a risk of
          denial of service.  Implementations SHOULD track the use of these features and set
          limits on their use.  An endpoint MAY treat activity that is suspicious as a <xref
          target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type <xref
          target="ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM" format="none">ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM</xref>.
        </t>

        <section anchor="MaxFieldBlock">
          <name>Limits on Field Block Size</name>
          <t>
            A large <xref target="FieldBlock">field block</xref> can cause an implementation to
            commit a large amount of state.  Field lines that are critical for routing can appear
            toward the end of a field block, which prevents streaming of fields to their
            ultimate destination.  This ordering and other reasons, such as ensuring cache
            correctness, mean that an endpoint might need to buffer the entire field block.  Since
            there is no hard limit to the size of a field block, some endpoints could be forced to
            commit a large amount of available memory for field blocks.
          </t>
          <t>
            An endpoint can use the <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_HEADER_LIST_SIZE" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_HEADER_LIST_SIZE</xref> to advise peers of
            limits that might apply on the size of uncompressed field blocks.  This setting is only advisory, so
            endpoints MAY choose to send field blocks that exceed this limit and risk having the
            request or response being treated as malformed.  This setting is specific to a
            connection, so any request or response could encounter a hop with a lower, unknown
            limit.  An intermediary can attempt to avoid this problem by passing on values presented
            by different peers, but they are not obliged to do so.
          </t>
          <t>
            A server that receives a larger field block than it is willing to handle can send an
            HTTP 431 (Request Header Fields Too Large) status code <xref target="RFC6585"/>.  A
            client can discard responses that it cannot process.  The field block MUST be processed
            to ensure a consistent connection state, unless the connection is closed.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="connectDos">
          <name>CONNECT Issues</name>
          <t>
            The CONNECT method can be used to create disproportionate load on an proxy, since stream
            creation is relatively inexpensive when compared to the creation and maintenance of a
            TCP connection.  A proxy might also maintain some resources for a TCP connection beyond
            the closing of the stream that carries the CONNECT request, since the outgoing TCP
            connection remains in the TIME_WAIT state.  Therefore, a proxy cannot rely on
            <xref target="SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS" format="none">SETTINGS_MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS</xref> alone to limit the resources consumed by
            CONNECT requests.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Use of Compression</name>
        <t>
          Compression can allow an attacker to recover secret data when it is compressed in the same
          context as data under attacker control.  HTTP/2 enables compression of field lines
          (<xref target="FieldBlock"/>); the following concerns also apply to the use of HTTP
          compressed content-codings (<xref target="HTTP" section="8.4.1"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          There are demonstrable attacks on compression that exploit the characteristics of the web
          (e.g., <xref target="BREACH"/>).  The attacker induces multiple requests containing
          varying plaintext, observing the length of the resulting ciphertext in each, which
          reveals a shorter length when a guess about the secret is correct.
        </t>
        <t>
          Implementations communicating on a secure channel MUST NOT compress content that includes
          both confidential and attacker-controlled data unless separate compression dictionaries
          are used for each source of data.  Compression MUST NOT be used if the source of data
          cannot be reliably determined.  Generic stream compression, such as that provided by TLS,
          MUST NOT be used with HTTP/2 (see <xref target="TLSUsage"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          Further considerations regarding the compression of header fields are described in <xref target="COMPRESSION"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="padding">
        <name>Use of Padding</name>
        <t>
          Padding within HTTP/2 is not intended as a replacement for general purpose padding, such
          as that provided by <xref target="TLS13">TLS</xref>.  Redundant padding could even be
          counterproductive.  Correct application can depend on having specific knowledge of the
          data that is being padded.
        </t>
        <t>
          To mitigate attacks that rely on compression, disabling or limiting compression might be
          preferable to padding as a countermeasure.
        </t>
        <t>
          Padding can be used to obscure the exact size of frame content and is provided to
          mitigate specific attacks within HTTP, for example, attacks where compressed content
          includes both attacker-controlled plaintext and secret data (e.g., <xref target="BREACH"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
          Use of padding can result in less protection than might seem immediately obvious.  At
          best, padding only makes it more difficult for an attacker to infer length information by
          increasing the number of frames an attacker has to observe.  Incorrectly implemented
          padding schemes can be easily defeated.  In particular, randomized padding with a
          predictable distribution provides very little protection; similarly, padding frame payloads to a
          fixed size exposes information as frame payload sizes cross the fixed-sized boundary, which could
          be possible if an attacker can control plaintext.
        </t>
        <t>
          Intermediaries SHOULD retain padding for <xref target="DATA" format="none">DATA</xref> frames but MAY drop padding
          for <xref target="HEADERS" format="none">HEADERS</xref> and <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE" format="none">PUSH_PROMISE</xref> frames.  A valid reason for an
          intermediary to change the amount of padding of frames is to improve the protections that
          padding provides.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
        <t>
          Several characteristics of HTTP/2 provide an observer an opportunity to correlate actions
          of a single client or server over time.  These include the value of settings, the manner
          in which flow-control windows are managed, the way priorities are allocated to streams,
          the timing of reactions to stimulus, and the handling of any features that are controlled by
          settings.
        </t>
        <t>
          As far as these create observable differences in behavior, they could be used as a basis
          for fingerprinting a specific client, as defined in <xref target="PRIVACY" section="3.2"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          HTTP/2's preference for using a single TCP connection allows correlation of a user's
          activity on a site.  Reusing connections for different origins allows tracking
          across those origins.
        </t>
        <t>
          Because the PING and SETTINGS frames solicit immediate responses, they can be used by an
          endpoint to measure latency to their peer.  This might have privacy implications in
          certain scenarios.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        A string for identifying HTTP/2 is entered into the "Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation
        (ALPN) Protocol IDs" registry established in <xref target="TLS-ALPN"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document establishes a registry for frame types, settings, and error codes.  These new
        registries appear in the new "Hypertext Transfer Protocol version 2 (HTTP/2)" section.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document registers the <tt>HTTP2-Settings</tt> header field for
        use in HTTP.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document registers the <tt>PRI</tt> method for use in HTTP to avoid
        collisions with the <xref target="ConnectionHeader">connection preface</xref>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="iana-alpn">
        <name>Registration of HTTP/2 Identification Strings</name>
        <t>
          This document creates two registrations for the identification of HTTP/2 (see <xref target="discover-https"/>) in the
          "Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) Protocol IDs" registry established in <xref target="TLS-ALPN"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The "h2" string identifies HTTP/2 when used over TLS:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Protocol:</dt>
          <dd>HTTP/2 over TLS</dd>
          <dt>Identification Sequence:</dt>
          <dd>0x68 0x32 ("h2")</dd>
          <dt>Specification:</dt>
          <dd>This document</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The "h2c" string identifies HTTP/2 when used over cleartext TCP:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Protocol:</dt>
          <dd>HTTP/2 over TCP</dd>
          <dt>Identification Sequence:</dt>
          <dd>0x68 0x32 0x63 ("h2c")</dd>
          <dt>Specification:</dt>
          <dd>This document</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-frames">
        <name>Frame Type Registry</name>
        <t>
          This document establishes a registry for HTTP/2 frame type codes.  The "HTTP/2 Frame
          Type" registry manages an 8-bit space.  The "HTTP/2 Frame Type" registry operates under
          either of the <xref target="RFC5226">"IETF Review" or "IESG Approval" policies</xref> for
          values between 0x00 and 0xef, with values between 0xf0 and 0xff being reserved for
          Experimental Use.
        </t>
        <t>
          New entries in this registry require the following information:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Frame Type:</dt>
          <dd>
              A name or label for the frame type.
            </dd>
          <dt>Code:</dt>
          <dd>
              The 8-bit code assigned to the frame type.
            </dd>
          <dt>Specification:</dt>
          <dd>
              A reference to a specification that includes a description of the frame layout, its
              semantics, and flags that the frame type uses, including any parts of the frame that
              are conditionally present based on the value of flags.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The entries in the following table are registered by this document.
        </t>
        <table align="left">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Frame Type</th>
              <th>Code</th>
              <th>Section</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>DATA</td>
              <td>0x0</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="DATA"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>HEADERS</td>
              <td>0x1</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="HEADERS"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>PRIORITY</td>
              <td>0x2</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="PRIORITY"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>RST_STREAM</td>
              <td>0x3</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="RST_STREAM"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>SETTINGS</td>
              <td>0x4</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="SETTINGS"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>PUSH_PROMISE</td>
              <td>0x5</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="PUSH_PROMISE"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>PING</td>
              <td>0x6</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="PING"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>GOAWAY</td>
              <td>0x7</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="GOAWAY"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>WINDOW_UPDATE</td>
              <td>0x8</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="WINDOW_UPDATE"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>CONTINUATION</td>
              <td>0x9</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="CONTINUATION"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-settings">
        <name>Settings Registry</name>
        <t>
          This document establishes a registry for HTTP/2 settings.  The "HTTP/2 Settings" registry
          manages a 16-bit space.  The "HTTP/2 Settings" registry operates under the <xref target="RFC5226">"Expert Review" policy</xref> for values in the range from 0x0000 to
          0xefff, with values between and 0xf000 and 0xffff being reserved for Experimental Use.
        </t>
        <t>
          New registrations are advised to provide the following information:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Name:</dt>
          <dd>
              A symbolic name for the setting.  Specifying a setting name is optional.
            </dd>
          <dt>Code:</dt>
          <dd>
              The 16-bit code assigned to the setting.
            </dd>
          <dt>Initial Value:</dt>
          <dd>
              An initial value for the setting.
            </dd>
          <dt>Specification:</dt>
          <dd>
              An optional reference to a specification that describes the use of the setting.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The entries in the following table are registered by this document.
        </t>
        <table align="left">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Name</th>
              <th>Code</th>
              <th>Initial Value</th>
              <th>Specification</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>HEADER_TABLE_SIZE</td>
              <td>0x1</td>
              <td>4096</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="SettingValues"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>ENABLE_PUSH</td>
              <td>0x2</td>
              <td>1</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="SettingValues"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>MAX_CONCURRENT_STREAMS</td>
              <td>0x3</td>
              <td>(infinite)</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="SettingValues"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>INITIAL_WINDOW_SIZE</td>
              <td>0x4</td>
              <td>65535</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="SettingValues"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>MAX_FRAME_SIZE</td>
              <td>0x5</td>
              <td>16384</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="SettingValues"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>MAX_HEADER_LIST_SIZE</td>
              <td>0x6</td>
              <td>(infinite)</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="SettingValues"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-errors">
        <name>Error Code Registry</name>
        <t>
          This document establishes a registry for HTTP/2 error codes.  The "HTTP/2 Error Code"
          registry manages a 32-bit space.  The "HTTP/2 Error Code" registry operates under the
          <xref target="RFC5226">"Expert Review" policy</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Registrations for error codes are required to include a description of the error code.  An
          expert reviewer is advised to examine new registrations for possible duplication with
          existing error codes.  Use of existing registrations is to be encouraged, but not
          mandated.
        </t>
        <t>
          New registrations are advised to provide the following information:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Name:</dt>
          <dd>
              A name for the error code.  Specifying an error code name is optional.
            </dd>
          <dt>Code:</dt>
          <dd>
              The 32-bit error code value.
            </dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt>
          <dd>
              A brief description of the error code semantics, longer if no detailed specification
              is provided.
            </dd>
          <dt>Specification:</dt>
          <dd>
              An optional reference for a specification that defines the error code.
            </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The entries in the following table are registered by this document.
        </t>
        <table align="left">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Name</th>
              <th>Code</th>
              <th>Description</th>
              <th>Specification</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>NO_ERROR</td>
              <td>0x0</td>
              <td>Graceful shutdown</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>PROTOCOL_ERROR</td>
              <td>0x1</td>
              <td>Protocol error detected</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>INTERNAL_ERROR</td>
              <td>0x2</td>
              <td>Implementation fault</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR</td>
              <td>0x3</td>
              <td>Flow-control limits exceeded</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>SETTINGS_TIMEOUT</td>
              <td>0x4</td>
              <td>Settings not acknowledged</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>STREAM_CLOSED</td>
              <td>0x5</td>
              <td>Frame received for closed stream</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>FRAME_SIZE_ERROR</td>
              <td>0x6</td>
              <td>Frame size incorrect</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>REFUSED_STREAM</td>
              <td>0x7</td>
              <td>Stream not processed</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>CANCEL</td>
              <td>0x8</td>
              <td>Stream cancelled</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>COMPRESSION_ERROR</td>
              <td>0x9</td>
              <td>Compression state not updated</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>CONNECT_ERROR</td>
              <td>0xa</td>
              <td>TCP connection error for CONNECT method</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM</td>
              <td>0xb</td>
              <td>Processing capacity exceeded</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>INADEQUATE_SECURITY</td>
              <td>0xc</td>
              <td>Negotiated TLS parameters not acceptable</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>HTTP_1_1_REQUIRED</td>
              <td>0xd</td>
              <td>Use HTTP/1.1 for the request</td>
              <td>
                <xref target="ErrorCodes"/>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>HTTP2-Settings Header Field Registration</name>
        <t>
          This section registers the <tt>HTTP2-Settings</tt> header field in the
          "Permanent Message Header Field Names" registry <xref target="BCP90"/>.
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Header field name:</dt>
          <dd>
              HTTP2-Settings
            </dd>
          <dt>Applicable protocol:</dt>
          <dd>
              http
            </dd>
          <dt>Status:</dt>
          <dd>
              standard
            </dd>
          <dt>Author/Change controller:</dt>
          <dd>
              IETF
            </dd>
          <dt>Specification document(s):</dt>
          <dd><xref target="Http2SettingsHeader"/> of this document
            </dd>
          <dt>Related information:</dt>
          <dd>
              This header field is only used by an HTTP/2 client for Upgrade-based negotiation.
            </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>PRI Method Registration</name>
        <t>
          This section registers the <tt>PRI</tt> method in the "HTTP Method
          Registry" (<xref target="HTTP" section="18.2"/>).
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Method Name:</dt>
          <dd>
              PRI
            </dd>
          <dt>Safe:</dt>
          <dd>
              Yes
            </dd>
          <dt>Idempotent:</dt>
          <dd>
              Yes
            </dd>
          <dt>Specification document(s):</dt>
          <dd><xref target="ConnectionHeader"/> of this document
            </dd>
          <dt>Related information:</dt>
          <dd>
              This method is never used by an actual client. This method will appear to be used
              when an HTTP/1.1 server or intermediary attempts to parse an HTTP/2 connection
              preface.
            </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-h2c">
        <name>The h2c Upgrade Token</name>
        <t>
         This document registers the "h2c" upgrade token in the "HTTP
         Upgrade Tokens" registry (<xref target="HTTP" section="18.10"/>).
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Value:</dt>
          <dd>
             h2c
           </dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt>
          <dd>
             Hypertext Transfer Protocol version 2 (HTTP/2)
           </dd>
          <dt>Expected Version Tokens:</dt>
          <dd>
             None
           </dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt>
          <dd><xref target="discover-http"/> of this document
           </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="COMPRESSION">
          <front>
            <title>HPACK: Header Compression for HTTP/2</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7541"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Peon" fullname="Roberto Peon"/>
            <author initials="H." surname="Ruellan" fullname="Herve Ruellan"/>
            <date month="May" year="2015"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TCP">
          <front>
            <title abbrev="Transmission Control Protocol">
            Transmission Control Protocol
            </title>
            <seriesInfo name="STD" value="7"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="793"/>
            <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
              <organization>University of Southern California (USC)/Information Sciences
            Institute</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="1981" month="September"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC2119">
          <front>
            <title>
            Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels
            </title>
            <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
              <organization>Harvard University</organization>
              <address>
                <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
              </address>
            </author>
            <date month="March" year="1997"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC3986">
          <front>
            <title abbrev="URI Generic Syntax">Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic
          Syntax</title>
            <seriesInfo name="STD" value="66"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986"/>
            <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="Tim Berners-Lee"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding"/>
            <author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter"/>
            <date year="2005" month="January"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC4648">
          <front>
            <title>The Base16, Base32, and Base64 Data Encodings</title>
            <seriesInfo value="4648" name="RFC"/>
            <author fullname="S. Josefsson" initials="S." surname="Josefsson"/>
            <date year="2006" month="October"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC5226">
          <front>
            <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
            <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="26"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5226"/>
            <author initials="T." surname="Narten" fullname="T. Narten"/>
            <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="H. Alvestrand"/>
            <date year="2008" month="May"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC5234">
          <front>
            <title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
            <seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
            <author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker" role="editor"/>
            <author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="P. Overell"/>
            <date year="2008" month="January"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TLS12">
          <front>
            <title>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5246"/>
            <author initials="T." surname="Dierks" fullname="Tim Dierks"/>
            <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="Eric Rescorla"/>
            <date year="2008" month="August"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TLS13">
          <front>
            <title>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.3</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8446"/>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8446"/>
            <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="E. Rescorla"/>
            <date year="2018" month="August" />
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8470">
          <front>
            <title>Using Early Data in HTTP</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8470"/>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8470"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="M. Thomson"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="M. Nottingham"/>
            <author initials="W." surname="Tarreau" fullname="W. Tarreau"/>
            <date year="2018" month="September"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TLS-EXT">
          <front>
            <title>
            Transport Layer Security (TLS) Extensions: Extension Definitions
            </title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6066"/>
            <author initials="D." surname="Eastlake 3rd" fullname="D. Eastlake 3rd"/>
            <date year="2011" month="January"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TLS-ALPN">
          <front>
            <title>Transport Layer Security (TLS) Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation Extension</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7301"/>
            <author initials="S." surname="Friedl" fullname="Stephan Friedl"/>
            <author initials="A." surname="Popov" fullname="Andrei Popov"/>
            <author initials="A." surname="Langley" fullname="Adam Langley"/>
            <author initials="E." surname="Stephan" fullname="Emile Stephan"/>
            <date month="July" year="2014"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TLS-ECDHE">
          <front>
            <title>
            TLS Elliptic Curve Cipher Suites with SHA-256/384 and AES Galois
            Counter Mode (GCM)
            </title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5289"/>
            <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla" fullname="E. Rescorla"/>
            <date year="2008" month="August"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="FIPS186" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.6028/NIST.FIPS.186-4">
          <front>
            <title>
            Digital Signature Standard (DSS)
            </title>
            <seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="PUB 186-4"/>
            <author>
              <organization>NIST</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2013" month="July"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="COOKIE">
          <front>
            <title>HTTP State Management Mechanism</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6265"/>
            <author initials="A." surname="Barth" fullname="A. Barth"/>
            <date year="2011" month="April"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="HTTP">
          <front>
            <title>HTTP Semantics</title>
            <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-semantics-15"/>
            <author fullname="Roy T. Fielding"
                    initials="R."
                    surname="Fielding"
                    role="editor"/>
            <author fullname="Mark Nottingham"
                    initials="M."
                    surname="Nottingham"
                    role="editor"/>
            <author fullname="Julian Reschke"
                    initials="J."
                    surname="Reschke"
                    role="editor"/>
            <date year="2021" month="March" day="30"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CACHE">
          <front>
            <title>HTTP Caching</title>
            <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-cache-15"/>
            <author fullname="Roy T. Fielding"
                    initials="R."
                    surname="Fielding"
                    role="editor"/>
            <author fullname="Mark Nottingham"
                    initials="M."
                    surname="Nottingham"
                    role="editor"/>
            <author fullname="Julian Reschke"
                    initials="J."
                    surname="Reschke"
                    role="editor"/>
            <date year="2021" month="March" day="30"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="HTTP11">
          <front>
            <title>HTTP/1.1</title>
            <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-messaging-15"/>
            <author fullname="Roy T. Fielding"
                    initials="R."
                    surname="Fielding"
                    role="editor"/>
            <author fullname="Mark Nottingham"
                    initials="M."
                    surname="Nottingham"
                    role="editor"/>
            <author fullname="Julian Reschke"
                    initials="J."
                    surname="Reschke"
                    role="editor"/>
            <date year="2021" month="March" day="30"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC7540">
          <front>
            <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol Version 2 (HTTP/2)</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7540"/>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7540"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Belshe" fullname="M. Belshe"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Peon" fullname="R. Peon"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="M. Thomson" role="editor"/>
            <date year="2015" month="May" />
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC8740">
          <front>
            <title>Using TLS 1.3 with HTTP/2</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8740"/>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8740"/>
            <author initials="D." surname="Benjamin" fullname="D. Benjamin"/>
            <date year="2020" month="February" />
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC7323">
          <front>
            <title>
            TCP Extensions for High Performance
            </title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7323"/>
            <author initials="D." surname="Borman" fullname="Dave Borman"/>
            <author initials="B." surname="Braden" fullname="Bob Braden"/>
            <author initials="V." surname="Jacobson" fullname="Van Jacobson"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Scheffenegger" fullname="Richard Scheffenegger" role="editor"/>
            <date year="2014" month="September"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC3749">
          <front>
            <title>Transport Layer Security Protocol Compression Methods</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3749"/>
            <author initials="S." surname="Hollenbeck" fullname="S. Hollenbeck"/>
            <date year="2004" month="May"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC6585">
          <front>
            <title>Additional HTTP Status Codes</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6585"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy Fielding"/>
            <date year="2012" month="April"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC4492">
          <front>
            <title>
            Elliptic Curve Cryptography (ECC) Cipher Suites for Transport Layer Security (TLS)
            </title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4492"/>
            <author initials="S." surname="Blake-Wilson" fullname="S. Blake-Wilson"/>
            <author initials="N." surname="Bolyard" fullname="N. Bolyard"/>
            <author initials="V." surname="Gupta" fullname="V. Gupta"/>
            <author initials="C." surname="Hawk" fullname="C. Hawk"/>
            <author initials="B." surname="Moeller" fullname="B. Moeller"/>
            <date year="2006" month="May"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="PRIVACY">
          <front>
            <title>Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols</title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6973"/>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6973"/>
            <author initials="A." surname="Cooper" fullname="A. Cooper"/>
            <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="H. Tschofenig"/>
            <author initials="B." surname="Aboba" fullname="B. Aboba"/>
            <author initials="J." surname="Peterson" fullname="J. Peterson"/>
            <author initials="J." surname="Morris" fullname="J. Morris"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Hansen" fullname="M. Hansen"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Smith" fullname="R. Smith"/>
            <date year="2013" month="July"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TALKING" target="http://w2spconf.com/2011/papers/websocket.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>
            Talking to Yourself for Fun and Profit
            </title>
            <author initials="L." surname="Huang"/>
            <author initials="E." surname="Chen"/>
            <author initials="A." surname="Barth"/>
            <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla"/>
            <author initials="C." surname="Jackson"/>
            <date year="2011"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="BREACH" target="http://breachattack.com/resources/BREACH%20-%20SSL,%20gone%20in%2030%20seconds.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>
            BREACH: Reviving the CRIME Attack
            </title>
            <author initials="Y." surname="Gluck"/>
            <author initials="N." surname="Harris"/>
            <author initials="A." surname="Prado"/>
            <date year="2013" month="July" day="12"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="BCP90">
          <front>
            <title>Registration Procedures for Message Header Fields</title>
            <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="90"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3864"/>
            <author initials="G." surname="Klyne" fullname="G. Klyne">
              <organization>Nine by Nine</organization>
              <address>
                <email>GK-IETF@ninebynine.org</email>
              </address>
            </author>
            <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="M. Nottingham">
              <organization>BEA Systems</organization>
              <address>
                <email>mnot@pobox.com</email>
              </address>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Mogul" fullname="J. Mogul">
              <organization>HP Labs</organization>
              <address>
                <email>JeffMogul@acm.org</email>
              </address>
            </author>
            <date year="2004" month="September"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TLSBCP">
          <front>
            <title>Recommendations for Secure Use of Transport Layer Security (TLS) and Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS)</title>
            <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="195"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7525"/>
            <author initials="Y." surname="Sheffer" fullname="Yaron Sheffer"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Holz" fullname="Ralph Holz"/>
            <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre"/>
            <date month="May" year="2015"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ALT-SVC">
          <front>
            <title>
            HTTP Alternative Services
            </title>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7838"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
              <organization>Akamai</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="P." surname="McManus" fullname="Patrick McManus">
              <organization>Mozilla</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian Reschke">
              <organization>greenbytes</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2016" month="April"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="DNS-TERMS">
          <front>
            <title>DNS Terminology</title>
            <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="219"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8499"/>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8499"/>
            <author initials="P." surname="Hoffman" fullname="P. Hoffman"/>
            <author initials="A." surname="Sullivan" fullname="A. Sullivan"/>
            <author initials="K." surname="Fujiwara" fullname="K. Fujiwara"/>
            <date year="2019" month="January" />
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="NFLX-2019-002" target="https://github.com/Netflix/security-bulletins/blob/master/advisories/third-party/2019-002.md">
          <front>
            <title>HTTP/2 Denial of Service Advisory</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Netflix</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019" month="August" day="13"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-httpbis-priority.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="BadCipherSuites">
      <name>Prohibited TLS 1.2 Cipher Suites</name>
      <t>
        An HTTP/2 implementation MAY treat the negotiation of any of the following cipher suites
        with TLS 1.2 as a <xref target="ConnectionErrorHandler">connection error</xref> of type
        <xref target="INADEQUATE_SECURITY" format="none">INADEQUATE_SECURITY</xref>:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="compact">
        <li>TLS_NULL_WITH_NULL_NULL</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_NULL_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_EXPORT_WITH_RC4_40_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_RC4_128_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_EXPORT_WITH_RC2_CBC_40_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_IDEA_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_EXPORT_WITH_DES40_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_DES_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_EXPORT_WITH_DES40_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_DES_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_EXPORT_WITH_DES40_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_DES_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_EXPORT_WITH_DES40_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_DES_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_EXPORT_WITH_DES40_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_DES_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_EXPORT_WITH_RC4_40_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_RC4_128_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_EXPORT_WITH_DES40_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_DES_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_WITH_DES_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_WITH_IDEA_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_WITH_DES_CBC_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_WITH_RC4_128_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_WITH_IDEA_CBC_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_EXPORT_WITH_DES_CBC_40_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_EXPORT_WITH_RC2_CBC_40_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_EXPORT_WITH_RC4_40_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_EXPORT_WITH_DES_CBC_40_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_EXPORT_WITH_RC2_CBC_40_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_KRB5_EXPORT_WITH_RC4_40_MD5</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_NULL_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_SEED_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_SEED_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_SEED_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_SEED_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_SEED_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_SEED_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_AES_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_AES_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_AES_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_AES_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_EMPTY_RENEGOTIATION_INFO_SCSV</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_anon_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_anon_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_anon_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_anon_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_anon_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_RSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_DSS_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_DSS_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_SRP_SHA_DSS_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_AES_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_AES_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_AES_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_RC4_128_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_NULL_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_DSS_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_RSA_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_ARIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_ARIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_ARIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_ARIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_ARIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_ARIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_ARIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_ARIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_ARIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_ARIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_ARIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_ARIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_ARIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_ARIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_ARIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_ARIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_ARIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_ARIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_ECDSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_DSS_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DH_anon_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_ECDSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDH_RSA_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_GCM_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_GCM_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_128_CBC_SHA256</li>
        <li>TLS_ECDHE_PSK_WITH_CAMELLIA_256_CBC_SHA384</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CCM</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CCM</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CCM_8</li>
        <li>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CCM_8</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CCM</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CCM</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CCM_8</li>
        <li>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CCM_8</li>
      </ul>
      <aside>
        <t>Note:
          This list was assembled from the set of registered TLS cipher suites at the time of
          writing.  This list includes those cipher suites that do not offer an ephemeral key
          exchange and those that are based on the TLS null, stream, or block cipher type (as
          defined in <xref target="TLS12" section="6.2.3"/>).  Additional cipher suites with
          these properties could be defined; these would not be explicitly prohibited.
        </t>
      </aside>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Changes from RFC 7540</name>
      <t>
        This revision includes a number of editorial updates, plus the following substantive changes:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          Use of TLS 1.3 is defined based on RFC 8740, which this document obsoletes.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section numbered="false">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <t>
        The previous version of this document was authored by Mike Belshe and Roberto Peon.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
        This document includes substantial input from the following individuals:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
            Adam Langley, Wan-Teh Chang, Jim Morrison, Mark Nottingham, Alyssa Wilk, Costin
            Manolache, William Chan, Vitaliy Lvin, Joe Chan, Adam Barth, Ryan Hamilton, Gavin
            Peters, Kent Alstad, Kevin Lindsay, Paul Amer, Fan Yang, and Jonathan Leighton (SPDY
            contributors).
          </li>
        <li>
            Gabriel Montenegro and Willy Tarreau (Upgrade mechanism).
          </li>
        <li>
            William Chan, Salvatore Loreto, Osama Mazahir, Gabriel Montenegro, Jitu Padhye, Roberto
            Peon, and Rob Trace (Flow control).
          </li>
        <li>
            Mike Bishop (Extensibility).
          </li>
        <li><t>
          Mark Nottingham, Julian Reschke, James Snell, Jeff Pinner, Mike Bishop,
          and <contact fullname="Herv Ruellan"/> (Substantial editorial contributions).
        </t></li>
        <li>
            Kari Hurtta, Tatsuhiro Tsujikawa, Greg Wilkins, Poul-Henning Kamp,
            and Jonathan Thackray.
          </li>
        <li>
            Alexey Melnikov, who was an editor of this document in 2013.
        </li>
        <li>
          David Benjamin, who was author of RFC 8740, the contents of which are integrated here.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        A substantial proportion of Martin's contribution was supported by Microsoft during his
        employment there.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Japanese HTTP/2 community provided invaluable contributions,
        including a number of implementations as well as numerous technical and
        editorial contributions.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
