<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-nottingham-http2-encryption-03" category="std">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Opportunistic HTTP Encryption">Opportunistic Encryption for HTTP URIs</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        
        
        <email>mnot@mnot.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
      <organization>Mozilla</organization>
      <address>
        
        
        <email>martin.thomson@gmail.com</email>
        
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2014"/>

    <area>General</area>
    
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This describes how “http” URIs can be accessed using Transport Layer Security (TLS) to mitigate
pervasive monitoring attacks.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>This document describes a use of HTTP Alternative Services <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc"/> to decouple
the URI scheme from the use and configuration of underlying encryption, allowing a “http”
URI to be accessed using TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/> opportunistically.</t>

<t>Currently, “https” URIs requires acquiring and configuring a valid certificate, which means that
some deployments find supporting TLS difficult. Therefore, this document describes a usage model
whereby sites can serve “http” URIs over TLS without being required to support strong server
authentication.</t>

<t>A mechanism for limiting the potential for active attacks is described in <xref target="http-tls"/>. This
provides clients with additional protection against them for a period after successfully connecting
to a server using TLS. This does not offer the same level of protection as afforded to “https”
URIs, but increases the likelihood that an active attack be detected.</t>

<section anchor="goals-and-non-goals" title="Goals and Non-Goals">

<t>The immediate goal is to make the use of HTTP more robust in the face of pervasive passive
monitoring <xref target="RFC7258"/>.</t>

<t>A secondary goal is to limit the potential for active attacks. It is not intended to offer the same
level of protection as afforded to “https” URIs, but instead to increase the likelihood that an
active attack can be detected.</t>

<t>A final (but significant) goal is to provide for ease of implementation, deployment and operation.
This mechanism should have a minimal impact upon performance, and should not require extensive
administrative effort to configure.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="notational-conventions" title="Notational Conventions">

<t>The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”, “SHOULD NOT”,
“RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, and “OPTIONAL” in this document are to be interpreted as described in
<xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="using-http-uris-over-tls" title="Using HTTP URIs over TLS">

<t>An origin server that supports the resolution of HTTP URIs can indicate support for this
specification by providing an alternative service advertisement <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc"/> for a
protocol identifier that uses TLS, such as “h2” <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2"/>, or “https/1.1”
<xref target="RFC2818"/>.</t>

<t>A client that receives such an advertisement MAY direct future requests for the associated origin
to the identified service (as specified by <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc"/>).</t>

<t>A client that places the importance of passive protections over performance might choose to withold
requests until an encrypted connection is available. However, if such a connection cannot be
successfully established, the client MAY resume its use of the cleartext connection.</t>

<t>A client can also explicitly probe for an alternative service advertisement by sending a request
that bears little or no sensitive information, such as one with the OPTIONS method. Clients with
expired alternative services information could make a similar request in parallel to an attempt to
contact an alternative service, to minimize the delays that might be incurred by failing to contact
the alternative service.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="auth" title="Server Authentication">

<t>There are no existing expectations with respect to cryptographically strong server authentication
when it comes to resolving HTTP URIs. Establishing it, as described in <xref target="RFC2818"/>, creates a
number of operational challenges. For these reasons, server authentication is not mandatory for
HTTP URIs when using the mechanism described in this specification.</t>

<t>When connecting to an alternative service for an “http” URI, clients are required to perform the
server authentication procedure described in Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC2818"/>. The server certificate, if
one is proffered by the alternative service, is not necessarily checked for validity, expiration,
issuance by a trusted certificate authority or matched against the name in the URI. Therefore, the
alternative service MAY provide any certificate, or even select TLS cipher suites that do not
include authentication.</t>

<t>A client MAY perform additional checks on the certificate that it is offered (if the server does
not select an unauthenticated TLS cipher suite). For instance, a client could examine the
certificate to see if it has changed over time.</t>

<t>In order to retain the authority properties of “http” URIs, and as stipulated by
<xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc"/>, clients MUST NOT use alternative services that identify a host other
than that of the origin, unless the alternative service indication itself is strongly
authenticated. This is not currently possible for “http” URIs on cleartext transports.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="interaction-with-https-uris" title="Interaction with “https” URIs">

<t>An alternative service that is discovered to support “http” URIs might concurrently support “https”
URIs, because HTTP/2 permits the sending of requests for multiple origins (see <xref target="RFC6454"/>) on the
one connection. Therefore, when using alternative services, both HTTP and HTTPS URIs might be sent
on the same connection.</t>

<t>“https” URIs rely on server authentication. Therefore, if a connection is initially created without
authenticating the server, requests for “https” resources cannot be sent over that connection until
the server certificate is successfully authenticated. Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC2818"/> describes the
basic mechanism, though the authentication considerations in <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc"/> could
also apply.</t>

<t>Connections that are established without any means of server authentication (for instance, the
purely anonymous TLS cipher suites), cannot be used for “https” URIs.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="http-tls" title="Persisting Use of TLS">

<t>Editors’ Note: this is a very rough take on an approach that would provide a limited form of
protection against downgrade attack. It’s unclear at this point whether the additional effort (and
modest operational cost) is worthwhile.</t>

<t>The mechanism described in this specification is trival to mount an active attack against, for two
reasons:</t>

<t><list style='symbols'>
  <t>A client that doesn’t perform authentication an easy victim of server impersonation, through
man-in-the-middle attacks.</t>
  <t>A client that is willing to use cleartext to resolve the resource will do so if access to any
TLS-enabled alternative services is blocked at the network layer.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Given that the primary goal of this specification is to prevent passive attacks, these are of less
concern than they might otherwise be. However, a modest form of protection against these attacks
can be provided for clients on return visits to a server.</t>

<t>This is acheived when a server makes a commitment to providing service over TLS for future
requests, within a bounded period; clients can then rely upon availability of TLS for the
associated origin, and take appropriate steps (e.g., failing) when the server cannot be contacted
safely.</t>

<t>One drawback with this approach is that clients need to strongly authenticate the origin server
to act upon such a commitment; otherwise, an attacker impersonating the origin could create a
persistent denial of service.</t>

<section anchor="the-http-tls-header-field" title="The HTTP-TLS Header Field">

<t>A server makes this commitment by sending a <spanx style='verb'>HTTP-TLS</spanx> header field:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP-TLS     = 1#parameter
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>For example:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/html
Cache-Control: 600
Age: 30
Date: Thu, 1 May 2014 16:20:09 GMT
HTTP-TLS: ma=3600
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>A client that has has not authenticated the server MAY do so when it sees a <spanx style='verb'>HTTP-TLS</spanx> header
field. The server is authenticated as described in Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC2818"/>, noting the
additional requirements in <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc"/>. If server authentication is successful,
the client can persistently store a record that the requested origin <xref target="RFC6454"/> can be retrieved
over TLS.</t>

<t>Persisted information expires after a period determined by the value of the “ma” parameter. See
Section 4.2.3 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-p6-cache"/> for details of determining response age.</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
ma-parameter     = delta-seconds
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Requests for an origin that has a persisted, unexpired value for <spanx style='verb'>HTTP-TLS</spanx> MUST fail if they
cannot be made over an authenticated TLS connection.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="operational-considerations" title="Operational Considerations">

<t>To avoid situations where a persisted value of <spanx style='verb'>HTTP-TLS</spanx> causes a client to be unable to contact a
site, clients SHOULD limit the time that a value is persisted for a given origin. A hard limit
might be set to a month. A lower limit might be appropriate for initial observations of <spanx style='verb'>HTTP-TLS</spanx>;
the certainty that a site has set a correct value - and the corresponding limit on persistence -
can increase as the value is seen more over time.</t>

<t>Once a server has indicated that it will support authenticated TLS, a client MAY use key pinning
<xref target="I-D.ietf-websec-key-pinning"/> or any other mechanism that would otherwise be restricted to use
with HTTPS URIs, provided that the mechanism can be restricted to a single HTTP origin.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<section anchor="security-indicators" title="Security Indicators">

<t>User Agents MUST NOT provide any special security indicia when an “http” resource is acquired using
TLS. In particular, indicators that might suggest the same level of security as “https” MUST NOT be
used (e.g., using a “lock device”).</t>

</section>
<section anchor="downgrade" title="Downgrade Attacks">

<t>A downgrade attack against the negotiation for TLS is possible. With the <spanx style='verb'>HTTP-TLS</spanx> header field,
this is limited to occasions where clients have no prior information (see <xref target="privacy"/>), or when
persisted commitments have expired.</t>

<t>For example, because the <spanx style='verb'>Alt-Svc</spanx> header field <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc"/> likely appears in an
unauthenticated and unencrypted channel, it is subject to downgrade by network attackers. In its
simplest form, an attacker that wants the connection to remain in the clear need only strip the
<spanx style='verb'>Alt-Svc</spanx> header field from responses.</t>

<t>As long as a client is willing to use cleartext TCP to contact a server, these attacks are
possible. The <spanx style='verb'>HTTP-TLS</spanx> header field provides an imperfect mechanism for establishing a
commitment. The advantage is that this only works if a previous connection is established where an
active attacker was not present. A continuously present active attacker can either prevent the
client from ever using TLS, or offer a self-signed certificate. This would prevent the client from
ever seeing the <spanx style='verb'>HTTP-TLS</spanx> header field, or if the header field is seen, from successfully
validating and persisting it.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">

<t>Clients that persist state for origins can be tracked over time based on their use of this
information. Persisted information can be cleared to reduce the ability of servers to track
clients. A browser client MUST clear persisted all alternative service information when clearing
other origin-based state (i.e., cookies).</t>

</section>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>





<reference anchor='RFC2119'>

<front>
<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='17970' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC2818'>

<front>
<title>HTTP Over TLS</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2000' month='May' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo describes how to use Transport Layer Security (TLS) to secure Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) connections over the Internet.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2818' />
<format type='TXT' octets='15170' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2818.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC5246'>

<front>
<title>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Dierks' fullname='T. Dierks'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='August' />
<abstract>
<t>This document specifies Version 1.2 of the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol.  The TLS protocol provides communications security over the Internet.  The protocol allows client/server applications to communicate in a way that is designed to prevent eavesdropping, tampering, or message forgery. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5246' />
<format type='TXT' octets='222395' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5246.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol version 2</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Belshe' fullname='Mike Belshe'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Peon' fullname='Roberto Peon'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Thomson' fullname='Martin Thomson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' day='23' year='2014' />

<abstract><t>This specification describes an optimized expression of the syntax of the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP).  HTTP/2 enables a more efficient use of network resources and a reduced perception of latency by introducing header field compression and allowing multiple concurrent messages on the same connection.  It also introduces unsolicited push of representations from servers to clients.  This document is an alternative to, but does not obsolete, the HTTP/1.1 message syntax.  HTTP's existing semantics remain unchanged.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-12' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-12.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-httpbis-alt-svc'>
<front>
<title>HTTP Alternative Services</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Nottingham' fullname='Mark Nottingham'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='McManus' fullname='Patrick McManus'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Reschke' fullname='Julian Reschke'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' day='1' year='2014' />

<abstract><t>This document specifies "alternative services" for HTTP, which allow an origin's resources to be authoritatively available at a separate network location, possibly accessed with a different protocol configuration.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-httpbis-alt-svc-01' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-httpbis-alt-svc-01.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-httpbis-p6-cache'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Caching</title>

<author initials='R' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy Fielding'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Nottingham' fullname='Mark Nottingham'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Reschke' fullname='Julian Reschke'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='February' day='6' year='2014' />

<abstract><t>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless application- level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems.  This document defines HTTP caches and the associated header fields that control cache behavior or indicate cacheable response messages.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-httpbis-p6-cache-26' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-httpbis-p6-cache-26.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-websec-key-pinning'>
<front>
<title>Public Key Pinning Extension for HTTP</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Evans' fullname='Chris Evans'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Palmer' fullname='Chris Palmer'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Sleevi' fullname='Ryan Sleevi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' day='13' year='2014' />

<abstract><t>This memo describes an extension to the HTTP protocol allowing web host operators to instruct user agents (UAs) to remember ("pin") the hosts' cryptographic identities for a given period of time.  During that time, UAs will require that the host present a certificate chain including at least one Subject Public Key Info structure whose fingerprint matches one of the pinned fingerprints for that host.  By effectively reducing the number of authorities who can authenticate the domain during the lifetime of the pin, pinning may reduce the incidence of man-in-the-middle attacks due to compromised Certification Authorities.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-websec-key-pinning-13' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-websec-key-pinning-13.txt' />
</reference>




    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>





<reference anchor='RFC6454'>

<front>
<title>The Web Origin Concept</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Barth' fullname='A. Barth'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='December' />
<abstract>
<t>This document defines the concept of an "origin", which is often used as the scope of authority or privilege by user agents.  Typically, user agents isolate content retrieved from different origins to prevent malicious web site operators from interfering with the operation of benign web sites.  In addition to outlining the principles that underlie the concept of origin, this document details how to determine the origin of a URI and how to serialize an origin into a string.  It also defines an HTTP header field, named "Origin", that indicates which origins are associated with an HTTP request. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6454' />
<format type='TXT' octets='41363' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6454.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC7258'>

<front>
<title>Pervasive Monitoring Is an Attack</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Farrell' fullname='S. Farrell'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='H. Tschofenig'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='May' />
<abstract>
<t>Pervasive monitoring is a technical attack that should be mitigated in the design of IETF protocols, where possible.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='188' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7258' />
<format type='TXT' octets='13396' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7258.txt' />
</reference>




    </references>


<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>Thanks to Patrick McManus, Eliot Lear, Stephen Farrell, Guy Podjarny, Stephen Ludin, Erik Nygren,
Paul Hoffman, Adam Langley, Eric Rescorla and Richard Barnes for their feedback and suggestions.</t>

</section>


  </back>
</rfc>

