<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='lib/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no"?>
<?rfc editing="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>

<rfc category="info"
    ipr="trust200902"
    docName="draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-latest"
    x:maturity-level="proposed"
    xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">
    <x:feedback template="mailto:ietf-http-wg@w3.org?subject={docname},%20%22{section}%22&amp;body=&lt;{ref}&gt;:"/>
    <front>
        <title abbrev="HPACK">HPACK - Header Compression for HTTP/2.0 </title>

        <author initials="R." surname="Peon" fullname="Roberto Peon">
            <organization>Google, Inc</organization>
            <address>
                <email>fenix@google.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author initials="H." surname="Ruellan" fullname="Hervé Ruellan">
            <organization>Canon CRF</organization>
            <address>
                <email>herve.ruellan@crf.canon.fr</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date year="2013"/>
        <area>Applications</area>
        <workgroup>HTTPbis Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>HTTP</keyword>
        <keyword>Header</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document describes HPACK, a format adapted to efficiently
                represent HTTP header fields in the context of HTTP/2.0.
            </t>
        </abstract>

      <note title="Editorial Note (To be removed by RFC Editor)">
        <t>
          Discussion of this draft takes place on the HTTPBIS working group
          mailing list (ietf-http-wg@w3.org), which is archived at <eref
          target="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/ietf-http-wg/"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Working Group information and related documents can be found at
          <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/wg/httpbis/"/> (Wiki) and <eref
              target="https://github.com/http2/http2-spec"/> (source code and
          issues tracker).
        </t>
        <t>
          The changes in this draft are summarized in <xref
          target="changes.since.draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-03"/>.
        </t>
      </note>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
                This document describes HPACK, a format adapted to efficiently
                represent HTTP header fields in the context of HTTP/2.0 (see <xref
                    target="HTTP2"/>).
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Overview" anchor="overview">
            <t>
                In HTTP/1.X, header fields are sent without any form of
                compression.  As web pages have grown to include dozens to
                hundreds of requests, the redundant header fields in these
                requests now pose a problem of measurable latency and
                unnecessary bandwidth (see <xref target="PERF1"/> and <xref
                    target="PERF2"/>).
            </t>

            <t>
                <xref target="SPDY">SPDY</xref> initially addressed this
                redundancy by compressing header fields with Deflate, which
                proved very effective at eliminating the redundant header
                fields.  However, that aproach exposed a security risk as
                demonstrated by the <xref target="CRIME">CRIME</xref>.
            </t>

            <t>
                In this document, we propose a new compressor for headers
                which eliminates redundant headers, is not vulnerable to CRIME
                style attacks, and which also has a bounded memory cost for
                use in constrained environments.
            </t>

            <section title="Outline">
                <t>
                    The HTTP header field encoding described in this document
                    is based on a header table that map (name, value) pairs to
                    index values.  Header tables are incrementally updated
                    during the HTTP/2.0 session.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The encoder is responsible for deciding which header
                    fields to insert as new entries in the header table.  The
                    decoder then does exactly what the encoder prescribes,
                    ending in a state that exactly matches the encoder's
                    state.  This enables decoders to remain simple and
                    understand a wide variety of encoders.
                </t>
                <t>
                    As two consecutive sets of header fields often have header
                    fields in common, each set of header fields is coded as a
                    difference from the previous set of header fields. The
                    goal is to only encode the changes (header fields present
                    in one of the set and not in the other) between the two
                    sets of header fields.
                </t>
                <t>
                    An example illustrating the use of these different
                    mechanisms to represent header fields is available in
                    <xref target="example"/>.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Header Field Encoding" anchor="header.encoding">
            <section title="Encoding Concepts" anchor="encoding.concepts">
                <t>
                    The encoding and decoding of headers relies on some
                    components and concepts:
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Header Field">
                            A key, value pair.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Header Table:">
                            The header table (see <xref
                                target="header.table"/>) is a component used
                            to associate stored header fields to index values.
                            The data stored in this table is in first-in,
                            first-out order.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Static Table:">
                            The static table (see <xref
                                target="static.table"/>) is a component used
                            to associate static header fields to index values.
                            This data is ordered, read-only, always
                            accessible, and may be shared amongst all encoding
                            contexts.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Reference Set:">
                            The reference set (see <xref
                                target="reference.set"/>) is a component
                            containing an unordered set of references to
                            entries in the header table or static table.
                            This is used for the differential encoding of a new
                            header set.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Header Set:">
                            A header set is a potentially ordered group of
                            header fields that are encoded jointly. A complete
                            set of key-value pairs as encoded in a HTTP
                            request or response is a header set.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Header Representation:">
                            A header can be represented in encoded form either
                            as a literal or as an index (see <xref
                                target="header.representation"/>).
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Header Block:">
                            The entire set of encoded header representations
                            which, when decoded, yield a complete header set.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Header Field Emission:">
                            When decoding a set of header representations, some
                            operations emit a header field (see <xref
                                target="header.emission"/>). All emitted
                            header fields which are considered to be part of
                            the same header set comprise an HTTP request or
                            response.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>

                <section title="Encoding Context" anchor="encoding.context">
                    <t>
                        The set of mutable structures used within an encoding
                        context include a header table and a reference set.
                        Everything else is either immutable or conceptual.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Using HTTP, messages are exchanged between a client
                        and a server in both direction. To keep the encoding
                        of header fields in each direction independent from the
                        other direction, there is one encoding context for
                        each direction.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The header fields contained in a PUSH_PROMISE frame
                        sent by a server to a client are encoded within the
                        same context as the header fields contained in the
                        HEADERS frame corresponding to a response sent from
                        the server to the client.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Table" anchor="header.table">
                    <t>
                        A header table consists of a list of header fields
                        maintained in first-in, first-out order.
                        The first and newest entry in a header table is always
                        at index 0, and the oldest entry of a header table is
                        at the index len(header table)-1.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The header table is initially empty.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        There is typically no need for the header table to
                        contain duplicate entries. However, duplicate entries
                        MUST NOT be treated as an error by a decoder.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The encoder decides how to update the header table and
                        as such can control how much memory is used by the
                        header table. To limit the memory requirements on the
                        decoder side, the header table size is strictly
                        bounded (see <xref target="maximum.table.size"/>).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The header table is updated during the processing of
                        a set of header representations (see <xref
                            target="header.representation.processing"> header
                            representation processing</xref>.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Reference Set" anchor="reference.set">
                    <t>
                        A reference set is an unordered set of references to
                        entries either within the header table or the static
                        table.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The reference set is initially empty.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The reference set is updated during the processing of
                        a set of header representations (see <xref
                            target="header.representation.processing"> header
                            representation processing</xref>.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The reference set enables differential encoding,
                        whereby only differences between the previous header
                        set and the current header set need to be encoded.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Field Representation"
                    anchor="header.representation">
                    <t>
                        A header field can be represented either as a literal
                        or as an index.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="Literal Representation:">
                                A literal representation defines a new header
                                field. The header field name is represented
                                either literally or as a reference to an entry
                                of the header table. The header field value is
                                represented literally.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                Two different literal representations are
                                provided:
                                <list style="symbols">
                                    <t>
                                        A literal representation that does not
                                        add the header field to the header
                                        table (see <xref
                                            target="literal.header.without.indexing"/>).
                                    </t>
                                    <t>
                                        A literal representation that adds the
                                        header field as a new entry at the
                                        beginning of the header table (see
                                        <xref
                                            target="literal.header.with.incremental.indexing"/>).
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="Indexed Representation:">
                                The indexed representation defines a header
                                field as a reference in the header table (see
                                <xref
                                    target="indexed.header.representation"/>).
                                <list>
                                    <t>
                                        Indices between 0 and len(header
                                        table)-1, inclusive, refer to elements
                                        in the header table, with index 0
                                        referring to the beginning of the
                                        table.
                                    </t>
                                    <t>
                                        Indices between len(header table) and
                                        len(header table)+len(static table)-1,
                                        inclusive, refer to elements in the
                                        static table, where the index
                                        len(header table) refers to the first
                                        entry in the static table.
                                    </t>
                                    <t>
                                        Any other indices MUST be treated as
                                        erroneous, and the compression context
                                        considered corrupt and unusable.
                                    </t>
                                    <figure title="Index Address Space">
                                        <artwork type="drawing">
                                            <![CDATA[
       <----------  Index Address Space ---------->
       <-- Header  Table -->  <-- Static  Table -->
       +---+-----------+---+  +---+-----------+---+
       | 0 |    ...    | k |  |k+1|    ...    | n |
       +---+-----------+---+  +---+-----------+---+
       ^                   |
       |                   V
Insertion Point       Drop Point
]]>
                                        </artwork>
                                    </figure>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Field Emission" anchor="header.emission">
                    <t>
                        The emission of header field is the process of passing
                        that header field to the application, so that the
                        application can process and react to header field data.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        By emitting headers instead of emitting header sets,
                        the decoder may be implemented in a streaming way, and
                        as such must only keep in memory the header table and
                        the reference set. This bounds the amount of memory
                        used by the decoder, even in presence of a very large
                        set of header fields. The management of memory for
                        handling very large sets of header fields can
                        therefore be deferred to the application.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section title="Header Block Decoding"
                anchor="header.block.decoding">
                <t>
                    The processing of a header block to obtain a header set is
                    defined in this section.  To ensure that the decoding will
                    successfully produce a header set, a decoder MUST obey the
                    following rules.
                </t>

                <section title="Header Field Representation Processing"
                    anchor="header.representation.processing">
                    <t>
                        All the header field representations contained in a
                        header block are processed in the order in which they
                        are presented, as specified below.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        An <spanx>indexed representation</spanx> corresponding
                        to an entry <spanx>not present</spanx> in the
                        reference set entails the following actions:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>A reference to the entry is added to the
                                reference set.</t>
                            <t>The header field corresponding to the entry is
                                emitted.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        An <spanx>indexed representation</spanx> corresponding
                        to an entry <spanx>present</spanx> in the
                        reference set entails the following actions:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The reference to the entry is removed from the
                                reference set.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A <spanx>literal representation</spanx> that is
                        <spanx>not added</spanx> to the header table entails
                        the following action:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The header field is emitted.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        A <spanx>literal representation</spanx> that is
                        <spanx>added</spanx> to the header table entails
                        the following actions:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>The header field is inserted at the beginning
                                of  the header table.</t>
                            <t>A reference to the new entry is added to the
                                reference set.</t>
                            <t>The header is emitted.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Reference Set Emission"
                    anchor="reference.set.emission">
                    <t>
                        Once all the representations contained in a header
                        block have been processed, the header fields referenced in
                        the reference set which have not previously been
                        emitted during this processing are emitted.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Header Set Completion"
                    anchor="header.set.completion">
                    <t>
                        Once all of the header field representations have been
                        processed, and the remaining items in the reference
                        set have been emitted, the header set is complete.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section title="Header Table Management"
                anchor="header.table.management">
                <section title="Maximum Table Size"
                    anchor="maximum.table.size">
                    <t>
                        To limit the memory requirements on the decoder side,
                        the size of the the header table is bounded. The size
                        of the header table MUST stay lower than or equal to
                        the value of the HTTP/2.0 setting
                        SETTINGS_HEADER_TABLE_SIZE (see <xref
                            target="HTTP2"/>).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The size of the the header table is the sum of the
                        size of its entries.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The size of an entry is the sum of its name's length
                        in bytes (as defined in <xref
                            target="string.literal.representation" />), of its
                        value's length in bytes (<xref
                            target="string.literal.representation" />) and of
                        32 bytes. The 32 bytes are an accounting for the entry
                        structure overhead. For example, an entry structure
                        using two 64-bits pointers to reference the name and
                        the value and the entry, and two 64-bits integer for
                        counting the number of references to these name and
                        value would use 32 bytes.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Entry Eviction" anchor="entry.eviction">
                    <t>
                        Whenever an entry is evicted from the header table,
                        any reference to that entry contained by the reference
                        set is removed.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Whenever SETTINGS_HEADER_TABLE_SIZE is made smaller,
                        entries are evicted from the end of the header table
                        until the size of the header table is less than or
                        equal to SETTINGS_HEADER_TABLE_SIZE.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The eviction of an entry from the header
                        table causes the index of the entries in the static
                        table to be reduced by one.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Entry Addition" anchor="entry.addition">
                    <t>
                        Whenever a new entry is to be added to the table,
                        entries are first evicted from the end of the header
                        table until the size of the header table is less than
                        or equal to SETTINGS_HEADER_TABLE_SIZE - new entry size, or
                        until the table is empty.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the size of the new entry is less than or equal to
                        SETTINGS_HEADER_TABLE_SIZE, that entry is added to the
                        table.  It is not an error to attempt to add an entry
                        that is larger than SETTINGS_HEADER_TABLE_SIZE.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Detailed Format" anchor="detailed.format">
            <section title="Low-level representations"
                anchor="low-level.representation">
                <section title="Integer representation"
                    anchor="integer.representation">
                    <t>
                        Integers are used to represent name indexes, pair
                        indexes or string lengths. To allow for optimized
                        processing, an integer representation always finishes
                        at the end of a byte.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        An integer is represented in two parts: a prefix that
                        fills the current byte and an optional list of bytes
                        that are used if the integer value does not fit in the
                        prefix.  The number of bits of the prefix (called N)
                        is a parameter of the integer representation.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The N-bit prefix allows filling the current byte.  If
                        the value is small enough (strictly less than
                        2<x:sup>N</x:sup>-1), it is encoded within the N-bit
                        prefix.  Otherwise all the bits of the prefix are set
                        to 1 and the value is encoded using an <eref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Variable-length_quantity">
                            unsigned variable length integer</eref>
                        representation.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The algorithm to represent an integer I is as follows:
                        <figure><artwork type = "inline">
If I &lt; 2^N - 1, encode I on N bits
Else
    encode 2^N - 1 on N bits
    I = I - (2^N - 1)
    While I >= 128
         Encode (I % 128 + 128) on 8 bits
         I = I / 128
    encode (I) on 8 bits
                        </artwork></figure>
                    </t>

                    <section title="Example 1: Encoding 10 using a 5-bit prefix"
                        anchor="integer.representation.example1">
                        <t>
                            The value 10 is to be encoded with a 5-bit prefix.
                            <list style="symbols">
                                <t>
                                    10 is less than 31 (= 2<x:sup>5</x:sup> -
                                    1) and is represented using the 5-bit
                                    prefix.
                                </t>
                            </list>
                        </t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| X | X | X | 0 | 1 | 0 | 1 | 0 |   10 stored on 5 bits
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Example 2: Encoding 1337 using a 5-bit prefix"
                        anchor="integer.representation.example2">
                        <t>
                            The value I=1337 is to be encoded with a 5-bit
                            prefix.
                            <list>
                                <t>
                                    1337 is greater than 31 (=
                                    2<x:sup>5</x:sup> - 1).
                                </t>
                                <t>
                                    <list>
                                        <t>The 5-bit prefix is filled with its
                                            max value (31).</t>
                                    </list>
                                </t>
                                <t>I = 1337 - (2<x:sup>5</x:sup> - 1) =
                                    1306.</t>
                                <t>
                                    <list>
                                        <t>I (1306) is greater than or equal
                                            to 128, the while loop body
                                            executes:</t>
                                        <t>
                                            <list>
                                                <t>I % 128 == 26</t>
                                                <t>26 + 128 == 154</t>
                                                <t>154 is encoded in 8 bits as:
                                                    10011010</t>
                                                <t>I is set to 10 (1306 / 128 ==
                                                    10)</t>
                                                <t>I is no longer greater than
                                                    or equal to 128, the while
                                                    loop terminates.</t>
                                            </list>
                                        </t>
                                        <t>
                                            I, now 10, is encoded on 8 bits
                                            as: 00001010
                                        </t>
                                    </list>
                                </t>

                                <t>The process ends.</t>
                            </list>

                        </t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| X | X | X | 1 | 1 | 1 | 1 | 1 |  Prefix = 31, I = 1306
| 1 | 0 | 0 | 1 | 1 | 0 | 1 | 0 |  1306>=128, encode(154), I=1306/128
| 0 | 0 | 0 | 0 | 1 | 0 | 1 | 0 |  10&lt;128, encode(10), done
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </section>
                </section>

                <section title="String Literal Representation"
                    anchor="string.literal.representation">
                    <t>
                        Header field names and header field values are encoded
                        as sequences of bytes. A header field name or a header
                        field value is encoded in two parts:
                        <list style="numbers">
                          <t>The number of bytes in the sequence, represented
                              as a <xref target="integer.representation">
                                  variable-length-quantity </xref>.
                          </t>
                          <t>
                              The sequence of bytes representing the header
                              field name or value.
                          </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section title="Indexed Header Field Representation"
                anchor="indexed.header.representation">
                <t>
                    An indexed header representation either identifies an
                    entry in the header table or static table.  The specified
                    entry is emitted and a reference to that entry is added to
                    the reference set if it is not currently in the reference
                    set. If it is present in the reference set then the
                    reference is removed and the entry is not emitted.
                </t>

                <figure title="Indexed Header">
                    <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 1 |        Index (7+)         |
+---+---------------------------+
</artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    This representation starts with the '1' 1-bit pattern,
                    followed by the index of the matching pair, represented as
                    an integer with a 7-bit prefix.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Literal Header Field Representation"
                anchor="literal.header.representation">
                <t>
                    Literal header field representations contain a literal
                    header field value.  Header field names are either
                    provided as a literal or by reference to an existing
                    header table entry.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Literal representations all result in the emission of a
                    header field when decoded.
                </t>
                <section title="Literal Header Field without Indexing"
                    anchor="literal.header.without.indexing">
                    <t>
                        A literal header field without indexing causes the
                        emission of a header field without altering the header
                        table.
                    </t>
                    <figure title="Literal Header Field without Indexing - Indexed Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 1 |      Index (6+)       |
+---+---+---+-------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <figure title="Literal Header Field without Indexing - New Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 1 |           0           |
+---+---+---+-------------------+
|       Name Length (8+)        |
+-------------------------------+
|  Name String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        This representation starts with the '01' 2-bit pattern.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header name matches the header name of a (name,
                        value) pair stored in the Header Table or Static
                        Table, the index of that entry, increased by one
                        (index + 1), is represented as an integer with a 6-bit
                        prefix.  Note that if the index is strictly below 63,
                        only one byte is used for this representation.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header field name does not match a header field
                        name entry, the value 0 is represented on 6 bits
                        followed by the header field name (<xref
                            target="string.literal.representation" />).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The header field name representation is followed by
                        the header field value represented as a literal string
                        as described in <xref
                            target="string.literal.representation" />.
                    </t>

                </section>

                <section title="Literal Header Field with Incremental Indexing"
                    anchor="literal.header.with.incremental.indexing">
                    <t>
                        A literal header field with incremental indexing adds
                        a new entry to the header table.
                    </t>
                    <figure title="Literal Header Field with Incremental Indexing -
                        Indexed Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 0 |      Index (6+)       |
+---+---+---+-------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <figure title="Literal Header Field with Incremental Indexing -
                        New Name">
                        <artwork type="inline">
  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
| 0 | 0 |           0           |
+---+---+---+-------------------+
|       Name Length (8+)        |
+-------------------------------+
|  Name String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
|       Value Length (8+)       |
+-------------------------------+
| Value String (Length octets)  |
+-------------------------------+
</artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        This representation starts with the '00' 2-bit
                        pattern.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header name matches the header name of a (name,
                        value) pair stored in the header table or static
                        table, the index of the pair increased by one (index +
                        1) is represented as an integer with a 6-bit prefix.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        If the header field name does not match a header field
                        name entry, the value 0 is represented on 6 bits
                        followed by the header field name (<xref
                            target="string.literal.representation" />).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The header field name representation is followed by
                        the header field value represented as a literal string
                        as described in <xref
                            target="string.literal.representation" />.
                    </t>
                </section>
           </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                This compressor exists to solve security issues present in
                stream compressors such as DEFLATE whereby the compression
                context can be efficiently probed to reveal secrets.
                A conformant implementation of this specification should be
                fairly safe against that kind of attack, as the reaping of any
                information from the compression context requires more work than
                guessing and verifying the plaintext data directly with the
                server.  As with any secret, however, the longer the length
                of the secret, the more difficult the secret is to guess. It
                is inadvisable to have short cookies that are relied upon to
                remain secret for any duration of time.
            </t>
            <t>
                A proper security-conscious implementation will also need to
                prevent timing attacks by ensuring that the amount of time it
                takes to do string comparisons is always a function of the
                total length of the strings, and not a function of the number
                of matched characters.
            </t>
            <t>
                Another common security problem is when the remote endpoint
                successfully causes the local endpoint to exhaust its memory.
                This compressor attempts to deal with the most obvious ways
                that this could occur by limiting both the peak and the
                steady-state amount of memory consumed in the compressor
                state, by providing ways for the application to consume/flush
                the emitted header fields in small chunks, and by considering
                overhead in the state size calculation.  Implementors must
                still be careful in the creation of APIs to an implementation
                of this compressor by ensuring that header field keys and
                values are either emitted as a stream, or that the compression
                implementation have a limit on the maximum size of a key or
                value. Failure to implement these kinds of safeguards may
                still result in a scenario where the local endpoint exhausts
                its memory.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <reference anchor="HTTP2">
                <front>
                    <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol version 2.0</title>
                    <author initials="M." surname="Belshe" fullname="Mike Belshe">
                        <organization>Twist</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="R." surname="Peon" fullname="Roberto Peon">
                        <organization>Google</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
                        <organization></organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="A." surname="Melnikov" fullname="Alexey Melnikov">
                        <organization></organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="August" year="2013"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-06"/>
            </reference>
        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">
            <reference anchor="SPDY" target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-mbelshe-httpbis-spdy">
                <front>
                    <title>SPDY Protocol</title>
                    <author initials="M." surname="Belshe" fullname="Mike Belshe">
                        <organization>Twist</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="R." surname="Peon" fullname="Roberto Peon">
                        <organization>Google</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="February" year="2012"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="CRIME" target="https://docs.google.com/a/twist.com/presentation/d/11eBmGiHbYcHR9gL5nDyZChu_-lCa2GizeuOfaLU2HOU/edit#slide=id.g1eb6c1b5_3_6">
                <front>
                    <title>The Crime Attack</title>
                    <author initials="J." surname="Rizzo" fullname="Juliano Rizzo"></author>
                    <author initials="T." surname="Duong" fullname="Thai Duong"></author>
                    <date month="September" year="2012"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="PERF1" target="http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/83/slides/slides-83-httpbis-3">
                <front>
                    <title>IETF83: SPDY and What to Consider for HTTP/2.0</title>
                    <author initials="M." surname="Belshe" fullname="Mike Belshe">
                    </author>
                    <date month="March" year="2012"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="PERF2" target="http://bitsup.blogspot.com/2011/09/spdy-what-i-like-about-you.html">
                <front>
                    <title>SPDY: What I Like About You</title>
                    <author initials="P." surname="McManus" fullname="Patrick McManus">
                    </author>
                    <date month="September" year="2011"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
        </references>


        <section title="Change Log (to be removed by RFC Editor before publication">
            <section title="Since draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-03" anchor="changes.since.draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-03">
                <t><list style="symbols">
                    <t>
                        A large number of editorial changes; changed the
                        description of evicting/adding new entries.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Removed substitution indexing
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Changed 'initial headers' to 'static headers', as per
                        issue #258
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Merged 'request' and 'response' static headers, as per
                        issue #259
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Changed text to indicate that new headers are added at
                        index 0 and expire from the largest index, as per
                        issue #233
                    </t>
                </list></t>
            </section>
            <section title="Since draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-02">
                <t><list style="symbols">
                    <t>
                        Corrected error in integer encoding pseudocode.
                    </t>
                </list></t>
            </section>

            <section title="Since draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-01">
                <t>
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>
                            Refactored of Header Encoding Section: split
                            definitions and processing rule.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Backward incompatible change: Updated
                            reference set management as per issue #214. This
                            changes how the interaction between the reference
                            set and eviction works. This also changes the
                            working of the reference set in some specific
                            cases.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Backward incompatible change: modified initial
                            header list, as per issue #188.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Added example of 32 bytes entry structure (issue
                            #191).
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Added Header Set Completion section.  Reflowed
                            some text. Clarified some writing which was
                            akward.  Added text about duplicate header entry
                            encoding.  Clarified some language w.r.t Header
                            Set.  Changed x-my-header to mynewheader. Added
                            text in the HeaderEmission section indicating that
                            the application may also be able to free up memory
                            more quickly.  Added information in Security
                            Considerations section.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Since draft-ietf-httpbis-header-compression-01">
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>Fixed bug/omission in integer representation algorithm.</t>
                        <t>Changed the document title.</t>
                        <t>Header matching text rewritten.</t>
                        <t>Changed the definition of header emission.</t>
                        <t>Changed the name of the setting which dictates how
                            much memory the compression context should
                            use.</t>
                        <t>Removed "specific use cases" section</t>
                        <t>Corrected erroneous statement about what index can
                            be contained in one byte</t>
                        <t>Added descriptions of opcodes</t>
                        <t>Removed security claims from introduction.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Static Table" anchor="static.table">
            <t>
                The static table consists of an unchangable ordered list of
                (name, value) pairs. The first entry in the table is always
                represented by the index len(header table), and the last entry
                in the table is represented by the index len(header
                table)+len(static table)-1.
            </t>
            <t>
                <cref>
                    The ordering of these tables is currently arbitrary.
                    The tables in this section should be updated and ordered
                    such that the table entries with the smallest indices are
                    those which, based on a statistical analysis of the
                    frequency of use weighted by size, achieve the largest
                    decrease in bytes transmitted subject to HTTP 2.0 header
                    rules (like removal of some headers). This set of headers
                    is currently very likely incomplete, and should be made
                    complete.
                </cref>
                <vspace blankLines="0"/>
            </t>

            <t>
                The following table lists the pre-defined header fields that
                make-up the static header table.
            </t>
            <texttable title="Static Table Entries"
                anchor="static.table.entries">
                <!-- An easy way to renumber these in vim:
                      :let @a=0 | 'a,'bs/>[0-9 ][0-9 ]*</\='>'.(@a+setreg('a',@a+1)).'<'/
                    -->
                    <ttcol>Index</ttcol>
                    <ttcol>Header Name</ttcol>
                    <ttcol>Header Value</ttcol>

                    <c>0</c><c>:host</c><c></c>
                    <c>1</c><c>:method</c><c>GET</c>
                    <c>2</c><c>:method</c><c>POST</c>
                    <c>3</c><c>:path</c><c>/</c>
                    <c>4</c><c>:path</c><c>/index.html</c>
                    <c>5</c><c>:scheme</c><c>http</c>
                    <c>6</c><c>:scheme</c><c>https</c>
                    <c>7</c><c>:status</c><c>200</c>
                    <c>8</c><c>:status</c><c>500</c>
                    <c>9</c><c>:status</c><c>404</c>
                    <c>10</c><c>:status</c><c>403</c>
                    <c>11</c><c>:status</c><c>400</c>
                    <c>12</c><c>:status</c><c>401</c>
                    <c>13</c><c>accept-charset</c><c></c>
                    <c>14</c><c>accept-encoding</c><c></c>
                    <c>15</c><c>accept-language</c><c></c>
                    <c>16</c><c>accept-ranges</c><c></c>
                    <c>17</c><c>accept</c><c></c>
                    <c>18</c><c>access-control-allow-origin</c><c></c>
                    <c>19</c><c>age</c><c></c>
                    <c>20</c><c>allow</c><c></c>
                    <c>21</c><c>authorization</c><c></c>
                    <c>22</c><c>cache-control</c><c></c>
                    <c>23</c><c>content-disposition</c><c></c>
                    <c>24</c><c>content-encoding</c><c></c>
                    <c>25</c><c>content-language</c><c></c>
                    <c>26</c><c>content-length</c><c></c>
                    <c>27</c><c>content-location</c><c></c>
                    <c>28</c><c>content-range</c><c></c>
                    <c>29</c><c>content-type</c><c></c>
                    <c>30</c><c>cookie</c><c></c>
                    <c>31</c><c>date</c><c></c>
                    <c>32</c><c>etag</c><c></c>
                    <c>33</c><c>expect</c><c></c>
                    <c>34</c><c>expires</c><c></c>
                    <c>35</c><c>from</c><c></c>
                    <c>36</c><c>if-match</c><c></c>
                    <c>37</c><c>if-modified-since</c><c></c>
                    <c>38</c><c>if-none-match</c><c></c>
                    <c>39</c><c>if-range</c><c></c>
                    <c>40</c><c>if-unmodified-since</c><c></c>
                    <c>41</c><c>last-modified</c><c></c>
                    <c>42</c><c>link</c><c></c>
                    <c>43</c><c>location</c><c></c>
                    <c>44</c><c>max-forwards</c><c></c>
                    <c>45</c><c>proxy-authenticate</c><c></c>
                    <c>46</c><c>proxy-authorization</c><c></c>
                    <c>47</c><c>range</c><c></c>
                    <c>48</c><c>referer</c><c></c>
                    <c>49</c><c>refresh</c><c></c>
                    <c>50</c><c>retry-after</c><c></c>
                    <c>51</c><c>server</c><c></c>
                    <c>52</c><c>set-cookie</c><c></c>
                    <c>53</c><c>strict-transport-security</c><c></c>
                    <c>54</c><c>transfer-encoding</c><c></c>
                    <c>55</c><c>user-agent</c><c></c>
                    <c>56</c><c>vary</c><c></c>
                    <c>57</c><c>via</c><c></c>
                    <c>58</c><c>www-authenticate</c><c></c>
                </texttable>
            <t>
                The table give the index of each entry in the static table.
                The full index of each entry, to be used for encoding a
                reference to this entry, is computed by adding the number of
                entries in the header table to this index.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Example" anchor="example">
            <t>
                Here is an example that illustrates different representations
                and how tables are updated.
                <cref>This section needs to be updated to better reflect the
                    new processing of header fields, and include more
                    examples.</cref>
            </t>
            <section title="First header set">
                <t>
                    The first header set to represent is the following:
                    <figure><artwork type="message/http">
:path, /my-example/index.html
user-agent, my-user-agent
mynewheader, first
</artwork></figure>
                    The header table is empty, all header fields are
                    represented as literal header fields with indexing.  The
                    'mynewheader' header field name is not in the header table
                    and is encoded literally.  This gives the following
                    representation:
                    <figure><artwork type="message/http">
0x04      (literal header with incremental indexing, name index = 3)
0x16      (header field value string length = 22)
/my-example/index.html
0x0D      (literal header with incremental indexing, name index = 12)
0x0D      (header field value string length = 13)
my-user-agent
0x00      (literal header with incremental indexing, new name)
0x0B      (header field name string length = 11)
mynewheader
0x05      (header field value string length = 5)
first
</artwork></figure>
                    The header table is as follows after the processing of
                    these header fields:
                    <figure><artwork type="inline">
Header table
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|  Index  | Header Name    | Header Value              |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    0    | mynewheader    | first                     | added header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    1    | user-agent     | my-user-agent             | added header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    2    | :path          | /my-example/index.html    | added header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    3    | :scheme        | http                      |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    4    | :scheme        | https                     |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   ...   | ...            | ...                       |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   32    | via            |                           |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
</artwork></figure>
                    As all the header fields in the first header set are
                    indexed in the header table, all are kept in the reference
                    set of header fields, which is:
                    <figure><artwork type="inline">
Reference Set:
:path, /my-example/index.html
user-agent, my-user-agent
mynewheader, first
</artwork></figure>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Second header set">
                <t>
                    The second header set to represent is the following:
                    <figure><artwork type="message/http">
:path, /my-example/resources/script.js
user-agent, my-user-agent
mynewheader, second
</artwork></figure>
                    Comparing this second header set to the reference set, the
                    first and third header fields are from the reference set
                    are not present in this second header set and must be
                    removed. In addition, in this new set, the first and third
                    header fields have to be encoded.  The path header field
                    is represented as a literal header field without indexing.
                    The mynewheader will be represented as a literal header
                    field with incremental indexing.
                    <figure><artwork type="message/http">
0x80       (indexed header, index = 0: removal from reference set)
0x82       (indexed header, index = 2: removal from reference set)
0x43       (literal header, without indexing, name index = 2)
0x1f       (header field value string length = 31)
/my-example/resources/script.js
0x01       (literal header, incremental indexing, name index = 0)
0x06       (header field value string length = 6)
second
</artwork></figure>
                    The header table is updated as follow:
                    <figure><artwork type="inline">
Header table
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|  Index  | Header Name    | Header Value              |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    0    | mynewheader    | second                    | added header
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    1    | mynewheader    | first                     |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    2    | user-agent     | my-user-agent             |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    3    | :path          | /my-example/index.html    |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    4    | :scheme        | http                      |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|    5    | :scheme        | https                     |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   ...   | ...            | ...                       |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
|   33    | via            |                           |
+---------+----------------+---------------------------+
</artwork></figure>
                    All the header fields in this second header set are
                    indexed in the header table, therefore, all are kept in
                    the reference set of header fields, which becomes:
                    <figure><artwork type="inline">
Reference Set:
:path, /my-example/resources/script.js
user-agent, my-user-agent
mynewheader, second
</artwork></figure>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

    </back>
</rfc>
<!--
  vim:et:tw=78:sw=4:
 -->
